Chapter 80: The anatomy of the peripheral nervous system

The peripheral nervous system (PNS) is composed of spinal and cranial nerves, their associated ganglia (autonomic and sensory) and their ramifications that transmit afferent and efferent information between the central nervous system (CNS) and the rest of the body. It also includes the peripheral part of the autonomic nervous system (ANS), notably the sympathetic trunks and the sympathetic and parasympathetic ganglia and their ramifications, and the enteric nervous system (ENS), composed of plexuses of nerve fibres and cell bodies in the wall of the gastrointestinal tract, and the visceral afferent system.

Cranial Nerves

Cranial nerves are the means by which the brain receives information from, and controls the activities of, the head and neck and the thoracic and greater part of the abdominal viscera. There are 12 pairs of cranial nerves, individually named and numbered (Roman numerals) in a rostrocaudal sequence (see Table 24.1). Unlike spinal nerves, only some cranial nerves are mixed in function, i.e. they carry both sensory and motor fibres; others are purely sensory or motor. The first cranial nerve (I; olfactory) has an ancient lineage and is derived from the forerunner of the cerebral hemisphere. It retains this unique position through the connections of the olfactory bulb, and is the only sensory cranial nerve that projects directly to the cerebral cortex rather than indirectly via the thalamus. The areas of cerebral cortex receiving olfactory input have a primitive cellular organization and are an integral part of the limbic system, which is concerned with the emotional aspects of behaviour. The second cranial nerve (II; optic) consists of the axons of second-order visual neurones and these terminate in the thalamus. Most of the component fibres of the other 10 pairs of cranial nerves originate from, or terminate in, named cranial nerve nuclei in the brainstem.

Olfactory nerve

The olfactory nerve is the first cranial nerve and, as its name suggests, is concerned with olfaction (the sense of smell). It is composed of bundles of very small unmyelinated axons derived from olfactory receptor neurones in the olfactory mucosa. The axons are in varying stages of maturity, reflecting the constant turnover of olfactory neurones that takes place in the olfactory epithelium. Bundles of axons are surrounded by olfactory ensheathing cells and form a plexiform network in the subepithelial lamina propria of the mucosa. The bundles unite into as many as 20 branches that cross the cribriform plate of the ethmoid bone in lateral and medial groups, and enter the overlying olfactory bulb, where they end in glomeruli. Each branch is ensheathed by dura mater and pia/arachnoid as it passes through the cribriform plate (see Fig. 39.13A). The dura subsequently becomes continuous with the nasal periosteum, and the pia/arachnoid merges with the connective tissue sheaths that surround the nerve bundles, an arrangement that may facilitate the spread of infection into the cranial cavity from the nasal cavity.

The olfactory bulb is continuous posteriorly with the olfactory tract, through which the output of the bulb projects directly to the ipsilateral retrobulbar area (anterior olfactory nucleus), olfactory tubercle, prepiriform area, amygdala and rostral entorhinal cortex. There is a clear laminar structure in the olfactory bulb (Fig. 32.32A). Different odour molecules are represented by different patterns of spatial activity in the olfactory bulb (Shepherd 2006).

In severe injuries involving the anterior cranial fossa, the olfactory bulb may be separated from the olfactory nerves or the nerves may be torn, producing anosmia, i.e. loss of olfaction. Fractures may involve the meninges, so that cerebrospinal fluid may leak into the nose, resulting in cerebrospinal rhinorrhoea. These injuries open up avenues for intracranial infection from the nasal cavity.

Optic Nerve

The optic nerve is the second cranial nerve and contains the axons of retinal ganglion cells. The two optic nerves join to form the optic chiasma which is usually positioned over the diaphragma sellae and pituitary gland (normofixed), although it may be prefixed (above the tuberculum sellae) or postfixed (above the dorsum sellae). On entering the optic nerve, retinal ganglion cell axons initially maintain their relative retinal positions, with axons from the fovea forming a lateral wedge. This retinotopic mapping is largely maintained within the optic nerve, although nearer the chiasma the foveal axons take a position in the centre of the optic nerve while temporal fibres occupy their previous lateral location. A substantial rearrangement of axons takes place at the chiasma. Most axons arising from the nasal half of a line bisecting the fovea within each retina cross in the chiasma to enter the contralateral optic tract. Fibres from the temporal hemi-retinas do not generally cross in the chiasma.

Th axons within the optic tract were thought to maintain their topographic order and each tract was assumed to be a single representation of the contralateral hemifield. However, it is now clear that axons are mainly organized in functional groupings, larger superficial axons representing the magnocellular pathway and deeper axons originating from midget ganglion cells and forming the parvocellular pathway. This arrangement is chronotopic, the deeper axons developing earlier during axogenesis than the more superficial ones (Reese 1993).

Almost all (90%) of the retinal ganglion cell axons terminate on neurones in the lateral geniculate nucleus. Extrageniculate axons (10%) leave the optic tract before the lateral geniculate nucleus: they may leave the optic chiasma dorsally and project to the suprachiasmatic nucleus of the hypothalamus, or may branch off the optic tract at the superior brachium and project to the superior colliculus, pretectal areas and inferior pulvinar.

The optic nerve is usually described in four parts, intracranial (approximately 10 mm), intracanalicular (approximately 10 mm), intraorbital (25–30 mm), and intraocular (1 mm). The intracranial part arises from the optic chiasma in the suprasellar cistern. It is surrounded by the optic sheath and its dorsal surface is covered by the falciform ligament. The intracanalicular part passes through the optic canal together with the ophthalmic artery: this is the weakest point of the anterior visual pathway because the nerve is fixed to its bony surroundings by fibrous adhesions. The intraorbital part passes forwards, laterally and downwards, and pierces the sclera at the lamina cribrosa, slightly medial to the posterior pole: it has a somewhat tortuous course within the orbit that allows for movements of the eyeball ([Demer 2016]). The subarachnoid space surrounding the intracranial part is continuous with the subarachnoid space around the intracanalicular and intraorbital parts. The dural sheath surrounding the optic nerve originates at the level of the optic canal and accompanies the optic nerve to the sclera. The intraorbital part of optic nerve has important relationships with other orbital structures (see Fig. 44.4). As it leaves the optic canal, it lies superomedial to the ophthalmic artery, and is separated from lateral rectus by the oculomotor, nasociliary and abducens nerves, and sometimes by the ophthalmic veins. It is closely related to the origins of the four recti, whereas more anteriorly, where the muscles diverge, it is separated from them by a substantial amount of orbital fat. Just beyond the optic canal, the ophthalmic artery and the nasociliary nerve cross the optic nerve to reach the medial wall of the orbit. The central artery of the retina enters the substance of the optic nerve about halfway along its length. Near the back of the eyeball, the optic nerve is surrounded by the long and short ciliary nerves and vessels.

Oculomotor Nerve

The oculomotor nerve is the third cranial nerve and innervates levator palpebrae superioris and four of the extraocular muscles (superior, inferior and medial rectus and inferior oblique) (see Fig. 44.15). It also conveys preganglionic parasympathetic fibres from cell bodies in the Edinger–Westphal nucleus that relay in the ciliary ganglion.

Oculomotor nuclear complex

The nuclear complex from which the oculomotor nerve arises consists of several groups of large motor neurones that are collectively designated the oculomotor nucleus, and the smaller preganglionic parasympathetic Edinger–Westphal nucleus (see Figs 28.3, 28.16). The nuclear complex lies at the ventromedial aspect of the periaqueductal grey matter, superior to the trochlear nuclei and is partially enclosed by the fibres of the median longitudinal fasciculi. It is approximately 5 mm long and is divisible into neuronal groups that correlate with the distribution of motor fibres within the oculomotor nerve. Afferent inputs to the oculomotor nuclear complex include fibres from the rostral interstitial nucleus of the medial longitudinal fasciculus and the interstitial nucleus of Cajal, both of which are involved in the control of vertical and torsional gaze. Other inputs come, directly or indirectly, from the nuclei of the posterior commissure and, via these nuclei, from the frontal eye fields, the superior colliculus, the dentate nucleus and cortical areas. The medial longitudinal fasciculus carries afferent connections from the trochlear, abducens and vestibular nuclei.

The fibres from the medial vestibular nucleus project to the medial rectus subnucleus. In order from dorsal to ventral, the oculomotor neurone groups innervate the ipsilateral inferior rectus, inferior oblique and medial rectus. A medially placed column of cells innervates the contralateral superior rectus through axons that decussate in the caudal part of this subnucleus. A median subnucleus of large neurones, designated the caudal central nucleus, lies at the caudal pole of the oculomotor nucleus adjacent to the superior rectus and medial rectus subnuclei. Fascicles of axons from these subnuclei course forwards in the midbrain, through the tegmentum, red nucleus and medial substantia nigra, to emerge as the oculomotor nerve in the interpeduncular fossa. The fascicles are most probably arranged from medial to lateral subserving the pupil, inferior rectus, medial rectus, levator palpebrae superioris and superior rectus, and inferior oblique.

Intra- and extracranial course

For descriptive purposes, the oculomotor nerve is usually divided into cisternal, cavernous and orbital portions: surgically oriented classifications derived from combined microsurgical and endoscopic cadaveric dissection studies have proposed five or seven parts (Iaconetta et al 2010, Park et al 2017).

The cisternal portion of the oculomotor nerve emerges from the midbrain, either through the medial sulcus of the crus cerebri in the caudal part of the interpeduncular fossa or through the medial or the middle part of the crus cerebri. It usually passes forwards and laterally through the interpeduncular cistern between the posterior communicating artery and the superior cerebellar artery: this portion of the nerve is supplied by the P1 and P2 segments of the posterior cerebral artery. The pupilloconstrictor fibres lie superficially on the dorsomedial surface of the cisternal portion of oculomotor nerve, a location that renders them vulnerable to aneurysmal compression (Kerr and Hollowell 1964, Shechtman et al 2007), whereas a pupil-sparing palsy of the oculomotor nerve is pathognomonic of an ischaemic lesion, which tends to involve the central region of the nerve. The oculomotor nerve next passes inferolateral to the posterior communicating artery and inferomedial to the uncus and enters the roof of the cavernous sinus through the oculomotor trigone. This cavernous portion of the nerve passes along the lateral dural wall of the cavernous sinus, dividing into superior and inferior divisions that run beneath the trochlear and ophthalmic nerves. The two divisions enter the orbit through the superior orbital fissure, within the common tendinous ring of the recti, and separated by the nasociliary branch of the ophthalmic nerve.

The superior division of the oculomotor nerve passes above the optic nerve to enter the inferior (ocular) surface of superior rectus. It supplies this muscle and gives off a branch that runs to innervate levator palpebrae superioris. The inferior division of the oculomotor nerve divides into medial, central and lateral branches. The medial branch passes beneath the optic nerve to enter the lateral (ocular) surface of medial rectus; the central branch runs downwards and forwards to enter the superior (ocular) surface of inferior rectus; the lateral branch travels forwards on the lateral side of inferior rectus to enter the orbital surface of inferior oblique and also communicates with the ciliary ganglion to distribute parasympathetic fibres to sphincter pupillae and the ciliary muscle.

Edinger–Westphal nucleus

The Edinger–Westphal nucleus lies dorsal to the main oculomotor nucleus. It is composed of small, multipolar, preganglionic parasympathetic (general visceral efferent, GVE) neurones. Afferent inputs to the nucleus come primarily from the pretectal nuclei bilaterally, mediating the pupillary light reflex, and from the visual cortex, mediating accommodation. Efferent fibres from the nucleus travel in the oculomotor nerve to synapse with postganglionic neurones in the ciliary ganglion (Kozicz et al 2011), and also descend through the medial longitudinal fasciculus to innervate the medial and descending vestibular nuclei (Nieuwenhuys et al 2008).

Trochlear Nerve

The trochlear nerve is the fourth cranial nerve and innervates superior oblique. It has the longest intracranial course and the smallest diameter of all of the cranial nerves, and is also the only cranial nerve to emerge from the dorsal surface of the brainstem, lateral to the lower edge of the inferior colliculus.

Trochlear nucleus

The trochlear nucleus is a small ovoid mass of grey matter just to the side of the midline (see Fig. 28.15). It is bounded by the periaqueductal grey matter dorsally and is enveloped by the fibres of the longitudinal fasciculi ventrally and laterally (Naidich et al 2009). The nucleus is part of the somatic efferent column in line with the oculomotor, abducens and hypoglossal nuclei. Afferent inputs to the trochlear nucleus include fibres from the rostral intermediate nucleus of the medial longitudinal fasciculus and from the interstitial nucleus of Cajal, both of which are involved in the control of vertical and torsional gaze. Other inputs come from the vestibular, abducens and oculomotor nuclei and, directly or indirectly, from the nuclei of the posterior commissure (nuclei of Darkschewitsch and of Cajal) and, via these nuclei, from the superior colliculus, frontal eye fields and other cortical areas. Other afferents arrive from the nucleus prepositus hypoglossi. Efferent trochlear fibres first course dorsally and caudally, just deep to the outer perimeter of the periaqueductal grey matter and medial to the mesencephalic trigeminal nucleus. The trochlear nerves then decussate within the superior medullary velum of the fourth ventricle. A few fibres may remain ipsilateral.

Intra- and extracranial course

The nerves emerge from the dorsal surface of the brainstem just caudal to the inferior colliculus and to each side of the frenulum veli. At the point of emergence, a variable number of rootlets, usually two, unite to form the nerve trunks that curve ventrally through the perimesencephalic cisterns, between the superior cerebellar arteries below and the posterior cerebral arteries above. The cisternal portion of each nerve courses anterolaterally, winding round the cerebral peduncle toward the tentorium cerebelli through the quadrigeminal and ambient cisterns. The nerve passes anteriorly along the infratentorial groove of the tentorium cerebelli and penetrates the roof of the cavernous sinus at the junction of the anterior and posterior petroclinoid dural folds. The cavernous portion continues along the lateral wall of the cavernous sinus below the oculomotor nerve, crossing this nerve at the level of the optic strut to become the most superior structure in the cavernous sinus. The trochlear nerve enters the orbit through the superior orbital fissure outside the common tendinous ring, superior to levator palpebrae superioris and medial to the frontal and lacrimal nerves (see Fig. 44.16). The orbital portion runs medially across levator palpebrae superior and superior rectus to reach superior oblique: its branches typically end on the posterior one-third of the muscle, most often on the medial aspect (Joo and Rhoton 2015).

Trigeminal Nerve

The trigeminal nerve is the fifth cranial nerve and has extensive sensory, motor and autonomic components.

Sensory nuclei and central connections

The trigeminal nerve has three sensory nuclei (spinal tract, principal and mesencephalic) and one motor nucleus. On entering the pons, the fibres of the sensory root of the trigeminal nerve run dorsomedially towards the principal sensory nucleus. About 50% of the fibres divide into ascending and descending branches and the others ascend or descend without division. The descending fibres form the spinal tract of the trigeminal nerve, which terminates in the medially adjacent spinal nucleus of the trigeminal nerve. Some ascending trigeminal fibres, many of them heavily myelinated, synapse around the small neurones in the principal sensory nucleus, which lies lateral to the motor nucleus and medial to the middle cerebellar peduncle, and is continuous inferiorly with the spinal nucleus of the trigeminal nerve. The principal nucleus is considered to be mainly concerned with tactile stimuli. Other ascending fibres enter the mesencephalic nucleus, a column of unipolar cells with peripheral branches that may convey proprioceptive impulses from the masticatory muscles, and possibly also from the teeth, the facial and oculogyric muscles. Its neurones are unique in being the only primary sensory unipolar neurones that have cell bodies in the CNS. It is the relay for the ‘jaw jerk’, the only significant supraspinal monosynaptic reflex. Nerve fibres that ascend to the mesencephalic nucleus may give collaterals to the motor nucleus of the trigeminal nerve and to the cerebellum. Most fibres that arise in the trigeminal sensory nuclei cross the midline, ascend in the trigeminal lemniscus and end in the contralateral ventral posteromedial thalamic nucleus, from which third-order neurones project to the postcentral gyrus (areas 3, 1, 2).

Motor nucleus

The motor nucleus of the trigeminal nerve is ovoid in outline and lies in the upper pontine tegmentum, under the lateral part of the floor of the fourth ventricle. It lies medial to the principal sensory nucleus from which it is separated by fibres of the trigeminal nerve. It forms the rostral part of the pharyngeal (special visceral) efferent column. The motor nucleus contains characteristic large multipolar neurones interspersed with smaller multipolar cells, organized into a number of relatively discrete subnuclei that drive individual muscles. It receives fibres from both corticonuclear tracts. These fibres leave the tracts at the nuclear level or higher in the pons (aberrant corticospinal fibres), descend in the medial lemniscus and may end on motor neurones or interneurones. The motor nucleus receives afferents from the sensory nuclei of the trigeminal nerve, possibly including some from the mesencephalic nucleus, that form monosynaptic reflex arcs for proprioceptive control of the masticatory muscles. It also receives afferents from the reticular formation, red nucleus and tectum, the medial longitudinal fasciculus and possibly from the locus coeruleus. Collectively these represent pathways by which salivary secretion and mastication may be coordinated.

Tensor tympani and stapedius reflex

Loud sound elicits reflex contraction of tensor tympani and stapedius, attenuating movement of the tympanic membrane and the ossicular chain. Afferent impulses travel in the cochlear nerve to the cochlear nuclei in the brainstem. Efferent fibres to tensor tympani arise in the motor nucleus of the trigeminal nerve and travel in the mandibular division of the nerve. Efferent fibres to stapedius originate in the facial nucleus and travel in the facial nerve.

Jaw jerk reflex

The jaw jerk reflex is a deep tendon reflex, elicited by tapping on the midline of the mandible. Rapid stretching of the muscles that close the jaw (masseter, temporalis, medial pterygoid) activates muscle spindle afferents that travel via the mandibular division of the trigeminal nerve to the mesencephalic trigeminal nucleus. Collaterals project monosynaptically to the motor nucleus of the trigeminal nerve in the pons, establishing a two-neurone reflex arc.

Intra- and extracranial course

Embryologically, each division of the trigeminal nerve is associated with a developing facial process that gives rise to a specific area of the adult face: the ophthalmic nerve is associated with the frontonasal process, the maxillary nerve with the maxillary process, and the mandibular nerve with the mandibular process.

Ophthalmic nerve

The ophthalmic division of the trigeminal nerve is a sensory nerve. It arises from the trigeminal ganglion in the middle cranial fossa and passes forwards along the lateral dural wall of the cavernous sinus, giving off three main branches, the lacrimal, frontal and nasociliary nerves, just before it reaches the superior orbital fissure. These branches subsequently travel through the orbit to supply targets that are primarily in the upper part of the face (conjunctiva, skin over the forehead, upper eyelid and much of the external surface of the nose via the supraorbital, lacrimal, infratrochlear and external nasal nerves).

Lacrimal nerve

The lacrimal nerve is the smallest of the main ophthalmic branches. It enters the orbit through the superior orbital fissure, outside the common tendinous ring and lateral to the frontal and trochlear nerves. It passes forwards along the lateral wall of the orbit on the superior border of lateral rectus, and travels through the lacrimal gland and the orbital septum to supply the conjunctiva and skin covering the lateral part of the upper eyelid. The nerve also communicates with the zygomatic branch of the maxillary nerve, which may carry some postganglionic parasympathetic fibres from the pterygopalatine ganglion to the lacrimal gland. Occasionally, the lacrimal nerve is absent, in which case it is replaced by the zygomaticotemporal nerve; the relationship is reciprocal, and when the zygomaticotemporal nerve is absent it is replaced by a branch of the lacrimal nerve. The lacrimal nerve anastomoses with filaments of the facial nerve.

Frontal nerve

The frontal nerve is the largest branch of the ophthalmic nerve. It enters the orbit through the superior orbital fissure outside the common tendinous ring, and lies between the lacrimal nerve laterally and the trochlear nerve medially. It passes forwards towards the rim of the orbit on levator palpebrae superioris, and about halfway along this course it divides into the supraorbital and supratrochlear nerves.

Supraorbital nerve

The supraorbital nerve is the larger of the two terminal branches of the frontal nerve. It continues forwards along levator palpebrae superioris until it leaves the orbit through the supraorbital notch or foramen to emerge onto the forehead. It supplies the mucous membrane that lines the frontal sinus, the conjunctiva and the skin covering the upper eyelid via palpebral branches. It ascends on the forehead with the supraorbital artery, and divides into medial and lateral branches that supply the skin of the scalp nearly as far back as the lambdoid suture. These branches are at first deep to the frontal belly of occipitofrontalis. The medial branch perforates the muscle to reach the skin, while the lateral branch pierces the epicranial aponeurosis. The postganglionic sympathetic fibres that innervate the sweat glands of the supraorbital area probably travel in the supraorbital nerve, having entered the ophthalmic nerve via its communication with the abducens nerve within the cavernous sinus.

Supratrochlear nerve

The supratrochlear nerve is the smaller terminal branch of the frontal nerve. It runs anteromedially in the roof of the orbit, passes above the trochlea for the tendon of superior oblique, and supplies a descending filament to the infratrochlear branch of the nasociliary nerve. The nerve emerges between the trochlea and the supraorbital foramen at the frontal notch, curves up on the forehead close to the bone with the supratrochlear artery, and supplies the conjunctiva and the skin of the upper eyelid. It then ascends beneath corrugator and the frontal belly of occipitofrontalis before dividing into branches that pierce these muscles to supply the skin of the lower forehead near the midline.

Nasociliary nerve

The nasociliary nerve is intermediate in size between the frontal and lacrimal nerves. It is more deeply placed in the orbit, which it enters through the common tendinous ring, lying between the two rami of the oculomotor nerve. It crosses the optic nerve with the ophthalmic artery and runs obliquely below superior rectus and superior oblique to reach the medial orbital wall, where it gives off the anterior and posterior ethmoidal nerves. The nasociliary nerve has long ciliary and infratrochlear branches and a connection with the ciliary ganglion.

Anterior ethmoidal nerve

The anterior ethmoidal nerve passes through the anterior ethmoidal foramen and canal and enters the cranial cavity. It runs forwards in a groove on the upper surface of the cribriform plate beneath the dura mater, descends through a slit lateral to the crista galli into the nasal cavity, where it occupies a groove on the internal surface of the nasal bone, and supplies the roof of the nasal cavity. It gives off medial and lateral internal nasal branches that supply the anterior and upper parts of the septum and the anterior part of the lateral wall, respectively, before emerging at the inferior margin of the nasal bone as the external nasal nerve, which descends through the lateral wall of the nose and supplies the skin of the nose below the nasal bones to the nasal tip but excluding the alar portion around the external nares: damage following nasal trauma may result in paraesthesia of the nasal tip.

Posterior ethmoidal nerve

The posterior ethmoidal nerve leaves the orbit by the posterior ethmoidal foramen and supplies the ethmoidal and sphenoidal sinuses.

Infratrochlear nerve

The infratrochlear nerve leaves the orbit below the trochlea and supplies the skin of the eyelids, the conjunctiva, lacrimal sac, lacrimal caruncle and the side of the nose above the medial canthus.

Long ciliary nerves

Two or three long ciliary nerves branch from the nasociliary nerve as it crosses the optic nerve. They accompany the short ciliary nerves, pierce the sclera near the attachment of the optic nerve, and run forwards between the sclera and choroid. They supply the ciliary body, iris and cornea, and contain postganglionic sympathetic fibres for dilator pupillae from neurones in the superior cervical ganglion. An alternative pathway for the supply of the dilator pupillae is via the sympathetic root associated with the ciliary ganglion.

Ramus communicans to the ciliary ganglion

The ramus communicans to the ciliary ganglion usually branches from the nasociliary nerve as the latter enters the orbit lateral to the optic nerve. It is sometimes joined by a filament from the internal carotid sympathetic plexus or from the superior ramus of the oculomotor nerve as it enters the posterosuperior angle of the ganglion.

Maxillary nerve

The maxillary division of the trigeminal nerve is a sensory nerve. It leaves the skull via the foramen rotundum and enters the upper part of the pterygopalatine fossa where many of its extracranial branches are given off. It crosses the pterygopalatine fossa, giving off two large ganglionic branches that contain fibres destined for the nose, palate and pharynx and that all pass through the pterygopalatine ganglion without synapsing. The maxillary nerve then inclines sharply laterally on the posterior surface of the orbital process of the palatine bone and on the upper part of the posterior surface of the maxilla in the inferior orbital fissure (which is continuous posteriorly with the pterygopalatine fossa): it lies outside the orbital periosteum, and gives off zygomatic, and then posterior superior alveolar branches. About halfway between the orbital apex and the orbital rim, the maxillary nerve turns medially to enter the infraorbital canal as the infraorbital nerve. Named branches from the main trunk are meningeal, ganglionic, zygomatic, posterior, middle and anterior superior alveolar and infraorbital nerves. Named branches from the pterygopalatine ganglion are orbital, nasopalatine, posterior superior nasal, greater (anterior) palatine, lesser (posterior) palatine and pharyngeal nerves.

Meningeal nerve

The meningeal branch of the maxillary nerve arises within the middle cranial fossa and runs with the middle meningeal vessels. It contributes to the innervation of the dura mater (see Fig. 25.3B).

Ganglionic branches

Two ganglionic branches usually connect the maxillary nerve to the pterygopalatine ganglion.

Zygomatic nerve

The zygomatic branch of the maxillary nerve leaves the pterygopalatine fossa through the inferior orbital fissure with the maxillary nerve and lies close to the base of the lateral wall of the orbit. Soon after entering the orbit the nerve divides into two branches, the zygomaticotemporal and the zygomaticofacial nerves, which run within the orbit for only a short distance before passing onto the face through the lateral wall of the orbit. They may enter separate canals within the zygomatic bone or the zygomatic nerve itself may enter the bone before dividing.

Zygomaticotemporal nerve

The zygomaticotemporal nerve traverses a canal in the zygomatic bone and emerges into the anterior part of the temporal fossa, where it ascends between the bone and temporalis before piercing the temporal fascia about 2 cm above the zygomatic arch to supply the skin of the temple. It communicates with the facial and auriculotemporal nerves. As it pierces the deep layer of the temporal fascia, it sends a slender twig between the two layers of the fascia towards the lateral angle of the eye. It was thought that the branch carried parasympathetic postganglionic fibres from the pterygopalatine ganglion to the lacrimal gland, but it is now believed that these fibres innervate the lacrimal gland directly.

Zygomaticofacial nerve

The zygomaticofacial nerve traverses the inferolateral angle of the orbit and emerges on the face through a foramen in the zygomatic bone. It perforates orbicularis oculi to supply the skin on the prominence of the cheek and forms a plexus with zygomatic branches of the facial nerve and palpebral branches of the maxillary nerve. The nerve is absent occasionally.

Infraorbital nerve

The infraorbital nerve can be regarded as the terminal branch of the maxillary nerve. It leaves the pterygopalatine fossa to enter the orbit at the inferior orbital fissure and at first it lies in the infraorbital groove on the floor of the orbit. As it approaches the rim of the orbit it runs into the infraorbital canal through which it passes to emerge onto the face at the infraorbital foramen, where it lies between levator labii superioris and levator anguli oris. It gives off palpebral, nasal and superior labial branches. The palpebral branches ascend deep to orbicularis oculi, pierce the muscle to supply the skin in the lower eyelid, and join the facial and zygomaticofacial nerves near the lateral canthus. Nasal branches supply the skin of the side of the nose, the vestibule and the movable part of the nasal septum, and join the external nasal branch of the anterior ethmoidal nerve. Superior labial branches, which are large and numerous, descend behind levator labii superioris to supply the skin of the anterior part of the cheek and upper lip. They are joined by branches from the facial nerve to form the infraorbital plexus.

Orbital branches

Fine orbital branches enter the orbit through the inferior orbital fissure and supply orbital periosteum. Some fibres also pass through the posterior ethmoidal foramen to supply the sphenoidal and ethmoidal sinuses. The orbital branches probably join branches of the internal carotid nerve to form a ‘retro-orbital’ plexus from which orbital structures such as the lacrimal gland and orbitalis receive an autonomic innervation.

Posterior superior nasal nerves (lateral and medial)

The posterior superior alveolar nerves enter the back of the nasal cavity through the sphenopalatine foramen. Lateral posterior superior nasal nerves innervate the mucosa covering the posterior part of the superior and middle nasal turbinates (conchae) and lining the posterior ethmoidal sinuses. Two or three medial posterior superior nasal nerves cross the nasal roof below the opening of the sphenoidal sinus to supply the mucosa of the posterior part of the roof and of the nasal septum.

Nasopalatine nerve

The nasopalatine nerve leaves the pterygopalatine fossa through the sphenopalatine foramen and enters the nasal cavity. It passes across the cavity to the back of the nasal septum, runs downwards and forwards on the septum in a groove in the vomer, and then turns down through the incisive fossa in the anterior part of the hard palate to enter the roof of the mouth. When an anterior and a posterior incisive foramen exist in this fossa, the left nasopalatine nerve typically passes through the anterior foramen, and the right nerve passes through the posterior foramen. The nasopalatine nerve supplies the inferior part of the nasal septum and the anterior part of the hard palate, where it communicates with the greater palatine nerve.

Surgical division of the nasopalatine nerve, for example during the removal of an ectopic canine tooth, causes no obvious sensory deficit in the anterior part of the palate, which suggests that either the territory of the greater palatine nerve reaches as far forwards as the gingivae lingual to the incisor teeth or that the nasopalatine nerve has significant regenerative potential.

Palatine nerves (greater and lesser)

The greater and lesser palatine nerves pass downwards from the pterygopalatine ganglion through the greater palatine canal. The greater palatine nerve descends through the greater palatine canal, emerges on the hard palate from the greater palatine foramen and runs forwards in a groove on the inferior surface of the bony palate almost to the incisor teeth. It supplies the gingivae, mucosa and glands of the hard palate and also communicates with the terminal filaments of the nasopalatine nerve. In the greater palatine canal it gives off posterior inferior nasal branches that emerge through the perpendicular plate of the palatine bone and ramify over the inferior nasal turbinate (concha) and walls of the middle and inferior meatuses. As it leaves the greater palatine canal, it gives off branches which are distributed to both surfaces of the adjacent part of the soft palate.

The lesser (middle and posterior) palatine nerves are much smaller than the greater palatine nerve. They descend through the greater palatine canal, from which they diverge low down to emerge through the lesser palatine foramina in the tubercle or pyramidal process of the palatine bone. They innervate the uvula, tonsil and soft palate.

Fibres conveying taste impulses from the palate probably pass via the palatine nerves to the pterygopalatine ganglion. They pass through the ganglion without synapsing, and leave via the greater petrosal nerve. Their cell bodies are located in the facial ganglion and their central processes pass via the sensory root of the facial nerve (nervus intermedius) to the gustatory nucleus in the nucleus of the tractus solitarius.

Pharyngeal nerve

The pharyngeal branch of the maxillary nerve leaves the pterygopalatine ganglion posteriorly. It passes through the palatovaginal canal with the pharyngeal branch of the maxillary artery and supplies the mucosa of the nasopharynx behind the pharyngotympanic tube.

Superior alveolar nerves

The teeth in the upper jaw are supplied by the three superior alveolar (dental) nerves that arise from the maxillary nerve either in the pterygopalatine fossa or in the infraorbital groove and canal.

The posterior superior alveolar (dental) nerve leaves the maxillary nerve in the pterygopalatine fossa and runs anteroinferiorly to pierce the infratemporal surface of the maxilla, at which point it is possible to perform a local anaesthetic block that will anaesthetize the pulps of the premolar and molar ipsilateral teeth; it then descends under the mucosa of the maxillary sinus. After supplying the lining of the sinus, the nerve divides into small branches that link up as the molar part of the superior alveolar plexus, supplying twigs to the molar teeth. It also supplies a branch to the upper molar gingivae and the adjoining part of the cheek.

The middle superior alveolar (dental) nerve arises from the infraorbital nerve as it runs in the infraorbital groove, and runs downwards and forwards in the lateral wall of the maxillary sinus. It ends in small branches that link up with the superior dental plexus, supplying small rami to the upper premolar teeth. This nerve is variable; it may be duplicated, triplicated, or absent.

The anterior superior alveolar (dental) nerve leaves the lateral side of the infraorbital nerve near the midpoint of its canal and traverses the canalis sinuosus in the anterior wall of the maxillary sinus. It curves first under the infraorbital foramen, then passes medially towards the nose, and finally turns downwards and divides into branches to supply the incisor and canine teeth. It assists in the formation of the superior dental plexus and gives off a nasal branch that passes through a minute canal in the lateral wall of the inferior meatus to supply the mucous membrane of the anterior area of the lateral wall as high as the opening of the maxillary sinus, and the floor of the nasal cavity near the anterior nasal spine. It communicates with the nasal branches of the pterygopalatine ganglion and finally emerges near the root of the anterior nasal spine to supply the adjoining part of the nasal septum.

Mandibular nerve

The mandibular division of the trigeminal nerve is the largest division of the trigeminal nerve and is a mixed nerve. Its sensory branches supply the mandibular teeth and gingivae, the skin in the temporal region, part of the auricle and the lower lip, the lower part of the face and the mucosa of the anterior two-thirds (presulcal part) of the tongue and the floor of the oral cavity. The motor branches innervate the muscles of mastication, tensor veli palatini, tensor tympani, anterior belly of digastric and mylohyoid. The large sensory root emerges from the lateral part of the trigeminal ganglion and exits the cranial cavity through the foramen ovale. The small motor root passes under the ganglion and through the foramen ovale to unite with the sensory root just outside the skull. As it descends from the foramen ovale, the mandibular nerve is usually around 4 cm from the surface and a little anterior to the neck of the mandible. It immediately passes between tensor veli palatini, which is medial, and lateral pterygoid, which is lateral, gives off a meningeal branch and the nerve to medial pterygoid from its medial side, and then divides into a small anterior and large posterior trunk. The anterior trunk gives off branches to the four main muscles of mastication and a buccal branch which is sensory to the cheek. The posterior trunk gives off three main sensory branches, the auriculotemporal, lingual and inferior alveolar nerves, and motor fibres to supply mylohyoid and the anterior belly of digastric.

Meningeal branch (nervus spinosus)

The meningeal branch re-enters the middle cranial fossa through the foramen spinosum with the middle meningeal artery. It divides into anterior and posterior branches that accompany the main divisions of the middle meningeal artery and supply the dura mater in the middle cranial fossa and, to a lesser extent, in the anterior fossa and calvaria (see Fig. 25.3B).

Nerve to medial pterygoid

The nerve to medial pterygoid is a slender ramus that enters the deep aspect of the muscle. It supplies one or two filaments that pass through the otic ganglion without interruption to supply tensor tympani and tensor veli palatini.

Anterior trunk of mandibular nerve

The anterior trunk of the mandibular nerve gives rise to the buccal nerve, which is sensory, and the masseteric, deep temporal and lateral pterygoid nerves, which are all motor.

Buccal nerve

The buccal nerve passes between the two heads of lateral pterygoid, giving off motor fibres to the muscle as it passes through it. The nerve then descends deep to the tendon of temporalis, passes laterally anterior to masseter, and anastomoses with the buccal branches of the facial nerve. It may give off the anterior deep temporal nerve. The buccal nerve supplies sensation to the skin over the anterior part of buccinator, the corresponding buccal mucous membrane and the posterior part of the buccal gingivae opposite the second and third molar teeth. It may also give off a branch that passes through a small retromolar foramen to supply the molar teeth.

Nerve to masseter

The nerve to masseter passes laterally above lateral pterygoid onto the skull base, anterior to the temporomandibular joint and posterior to the tendon of temporalis. It crosses the posterior part of the mandibular notch with the masseteric artery and ramifies on and enters the deep surface of masseter. It provides articular branches to the temporomandibular joint.

Deep temporal nerves

There are usually two deep temporal nerves, anterior and posterior, although there may be a middle branch. They pass above lateral pterygoid to enter the deep surface of temporalis. The anterior branch may arise as a branch of the buccal nerve or from the nerve to masseter; the small posterior nerve sometimes arises in common with the nerve to masseter. Branches from the buccal nerve and the nerve to masseter may supply the inferior aspect of temporalis independently from the deep temporal nerves.

Nerve to lateral pterygoid

The nerve to lateral pterygoid enters the deep surface of the muscle. It may arise separately from the anterior division of the mandibular nerve or from the buccal nerve.

Posterior trunk of mandibular nerve

The posterior trunk of the mandibular nerve is larger than the anterior and is mainly sensory, although it receives fibres from the motor root for the nerve to mylohyoid. It divides into auriculotemporal, lingual and inferior alveolar (dental) nerves.

Auriculotemporal nerve

The auriculotemporal nerve usually has two roots that encircle the middle meningeal artery. It runs back under lateral pterygoid on the surface of tensor veli palatini, passes between the sphenomandibular ligament and the neck of the mandible, and then runs laterally behind the temporomandibular joint related to the upper part of the parotid gland. Emerging from behind the joint, it ascends over the posterior root of the zygoma, posterior to the superficial temporal vessels, and divides into superficial temporal branches. It communicates with the facial nerve and otic ganglion. The rami to the facial nerve, usually two, pass anterolaterally behind the neck of the mandible to join the facial nerve at the posterior border of masseter. Filaments from the otic ganglion join the roots of the auriculotemporal nerve close to their origin. The auriculotemporal nerve emerges onto the face behind the temporomandibular joint within the superior surface of the parotid gland, ascends posterior to the superficial temporal vessels, passes over the posterior root of the zygoma, and divides into superficial temporal branches. The cutaneous branches of the auriculotemporal nerve supply the tragus and part of the adjoining auricle of the ear and the posterior part of the temple. The nerve may be damaged during parotid gland surgery, resulting in impaired sensation over the tragus and temple. The auriculotemporal nerve communicates with the temporofacial division of the facial nerve, usually by two rami that pass anterolaterally behind the neck of the mandible. These communications anchor the facial nerve close to the lateral surface of the condylar process of the mandible and limit its mobility during surgery. Communications with the temporal and zygomatic branches of the facial nerve loop around the transverse facial and superficial temporal vessels.

Lingual nerve

The lingual nerve is sensory to the mucosa of the floor of the mouth, mandibular lingual gingivae and mucosa of the presulcal part of the tongue (excluding the circumvallate papillae, which are supplied by the glossopharyngeal nerve). It also carries postganglionic parasympathetic fibres from the submandibular ganglion to the sublingual and anterior lingual glands. It arises from the posterior trunk of the mandibular nerve and at first runs beneath lateral pterygoid and superficial to tensor veli palatini, where it is joined by the chorda tympani branch of the facial nerve, and often by a branch of the inferior alveolar nerve. Emerging from under cover of lateral pterygoid, the lingual nerve then runs downwards and forwards on the surface of medial pterygoid, and is thus carried progressively closer to the medial surface of the mandibular ramus. It becomes intimately related to the bone a few millimetres below and behind the junction of the vertical ramus and horizontal body of the mandible. Here it lies anterior to, and slightly deeper than, the inferior alveolar (dental) nerve. It next passes below the mandibular attachment of the superior pharyngeal constrictor and pterygomandibular raphe, closely applied to the periosteum of the medial surface of the mandible, until it lies opposite the posterior root of the lower third molar tooth, where it is covered only by the gingival mucoperiosteum. At this point it usually lies approximately 3 mm below the alveolar crest with a mean distance from the bone of 2 mm: it may be in direct contact with the bone (25%) or lie above the alveolar crest (15%). The nerve next passes medial to the mandibular origin of mylohyoid, and this carries it progressively away from the mandible, separating it from the alveolar bone covering the mesial root of the lower third molar tooth. It then passes downwards and forwards on the deep surface of mylohyoid (i.e. the surface nearer the mucosa covering the floor of the mouth), crossing the lingual sulcus beneath the mucosa. In this position, the lingual nerve lies on the deep portion of the submandibular gland, which bulges over the top of the posterior border of mylohyoid. The nerve passes below the submandibular duct, which crosses it from medial to lateral, and curves upwards, forwards and medially to enter the tongue by medial and lateral branches. Within the tongue, the medial branch sends small branches to the medial part of the ventrolateral tongue, and the lateral branch runs along the lateral border of the tongue and sends larger branches to innervate the mucosa of the anterior tip of the tongue. The lingual nerve is connected to the submandibular ganglion by two or three branches. It forms connecting loops with twigs of the hypoglossal nerve at the anterior margin of hyoglossus (Fitzgerald and Law 1958) and within the tongue (Zur et al 2004).

The lingual nerve is at risk during surgical removal of (impacted) lower third molars: patients occasionally develop lingual sensory disturbance postoperatively but this is rarely persistent ([Renton 2011]). The nerve is also at risk during operations to remove the submandibular salivary gland because the submandibular duct must be dissected from the lingual nerve, and also because its connection to the submandibular ganglion pulls it into the operating field.

Inferior alveolar (dental) nerve

The inferior alveolar nerve descends behind lateral pterygoid. At the lower border of the muscle the nerve passes between the sphenomandibular ligament and the mandibular ramus and enters the mandibular canal via the mandibular foramen. Just before entering the mandibular canal, the inferior alveolar nerve gives off a small mylohyoid branch that also carries fibres that innervate the anterior belly of digastric. Below lateral pterygoid, the nerve is accompanied by the inferior alveolar artery, a branch of the first part of the maxillary artery, which enters the canal with its associated veins. In the mandibular canal, the inferior alveolar nerve runs downwards and forwards, generally below the apices of the teeth until it is below the first and second premolars, where it divides into terminal incisive and mental branches. The incisive branch continues forwards in a bony canal or in a plexiform arrangement, giving off branches to the first premolar, canine and incisor teeth, and to the associated labial gingivae. The lower central incisor teeth receive a bilateral innervation, fibres probably crossing the midline within the periosteum to re-enter the bone via numerous canals in the labial cortical plate. The mental nerve passes upwards, backwards and outwards to emerge from the mandible via the mental foramen between and just below the apices of the premolar teeth. It immediately divides into three branches, two of which pass upwards and forwards to form an incisor plexus labial to the teeth that supplies the labial gingivae (and probably the periosteum). From this plexus and from the dental branches, fibres turn downwards and then lingually to emerge on the lingual surface of the mandible on the posterior aspect of the mental symphysis or opposite the premolar teeth, probably communicating with the lingual or mylohyoid nerves. The third branch of the mental nerve passes through the intermingled fibres of depressor anguli oris and platysma to supply the skin of the lower lip and chin. Branches of the mental nerve communicate with terminal filaments of the mandibular branch of the facial nerve.

Nerve to mylohyoid

The nerve to mylohyoid is given off from the inferior alveolar nerve just before that nerve enters the mandibular canal. It pierces the sphenomandibular ligament and enters a shallow groove on the medial surface of the mandible, following a course roughly parallel to its parent nerve. It passes below the origin of mylohyoid to lie on the superficial surface of the muscle, between it and the anterior belly of digastric, both of which it supplies. Although primarily a motor nerve supplying mylohyoid and the anterior belly of digastric, the mylohyoid nerve carries some sensory fibres that may enter the mandible via one or more small retromental foramina in the vicinity of the genial tubercles to supply some sensation to the anterior teeth, and it may also give a few filaments to supply the skin over the point of the chin.

Dental extractions

Variations in the fascicular organization of the inferior alveolar nerve are clinically important when extracting impacted third molars. The nerve may appear as a single bundle lying a few millimetres below the roots of the teeth, or it may lie much lower and almost reach the lower border of the bone, so that it gives off a variable number of large rami that pass anterosuperiorly towards the roots before dividing to supply the teeth and interdental septa. Only rarely is it plexiform. The nerve may lie on the lingual or buccal side of the mandible (slightly more commonly on the buccal side). Even when the third molar tooth is in a normal position, the nerve may be so intimately related to it that it grooves its root. Exceptionally, the nerve may be similarly related to the second molar tooth.

Failure to achieve complete anaesthesia to the mandibular teeth following an inferior alveolar nerve block (which should anaesthetize the nerve before it enters the mandibular canal) suggests that there are alternative pathways for sensory nerves to innervate the teeth. Knowledge of these pathways is important in helping clinicians to obtain complete dental anaesthesia. There are anatomical variations in the distribution of the inferior alveolar nerve, the buccal branch of the mandibular nerve, the mylohyoid nerve, the lingual nerve, the deep temporal nerves and the cervical plexus. The inferior alveolar nerve may give multiple branches before entering the mandibular canal that may re-enter the mandible via small accessory foramina in the retromolar region to supply sensation to the molar teeth: one or more of these branches may escape anaesthesia following inferior alveolar nerve block. If a successful inferior alveolar nerve block does not completely anaesthetize teeth in a jaw quadrant, additional local injections of anaesthetic solution around the tooth in question may be necessary to block alternative pathways. There is also the possibility of overlap across the midline involving the incisive and mylohyoid nerves. In children, there is evidence to suggest that the lingula is variable in position and its position from the occlusion plane increases with age: it is therefore not considered an appropriate landmark for inferior alveolar nerve block.

Neural connections between branches of trigeminal and other nerves

Communications exist between the inferior alveolar and lingual nerves. If the lingual nerve is not anaesthetized during an inferior alveolar nerve block, this pathway could account for any remaining sensation in the teeth. Although the deep temporal nerves are primarily motor, it has been suggested that terminal branches may pass from the substance of temporalis to enter the mandible through foramina in the retromolar region to supply some sensation to molar teeth. In the cervical plexus, the great auricular nerve, formed by the anterior primary rami of the second and third cervical spinal nerves, supplies skin over the angle of the mandible: it is possible that this nerve may provide a branch that penetrates the mandible to supply one or more of the cheek teeth.

Abducens Nerve

The abducens nerve is the sixth cranial nerve and innervates the ipsilateral lateral rectus.

Abducens nucleus and central connections

The abducens nucleus lies in the floor of the fourth ventricle, just lateral to the midline, immediately subjacent to the facial colliculus and slightly lateral to the medial longitudinal fasciculus (see Fig. 28.4). The abducens nucleus is composed of approximately 6500 neurones that align with the trochlear, oculomotor and hypoglossal nuclei to form the general somatic efferent column (GSE). Within the nucleus, large motor neurones are intermixed with small multipolar interneurones, the latter being most heavily concentrated in the lateral and ventral aspects of the nucleus. The abducens nucleus receives afferent connections from multiple sources, including corticonuclear fibres (principally contralateral, some of the fibres are aberrant corticospinal fibres that descend from the midbrain to this level in the medial lemniscus); the medial longitudinal fasciculus (connecting the abducens nucleus to oculomotor, trochlear and vestibular nuclei); the tectobulbar tract (from the deep layers of the superior colliculus); the paramedian pontine reticular formation (rostral and caudal to the nucleus); the nucleus prepositus hypoglossi; and the contralateral medullary reticular formation.

Neural Control of Gaze

Although the detailed anatomical substrates for the different types of eye movement differ, they share common neural circuitry that lies mainly in the pons and midbrain, for horizontal and vertical gaze movements, respectively (see Fig. 44.12). The common element for all types of horizontal gaze movements is the abducens nucleus. It contains motor neurones that innervate the ipsilateral lateral rectus and interneurones that project via the medial longitudinal fasciculus to the contralateral oculomotor nucleus, which controls medial rectus. A lesion of the abducens nucleus leads to a total loss of ipsilateral horizontal conjugate gaze. A lesion of the medial longitudinal fasciculus produces slowed or absent adduction of the ipsilateral eye, usually associated with jerky movements (nystagmus) of the contralateral abducting eye, a syndrome called internuclear ophthalmoplegia (Leigh and Zee 2015). The gaze motor command involves specialized areas of the reticular formation of the brainstem, which receive a variety of supranuclear inputs. The main region for the generation of horizontal saccades is the paramedian pontine reticular formation, located on each side of the midline in the central paramedian part of the tegmentum, and extending from the pontomedullary junction to the pontopeduncular junction. Each paramedian pontine reticular formation contains excitatory neurones (referred to as ‘burst’ neurones) that discharge at high frequencies just prior to and during ipsilateral saccades. Excitatory burst neurones make monosynaptic connections with the ipsilateral abducens nucleus. Omnipause neurones in the pontine nucleus raphe interpositus, located in the midline between the rootlets of the abducens nerves, discharge tonically during fixation but stop firing immediately prior to a saccade. They appear to exert an inhibitory influence on the burst neurones and act as a switch to change from fixation to saccadic mode (Ramat et al 2007).

The tonic activity of neurones in the nucleus prepositus hypoglossi and medial vestibular nucleus is thought to provide an eye position signal to maintain the eccentric position of the eye against the viscoelastic forces in the orbit. These forces tend to move the eyeball back to looking straight ahead, i.e. the primary position, after a saccade. Vestibular nuclei and the perihypoglossal complex project directly to the abducens nuclei: these projections probably also carry smooth pursuit signals, via the cerebellum.

The final common pathway for vertical gaze movements is formed by the oculomotor and trochlear nuclei. The rostral interstitial nucleus of the medial longitudinal fasciculus contains both excitatory burst neurones that discharge in relation to up-and-down vertical saccadic movements and project to motor neurones involved in vertical gaze, and omnipause neurones that act similarly to those for horizontal gaze. The rostral interstitial nucleus of the medial longitudinal fasciculus projects through the posterior commissure to its equivalent on the other side of the mesencephalon for upgaze, as well as directly to the ipsilateral oculomotor and trochlear nuclei for downgaze (see Fig. 44.12). Neurones in and around the interstitial nucleus of Cajal, which lies slightly caudal to the rostral interstitial nucleus of the medial longitudinal fasciculus, provide signals for vertical gaze holding. Vertical gaze palsies can affect upgaze, downgaze or both. Lesions within the posterior commissure predominantly give rise to disturbances in upgaze, associated with other signs of dorsal midbrain syndrome, e.g. pupillary abnormalities (light–near dissociation). Discrete lesions placed more ventrally in the region of the rostral interstitial nucleus of the medial longitudinal fasciculus may cause mixed up-and-down, or mainly downgaze disturbances (Leigh and Zee 2015).

Intra- and extracranial course

The axons of the motor neurones in the abducens nucleus spread diffusely from the ventromedial aspect of the nucleus. Fifteen to twenty fascicles pass ventrally, laterally and caudally, directly through the intervening reticular formation, trapezoid body, medial lemniscus, pontocerebellar fibres, pontine nuclei and descending corticospinal tracts to emerge from the brainstem at the pontomedullary sulcus about 1–2 cm lateral to the midline. In their course, the rootlets typically coalesce to emerge from the brainstem as a compact bundle of fibres. Occasionally all or some of the rootlets may emerge rostral to the pontomedullary sulcus. The nerve runs upward, anteriorly and slightly laterally across the prepontine cistern between the pons and clivus, pierces the inner layer of dura mater and runs through the inferior venous compartment of the petroclival venous confluence in a bow-shaped canal, Dorello’s canal. It then bends sharply across the upper border of the petrous part of the temporal bone to enter the cavernous sinus, where it lies lateral to the cavernous segment of the internal carotid artery but medial to the oculomotor, trochlear, ophthalmic and maxillary nerves that also course through the sinus (but merely invaginate the lateral dural wall of the sinus). The abducens nerve enters the orbit through the inferomedial part of the superior orbital fissure, within the common tendinous ring, at first below, and then between, the two divisions of the oculomotor nerve and lateral to the nasociliary nerve (see Fig. 44.15). It passes forwards to enter the medial (ocular) surface of lateral rectus, most often in the posterior one-third of the muscle (Joo et al 2012).

Facial nerve

The facial nerve is the seventh cranial nerve. It contains special visceral/branchial efferent (SVE) motor axons that supply muscles derived from the second branchial arch, namely the mimetic facial muscles, buccinator, stapedius, platysma, the posterior belly of digastric and stylohyoid. The craniofacial muscles innervated by the facial nerve typically lack muscle spindles: proprioceptive information may be mediated by modified cutaneous mechanoreceptors or capsular corpuscle-like structures within the muscles. The facial nerve contains two, possibly three, types of sensory axon. Special visceral afferent (SVA) axons carry taste from the anterior two-thirds of the tongue via the chorda tympani, and general sensory afferent (GSA) axons carry cutaneous sensation, including pain, from the posterior aspect of the external acoustic meatus, with the caveat that the innervation of this region is complex and largely contributed by Arnold’s nerve: these axons are thought to be responsible for coughing during cerumen removal, idiopathic otalgia, Hitselberger’s sign and to be the site of vesicular eruptions in Ramsay Hunt syndrome.

General visceral efferent (GVE) fibres in the facial nerve arise from preganglionic parasympathetic neurones in the superior salivatory nucleus and pass via either the chorda tympani to the submandibular ganglion or the greater petrosal nerve and the nerve of the pterygoid canal to the pterygopalatine ganglion. The GVE, SVA, GSA axons form the nervus intermedius (intermediate nerve, nerve of Wrisberg).

Facial nucleus and central connections

The facial (motor) nucleus is situated caudal, ventral and lateral to the abducens nucleus. It lies within the caudal pontine reticular formation, ventromedial to the spinal tract and nucleus of the trigeminal nerve (see Figs 28.11, 28.13) (Haines and Mihailoff 2017). Groups of neurones form columns that innervate individual muscles or that correspond to branches of the facial nerve. The facial nucleus receives corticonuclear fibres for volitional control of the facial musculature. Within the nucleus, neurones that innervate the muscles of the scalp and upper face are innervated by bilateral corticonuclear fibres. They lie dorsal to the neurones that innervate the muscles of the lower face, which receive a predominately contralateral innervation. Clinically, therefore, upper and lower motor neurone lesions affecting the facial nerve can be differentiated because upper motor neurone lesions cause paralysis that is confined to the contralateral lower face (supranuclear facial palsy), whilst lower motor neurone lesions cause complete ipsilateral facial paralysis (Bell’s palsy). The facial nucleus also receives ipsilateral afferents from the nucleus solitarius and from the sensory nucleus of the trigeminal nerve, establishing important reflex connections.

Efferent fibres that arise from large motor neurones of the facial nucleus form the motor root of the facial nerve. At first, the facial fibres course dorsomedially towards the floor of the fourth ventricle as a diffuse spread of fibres that pass dorsal and medial to the abducens nucleus. They then coalesce into a defined fibre bundle that re-curves dorsally and laterally over the rostral pole of the abducens nucleus, creating a bulge in the floor of the fourth ventricle, the facial colliculus (see Fig. 28.11). The fibres descend ventrolaterally through the reticular formation and pass between their nucleus of origin medially and the nucleus of the spinal tract of the trigeminal nerve laterally. The facial nerve emerges from the brainstem at the supraolivary fossette, between the olive and restiform body, and passes laterally through the cerebellopontine angle cistern to the porus acusticus of the internal acoustic meatus (internal auditory canal).

Vestibulocochlear Nerve

The vestibulocochlear nerve is the eighth cranial nerve. As its name suggests, it consists of two components, the vestibular nerve, concerned with balance, and the cochlear nerve, concerned with hearing.

Vestibular nuclei and central connections

The vestibular nuclear complex is situated beneath the floor of the fourth ventricle. It has traditionally been divided into four cellular masses, the lateral nucleus (of Deiter), medial nucleus (of Schwalbe), superior nucleus (of Bechterew) and inferior (spinal, descending) vestibular nucleus (see Figs 28.8, 28.11) (Haines and Mihailoff 2017). The nucleus prepositus hypoglossi, located medial to the medial vestibular nucleus, may also be regarded as a vestibular nucleus. Cell groups X and Y have been identified as accessory nuclei of the vestibular complex.

The medial vestibular nucleus is the largest of the vestibular nuclei. It lies lateral and superior to the visceromotor nuclei of the glossopharyngeal and vagus nerves, is crossed dorsally by the striae medullares of the fourth ventricle and is continuous with the nucleus intercalatus below. The superior vestibular nucleus is small and lies above the medial and lateral nuclei. It extends higher into the pons than the other subdivisions and occupies the upper part of the vestibular area. The inferior vestibular nucleus is the smallest of the group. It lies between the medial vestibular nucleus and the restiform body, from the level of the upper end of the nucleus gracilis to the pontomedullary junction, and is traversed by descending fibres of the vestibular nerve, from the cerebellum and the vestibulospinal tract. The lateral vestibular nucleus lies ventrolateral to the upper portion of the medial nucleus, just above the inferior nucleus and ascends almost to the level of the abducens nucleus. Its rostral end is continuous with the caudal end of the superior nucleus. It projects to the spinal cord through the lateral vestibulospinal tract ([Voogd 2016]). The lateral vestibular nucleus can be subdivided into dorsal and ventral components. The dorsal portion contains giant cells and is located within the juxtarestiform body: it receives no direct vestibular afferents, but receives Purkinje cell axons from the anterior vermis, and extends efferent connections to the cerebellum. The ventral portion contains cells of various sizes and is located medial to the juxtarestiform body

Vestibulocerebellar fibres (primary and secondary) travel via the juxtarestiform body mainly to the flocculus and nodule. Cerebellovestibular fibres pass to the nuclei, also via the juxtarestiform body: they arise mainly in the flocculus and nodule (posterior lobe), but some fibres are derived from the anterior lobe and the fastigial nucleus. A few vestibular fibres enter the cerebellum directly through the juxtarestiform body and end in the fastigial nucleus, flocculonodular lobe and uvula.

The vestibular nuclei receive afferent fibres from multiple sources, including the vestibular portion of the vestibulocochlear nerve, cerebellum, brainstem reticular formation and spinal cord. Myelinated fibres in the vestibular nerve enter the medulla between the restiform body and the spinal tract of the trigeminal nerve and bifurcate into ascending and descending branches. Most ascending vestibular fibres end in the superior vestibular nucleus. Descending vestibular fibres traverse the juxtarestiform body and give off extensive transverse collaterals to the inferior and medial (but not the lateral) vestibular nuclei. Additional afferent fibres descend from the cerebral cortex to innervate the vestibular nuclei bilaterally.

Afferent fibres arising from the interstitial nucleus of Cajal descend through the medial longitudinal fasciculus to synapse in the ipsilateral superior and medial vestibular nuclei and the nucleus prepositius hypoglossi. Afferent fibres from the Edinger–Westphal nucleus project to the medial and inferior vestibular nuclei, which also receive root fibres from the upper cervical nerve roots (C2, C3). The lateral vestibular nucleus and inferior portions of the medial and inferior vestibular nuclei receive ipsilateral spinovestibular fibres that ascend from lower spinal levels through the dorsal spinocerebellar tract.

The vestibular nuclei project extensively to the cerebellum and also receive fibres from the cerebellar cortex and the fastigial nuclei. Vestibulocerebellar fibres pass through the juxtarestiform body to the cerebellum (Carpenter and Sutin 1983). A few vestibular nerve fibres bypass the vestibular nuclei and traverse the juxtarestiform body to terminate directly in the fastigial nucleus, the flocculonodular lobe and uvula.

Evidence suggests that the vestibular apparatus is spatially represented in these nuclei. Efferents from the lateral vestibular nucleus descend to the spinal cord through the ipsilateral lateral vestibulospinal tract and extend along the full length of the spinal cord to exert a facilitatory influence on spinal reflex activity and on extensor muscle tone. Vestibular nuclear efferents form a major part of the medial longitudinal fasciculus, through which interconnections between the vestibular and oculogyric nuclei and the pontine reticular formation enable conjugate eye movements that compensate for head movements perceived by the labyrinths. The reflex arcs stabilize visual fixation despite changing head position. Vestibular efferents project to the thalamus (probably via the posterior portions of the ventroposterior complex and the medial pulvinar), which in turn projects to the primary vestibular cortex in the parietal lobe at the junction of the intraparietal and postcentral sulci, adjacent to the head portion of the postcentral gyrus. There may be additional representation of the vestibular system in the superior temporal gyrus near to the auditory cortex.

Vestibular ganglion

The somata of the bipolar neurones that form the vestibular nerve are in the vestibular (Scarpa’s) ganglion located in the trunk of the nerve within the lateral end of the internal acoustic meatus (see Fig. 43.12B). They vary considerably in size, with circumferences ranging from 45 to 160 μm (Felix et al 1987): no topographically ordered distribution relating to size has been found. The somata are notable for their abundant granular endoplasmic reticulum, which in places forms Nissl bodies, and prominent Golgi complexes. They are covered by a thin layer of satellite cells and are often arranged in pairs, closely abutting each other so that only a thin layer of endoneurium separates the adjacent coverings of satellite cells. This arrangement has led to speculation that ganglion cells may affect each other directly by electrotonic spread (ephaptic transmission: see Felix et al (1987)). Two distinct sympathetic components have been identified in the vestibular ganglion, a perivascular adrenergic system derived from the stellate ganglion, and a blood vessel-independent system derived from the superior cervical ganglion.

The central processes of the vestibular ganglion cells travel via the vestibular nerve, enter the brainstem at the cerebellopontine angle and terminate in the vestibular nuclear complex (see below). Neurones in this complex project to motor nuclei in the brainstem and upper spinal cord, and to the cerebellum and thalamus. Thalamic efferent projections pass to a cortical vestibular area that is probably located near the intraparietal sulcus in area 2 of the primary somatosensory cortex.

The peripheral processes of the vestibular ganglion cells are aggregated into definable nerves, each with a specific distribution. The main nerve divides at and within the ganglion into superior and inferior divisions connected by an isthmus. The superior division, the larger of the two, passes through the small holes in the superior vestibular area at the fundus of the internal acoustic meatus (see Fig. 43.3) and supplies the ampullary crests of the lateral and anterior semicircular canals via the lateral and anterior ampullary nerves, respectively. A secondary branch of the lateral ampullary nerve supplies the macula of the utricle; however, the greater part of the utricular macula is innervated by the utricular nerve, which is a separate branch of the superior division. Another branch of the superior division supplies part of the saccule. The inferior division passes through small holes in the inferior vestibular area (see Fig. 43.3) to supply the remainder of the saccule and the posterior ampullary crest via saccular and singular branches, respectively; the latter passes through the foramen singulare. Occasionally, a very small supplementary or accessory branch innervates the posterior crest; it is probably a vestigial remnant of the crista neglecta, an additional area of sensory epithelium found in some other mammals but seldom in humans.

Afferent and efferent cochlear fibres are also present in the inferior division of the vestibular nerve but leave at the anastomosis of Oort to join the main cochlear nerve (see review by [Warr (1992]). Another anastomosis, the vestibulofacial anastomosis, is situated more centrally between the facial and vestibular nerves and is the point at which fibres originating in the intermediate nerve pass from the vestibular nerve to the main trunk of the facial nerve.

There are approximately 20,000 fibres in the vestibular nerve, of which 12,000 travel in the superior division and 8000 travel in the inferior division. The distribution of fibre diameters is bimodal, with peaks at 4 μm and 6.5 μm. The smaller fibres go mainly to the type II hair cells and the larger fibres tend to supply the type I hair cells. In addition to the afferents, efferent and autonomic fibres have been identified. Efferent fibres synapse exclusively with the afferent calyceal terminals around type I cells and usually with the afferent boutons on type II cells, although a few are in direct contact with the cell bodies of type II cells. The autonomic fibres do not contact vestibular sensory cells but terminate beneath the sensory epithelia.

Cochlear nuclei and central connections

The primary afferents of the auditory pathway are the central processes of type I and II sensory neurones in the spiral ganglion of Corti in the cochlea. They travel in the cochlear division of the vestibulocochlear nerve and enter the brainstem just caudal to the vestibular division of the vestibulocochlear nerve at the cerebellopontine angle. The axons bifurcate and terminate in the dorsal (posterior) and ventral (anterior) cochlear nuclei lying along the lateral surface of the restiform body. The dorsal cochlear nucleus forms a bulge, the auditory tubercle (auditory eminence) on the posterior surface of the restiform body and also forms the floor of the lateral recess of the fourth ventricle; it is continuous medially with the vestibular area in the floor of the fourth ventricle (see Fig. 28.9). The ventral cochlear nucleus lies between the cochlear and vestibular fibres of the vestibulocochlear nerve. The dorsal and ventral cochlear nuclei are separated only by a thin stratum of nerve cell bodies and fibres.

The axons of type 1 spiral ganglion cells enter the ventral cochlear nucleus and bifurcate within its centre, dividing it into anterior and posterior ventral subnuclei. The fibres are organized into dorsoventrally oriented sheets in which fibres conveying low frequency sounds from apical spiral ganglion cells terminate ventrally and fibres conveying high frequency sounds from the basal turn of the spiral ganglion terminate dorsally. Posterior processes of type I ganglion cells pass to the caudal pole of the ventral nucleus, from which they enter the dorsal cochlear nucleus. Thin unmyelinated axons of type 2 spiral ganglion cells contact clusters of small interneurones scattered through the cochlear nuclei.

The axons that emerge from the cochlear nuclei are aggregated into three, mostly transverse, fibre bundles, the dorsal and intermediate acoustic striae and the trapezoid body. The dorsal cochlear nucleus projects via the dorsal acoustic stria to the contralateral inferior colliculus. The dorsal acoustic stria curves dorsally and medially, dorsal to the restiform body, traverses the reticular formation ventral to the striae medullares, crosses the midline, passes to the contralateral superior olivary complex, and ascends in the contralateral lateral lemniscus. The ventral cochlear nucleus projects via the trapezoid body or the intermediate acoustic stria to relay centres in either the superior olivary complex, the nuclei of the lateral lemniscus, or the inferior colliculus. Initially, the intermediate acoustic stria accompanies the dorsal acoustic stria as they pass medially, immediately dorsal to the restiform body, but it then separates from the dorsal acoustic stria, angles sharply ventrally in the ipsilateral tegmentum, passes through the spinal trigeminal nucleus, joins the trapezoid body, and crosses the midline to join and ascend with the contralateral lateral lemniscus.

The cochlear nerve also conveys efferent fibres that pass outward from the brainstem to terminate on the hair cells and on the cells of the spiral ganglion.

Intratemporal and intracranial course

The vestibulocochlear nerve emerges from the cerebellopontine angle (see Figs 28.4–28.5). It courses through the posterior cranial fossa in close association with the facial nerve, nervus intermedius and labyrinthine vessels. Together with these structures, it enters the petrous temporal bone via the porus acusticus of the internal acoustic meatus (see Fig. 43.3), and divides into an anterior trunk, the cochlear nerve, and a posterior trunk, the vestibular nerve. Both contain the centrally directed axons of bipolar neurones, together with a smaller number of efferent fibres that arise from brainstem neurones and terminate on cochlear and vestibular sensory neurones. In humans, the intratemporal portion of the vestibulocochlear nerve consists of two histologically distinct portions: a central glial zone adjacent to the brainstem, and a peripheral or non-glial zone (Bridger and Farkashidy 1980). In the glial zone, the axons are supported by central neuroglia, whereas in the non-glial zone they are ensheathed by Schwann cells. The non-glial zone sometimes extends into the cerebellopontine angle medial to the internal acoustic meatus in human vestibulocochlear nerves. During development, a gap of several weeks has been reported between the onset of Schwann cell myelination distally and glial myelination proximally; it has been suggested that the gap may coincide with the time of the final maturation of the organ of Corti. For further details about the development of the human cochlear nerve, see Ray et al (2005)).

In audiological practice, it is important to distinguish between intratemporal and intracranial lesions. However, this surgical distinction does not correlate with the precise anatomical description of peripheral and central portions of the auditory and vestibular systems. Clinically, the term ‘peripheral auditory lesion’ is used to describe lesions peripheral to the spiral ganglion, and the term ‘peripheral vestibular disturbance’ includes lesions of the vestibular ganglion and the entire vestibular nerve.

Glossopharyngeal Nerve

The glossopharyngeal nerve is the ninth cranial nerve (see Figs 35.8, 35.11, 35.19). It contains motor fibres to stylopharyngeus; parasympathetic secretomotor fibres to the parotid gland (derived from the inferior salivatory nucleus); sensory fibres to the tympanic cavity, pharyngotympanic tube, fauces, tonsils, nasopharynx, uvula and posterior (postsulcal) third of the tongue; and gustatory fibres from the circumvallate papillae.

Nucleus ambiguus

The nucleus ambiguus is a complex group of large motor neurones situated deep in the medullary reticular formation (see Figs 28.3, 28.9). Rostrally, it extends as far as the rostral end of the vagal nucleus and caudally it is in line with, but not continuous with, the nucleus of the accessory nerve. A small retrofacial nucleus separates the upper end of the nucleus ambiguus from the facial nucleus. The nucleus ambiguus contains cellular subgroups that exhibit some topographical representation. Relatively discrete groups of cells in the caudal region innervate individual laryngeal muscles; neurones in the intermediate area innervate the pharynx; neurones in the rostral area innervate the oesophagus and soft palate.

The nucleus ambiguus contributes special visceral efferent fibres to the glossopharyngeal nerve and may give general visceral efferent fibres to the vagus nerve. Fibres emerging from the nucleus ambiguus pass dorsomedially, then curve laterally. Rostral fibres join the glossopharyngeal nerve and caudal fibres join the vagus nerve and are distributed to the pharyngeal constrictors, intrinsic laryngeal muscles and striated muscles of the palate and upper oesophagus. A specific caudal pool of laryngeal motor neurones gives rise to the recurrent laryngeal nerve.

Extracranial course

The glossopharyngeal nerve leaves the skull through the anteromedial part of the jugular foramen, anterior to the vagus and accessory nerves, and in a separate dural sheath. In the foramen, it is lodged in a deep groove leading from the cochlear aqueductal depression, separated by the inferior petrosal sinus from the vagus and accessory nerves. The groove is bridged by fibrous tissue, which is sometimes calcified. After leaving the foramen, the nerve passes forwards between the internal jugular vein and internal carotid artery, and then descends anterior to the latter, deep to the styloid process and its attached muscles, to reach the posterior border of stylopharyngeus. It curves forwards on stylopharyngeus and either pierces the lower fibres of the superior pharyngeal constrictor or passes between it and the middle constrictor to be distributed to the palatine tonsil, the mucosae of the pharynx and postsulcal part of the tongue, the vallate papillae and oral mucous glands.

Two ganglia, superior and inferior, are situated on the glossopharyngeal nerve as it traverses the jugular foramen. The superior ganglion is in the upper part of the groove occupied by the nerve in the jugular foramen. It is small, has no branches and is usually regarded as a detached part of the inferior ganglion. The inferior ganglion is larger and lies in a notch in the lower border of the petrous part of the temporal bone. Its cells are typical unipolar neurones, their peripheral branches convey gustatory and tactile signals from the mucosa of the tongue (posterior third, including the sulcus terminalis and vallate papillae) and general sensation from the oropharynx, where the glossopharyngeal nerve is responsible for initiating the gag reflex.

The glossopharyngeal nerve has tympanic, carotid, pharyngeal, muscular, tonsillar and lingual branches.

Communicating branches

The glossopharyngeal nerve communicates with the sympathetic trunk and vagus and facial nerves. Its inferior ganglion is connected with the superior cervical sympathetic ganglion. Two filaments from the inferior ganglion pass to the vagus, one to its auricular branch and the other to its superior ganglion. A branch to the facial nerve arises from the glossopharyngeal nerve below the inferior ganglion and perforates the posterior belly of digastric to join the facial nerve near the stylomastoid foramen.

Tympanic nerve

The tympanic nerve leaves the inferior ganglion, ascends to the tympanic cavity through the tympanic canaliculus and divides into branches that contribute to the tympanic plexus on the promontory. The lesser petrosal nerve is derived from the tympanic plexus.

Carotid branch

The carotid branch is often double. It arises just below the jugular foramen and descends on the internal carotid artery to the wall of the carotid sinus and to the carotid body. The nerve contains primary afferent fibres from chemoreceptors in the carotid body and from the baroreceptors lying in the carotid sinus wall. It may communicate with the inferior ganglion of the vagus, or with one of its branches, and with a sympathetic branch from the superior cervical ganglion (see Fig. 35.20).

Pharyngeal branches

The pharyngeal branches are three or four filaments that unite with the pharyngeal branch of the vagus and the laryngopharyngeal branches of the sympathetic trunk to form the pharyngeal plexus near the middle pharyngeal constrictor. They constitute the route by which the glossopharyngeal nerve supplies sensory fibres to the mucosa of the pharynx.

Muscular branch

The muscular branch supplies stylopharyngeus.

Tonsillar, lingual and lesser petrosal branches and the tympanic plexus

The tympanic plexus supplies branches to the mucosa of the tympanic cavity, pharyngotympanic tube and mastoid air cells. The nerves that constitute the tympanic plexus ramify on the surface of the promontory on the medial wall of the tympanic cavity. They are derived from the tympanic branch of the glossopharyngeal nerve and the caroticotympanic nerves. The former arises from the inferior ganglion of the glossopharyngeal nerve and reaches the tympanic cavity via the tympanic canaliculus for the tympanic nerve. The superior and inferior caroticotympanic nerves are postganglionic sympathetic fibres derived from the carotid sympathetic plexus that traverse the wall of the carotid canal to join the plexus.

The lesser petrosal nerve, which may be regarded as the continuation of the tympanic branch of the glossopharyngeal nerve, traverses the tympanic plexus. It occupies a small canal below that for tensor tympani. It runs past, and receives a connecting branch from, the geniculate ganglion of the facial nerve. The lesser petrosal nerve emerges from the anterior surface of the temporal bone via a small opening lateral to the hiatus for the greater petrosal nerve and then traverses either the foramen ovale or the sphenopetrosal fissure or the innominate canal (of Arnold) to join the otic ganglion. Postganglionic secretomotor fibres leave this ganglion in the auriculotemporal nerve to supply the parotid gland. The tympanic plexus sends a branch to the greater petrosal nerve via an opening anterior to the fenestra vestibuli.

The tonsillar region is innervated by tonsillar branches of the maxillary and glossopharyngeal nerves. The fibres from the maxillary nerve pass through, but do not synapse in, the pterygopalatine ganglion; they are distributed through the lesser palatine nerves and form a plexus (the circulus tonsillaris) around the tonsil together with the tonsillar branches of the glossopharyngeal nerve. Nerve fibres from this plexus are also distributed to the soft palate and the region of the oropharyngeal isthmus. The tympanic branch of the glossopharyngeal nerve supplies the mucous membrane lining the tympanic cavity. Infection, malignancy and postoperative inflammation of the tonsil and tonsillar fossa may therefore be accompanied by pain referred to the ear.

Lesions of the glossopharyngeal nerve

There are anastomoses between the glossopharyngeal, vagus, greater auricular and other branches of the cervical plexus that may be significant when treating patients with skull base pathology. Damage to the glossopharyngeal nerve is rarely seen without associated involvement of other lower cranial nerves. Transient or sustained hypertension may follow surgical section of the nerve and indicates involvement of the carotid branch. Isolated lesions of the glossopharyngeal nerve lead to loss of sensation over the ipsilateral soft palate, fauces, pharynx and posterior third of the tongue, although this is difficult to assess clinically, and confirmation requires galvanic stimulation. The palatal and pharyngeal (gag) reflexes are reduced or absent and salivary secretion from the parotid gland may also be reduced. Weakness of stylopharyngeus cannot be tested individually. Glossopharyngeal neuralgia consists of episodic brief but severe pain, often precipitated by swallowing and experienced in the throat, behind the angle of the jaw and within the ear. Superior jugular bulb thromboses (e.g. in otitis media) and jugular foramen syndrome (associated with nasopharyngeal carcinoma or a jugular paraganglioma) may cause lesions of the adjacent glossopharyngeal, vagus and accessory nerves, with associated weakness in the muscles supplied in the pharynx and larynx.

Vagus nerve

The vagus is the tenth cranial nerve. It is a large mixed nerve, containing branchiomotor nerve fibres, general visceral afferents and preganglionic parasympathetic fibres. The vagus has a more extensive course and distribution than any other cranial nerve, running through the neck, thorax and abdomen. The proportion of efferent parasympathetic nerve fibres it contains varies at different levels but is small relative to its sensory and sensorimotor content. The branchiomotor fibres arise from neurones in the nucleus ambiguus in the medulla oblongata and are distributed to the constrictor muscles of the pharynx and the intrinsic muscles of the larynx. The preganglionic parasympathetic nerves arise from cell bodies in the vagal dorsal nucleus in the medulla oblongata, travel in the nerve and in its pulmonary, cardiac, oesophageal, gastric and intestinal branches and relay/synapse in minute ganglia in the visceral walls (see Fig. 56.6) (Mussa and Verberne 2013).

The general visceral afferent fibres carry sensation from thoracic and abdominal viscera and from aortic arch baroreceptors and chemoreceptors and end in the nucleus solitarius of the medulla. Their cell bodies are in the superior and inferior vagal ganglia. Their peripheral processes are distributed to terminals in the pharyngeal and oesophageal walls where, acting synergistically with glossopharyngeal visceral afferents in the pharynx, they are concerned with swallowing reflexes. Vagal afferents are also believed to innervate the thyroid and parathyroid glands. In the heart, vagal afferents innervate the walls of the great vessels, the aortic bodies and pressor receptors, where they are stimulated by raised intravascular pressure. In the lungs they are distributed via the pulmonary plexuses: they supply bronchial mucosa, where they are probably involved in cough reflexes; bronchial muscle, where they encircle myocytes and end in tendrils, which are sometimes regarded as muscle spindles and which are believed to be stimulated by change in the length of myocytes; interalveolar connective tissue, where their knob-like endings, together with terminals on myocytes, may evoke Hering–Breuer reflexes; the adventitia of pulmonary arteries, where they may be pressor receptors; and the intima of pulmonary veins, where they may be chemoreceptors. Vagal visceral afferent fibres also end in the gastric and intestinal walls, digestive glands and the kidneys. Fibres ending in the gut and its ducts respond to stretch or contraction. Gastric impulses may evoke sensations of hunger and nausea.

About 5% of the vagal afferents project directly to, and terminate in, the upper cervical spinal cord (C1–C2), where they are believed to contribute to referred sensations, as well as to propriospinal mechanisms of nociceptive modulation. Almost all the central processes of vagal and glossopharyngeal afferent fibres end in the nucleus solitarius of the medulla.

Dorsal motor nucleus of the vagus

The dorsal motor nucleus of the vagus lies slightly dorsolateral to the hypoglossal nucleus, from which it is separated by the nucleus intercalatus (see Fig. 28.8). The vagal nucleus extends caudally to the first cervical spinal segment and rostrally to the open portion of the medulla subjacent to the vagal trigone of the fourth ventricle. It is a general visceral efferent nucleus and is the largest parasympathetic nucleus in the brainstem. Most (80%) of its neurones give rise to the preganglionic parasympathetic fibres that pass into the vagus nerve. The remainder are interneurones or neurones that project centrally. The nucleus innervates the cardiac and smooth muscle of the thoracic viscera (heart, bronchi, lungs, oesophagus) and abdomen (stomach, liver, pancreas, spleen, small intestine and proximal part of the colon), and glandular epithelium. Sparse sensory afferents from the nodose ganglion project directly to the dorsal and lateral edges of the dorsal vagal nucleus, and possibly beyond it into the nucleus of the solitary tract (Holstein 2012).

Neurones within the nucleus are heterogeneous and can be classified into nine subnuclei, grouped into rostral, intermediate and caudal divisions. Topographic maps of visceral representation in animals suggest that the heart and lungs are represented in the caudal and lateral parts of the nucleus; the stomach and pancreas in intermediate regions; and the remaining abdominal organs in the rostral and medial parts of the nucleus.

Extracranial course

The vagus nerve exits the skull through the jugular foramen, accompanied by the accessory nerve, with which it shares an arachnoid and a dural sheath. Both nerves lie anterior to a fibrous septum that separates them from the glossopharyngeal nerve. The vagus descends vertically in the neck in the carotid sheath, between the internal jugular vein and the internal carotid artery, to the upper border of the thyroid cartilage, and then passes between the vein and the common carotid artery to the root of the neck. Its relationships in this part of its course are therefore similar to those described for these structures (see Figs 35.7A, 35.8, 35.17). Its further course differs on the two sides. The right vagus descends posterior to the internal jugular vein to cross the first part of the subclavian artery and enter the thorax. The left vagus enters the thorax between the left common carotid and subclavian arteries, and behind the left brachiocephalic vein.

After emerging from the jugular foramen, the vagus bears two marked enlargements: a small, round, superior (jugular) ganglion and a larger inferior (nodose) ganglion.

Superior (jugular) ganglion

The superior ganglion is greyish, spherical and approximately 4 mm in diameter. It is connected to the inferior glossopharyngeal ganglion and the sympathetic trunk, the latter by a filament from the superior cervical ganglion.

Inferior (nodose) ganglion

The inferior or nodose ganglion is larger than the superior ganglion, and is elongated and cylindrical in shape with a length of 25 mm and a maximum breadth of 5 mm. It is connected with the hypoglossal nerve, the loop between the first and second cervical spinal nerves, and with the superior cervical sympathetic ganglion. Most visceral afferent axons travelling in the vagus nerve are the peripheral processes of cell bodies located in the nodose ganglion.

Both vagal ganglia are exclusively sensory and contain somatic, special visceral and general visceral afferent neurones. The superior ganglion is mainly somatic and most of its neurones enter the auricular nerve, whilst neurones in the inferior ganglion are concerned with visceral sensation from the heart, larynx, lungs and the alimentary tract from the pharynx to the transverse colon. Some fibres transmit impulses from taste endings in the vallecula and epiglottis. Large afferent fibres are derived from muscle spindles in the laryngeal muscles. Vagal sensory neurones in the nodose ganglion may show some somatotopic organization. Both ganglia are traversed by parasympathetic and perhaps some sympathetic fibres, but there is no evidence that vagal parasympathetic components relay in the inferior ganglion. Preganglionic motor fibres from the dorsal vagal nucleus and the special visceral efferents from the nucleus ambiguus, which descend to the inferior vagal ganglion, commonly form a visible band that skirts the ganglion in some mammals. These larger fibres probably provide motor innervation to the larynx in the recurrent laryngeal nerve, together with some contribution to the superior laryngeal nerve supplying cricothyroid.

Vagus nerve in the neck

The branches of the vagus in the neck are the meningeal, auricular, pharyngeal, carotid body, superior and recurrent laryngeal nerves and cardiac branches.

Meningeal branches

Meningeal branches appear to start from the superior vagal ganglion and pass through the jugular foramen to be distributed to the dura mater in the posterior cranial fossa (see Fig. 25.3B).

Auricular branch

The auricular branch (Arnold’s nerve) arises from the superior vagal ganglion and is joined by a branch from the inferior ganglion of the glossopharyngeal nerve. It passes behind the internal jugular vein and enters the mastoid canaliculus on the lateral wall of the jugular fossa. Traversing the temporal bone, it crosses the facial canal approximately 4 mm above the stylomastoid foramen and here supplies an ascending branch to the facial nerve. Fibres of the nervus intermedius may pass to the auricular branch at this point, which may explain the cutaneous vesiculation in the auricle that sometimes accompanies geniculate herpes. The auricular branch then traverses the tympanomastoid fissure and divides into two rami. One ramus joins the posterior auricular nerve and the other is distributed to the skin of part of the ear and to the external acoustic meatus.

Pharyngeal branch

The pharyngeal branch of the vagus is the main motor nerve of the pharynx and consists of axons arising from neuronal cell bodies in the nucleus ambiguus. It supplies all the muscles of the soft palate (excluding tensor veli palatini, which is supplied by the mandibular division of the trigeminal nerve via the nerve to medial pterygoid) and all the muscles of the pharynx (excluding stylopharyngeus, which is supplied by the glossopharyngeal nerve). It emerges from the upper part of the inferior vagal ganglion, passes between the external and internal carotid arteries to reach the upper border of the middle pharyngeal constrictor, and divides into numerous filaments that join rami of the sympathetic trunk and glossopharyngeal nerve to form the pharyngeal plexus. It also gives off a minute filament, the ramus lingualis vagi, which joins the hypoglossal nerve as it curves round the occipital artery.

Branches to the carotid body

Branches to the carotid body are variable in number. They may arise from the inferior ganglion or travel in the pharyngeal branch, or in the superior laryngeal nerve. They form a plexus with the glossopharyngeal rami and branches of the cervical sympathetic trunk.

Superior laryngeal nerve

The superior laryngeal nerve is larger than the pharyngeal branch and issues from the middle of the inferior vagal ganglion. It receives one or more communicating branches from the superior cervical sympathetic ganglion; most frequently, the connection is with the external laryngeal nerve. The sympathetic communication contributes to the innervation of the carotid body (Monfared et al 2002) and the thyroid gland (Sun and Chang 1991). The superior laryngeal nerve descends alongside the pharynx, at first posterior, then medial, to the internal carotid artery: it may be found on the lateral side of the artery. It divides into a smaller, external, and a larger, internal, branch, approximately 1.5 cm below the ganglion: rarely, both branches may arise from the ganglion (see Figs 35.8, 41.12).

Internal laryngeal nerve

The internal laryngeal nerve passes forwards approximately 7 mm before piercing the thyrohyoid membrane, usually at a higher level than the superior thyroid artery (Durham and Harrison 1962). It splits into superior, middle and inferior branches on entering the larynx. The superior branch supplies the mucosa of the piriform fossa. The large middle branch is distributed to the mucosa of the ventricle, specifically the quadrangular membrane, and therefore probably conveys the afferent component of the cough reflex. The inferior ramus is mainly distributed to the mucosa of the ventricle and subglottic cavity. On the medial wall of the piriform fossa, descending branches give twigs to the interarytenoid muscle and share a number of communicating branches with the recurrent laryngeal nerve (Sanders and Mu 1998).

The internal laryngeal nerve is sensory to the laryngeal mucosa down to the level of the vocal folds. It also carries afferent fibres from the laryngeal neuromuscular spindles and other stretch receptors. It descends to the thyrohyoid membrane, pierces it above the superior laryngeal artery and divides into an upper and lower branch. The upper branch is horizontal and supplies the mucosa of the pharynx, the epiglottis, vallecula and laryngeal vestibule. The lower branch descends in the medial wall of the piriform recess, supplies the aryepiglottic fold, the mucosa on the back of the arytenoid cartilage and one or two branches to transverse arytenoid (the latter unite with twigs from the recurrent laryngeal to supply the same muscle). The internal laryngeal nerve ends by piercing the inferior pharyngeal constrictor to unite with an ascending branch from the recurrent laryngeal nerve. As it ascends in the neck, it supplies branches, more numerous on the left, to the mucosa and tunica muscularis of the oesophagus and trachea, and to the inferior constrictor.

External laryngeal nerve

The external laryngeal nerve, smaller than the internal, descends behind sternohyoid with the superior thyroid artery, but on a deeper plane. It lies first on (occasionally within) the inferior pharyngeal constrictor, to which it contributes some small branches, and then pierces it to curve round the inferior thyroid tubercle. It passes beneath the attachment of sternothyroid to the oblique line of the thyroid cartilage to reach cricothyroid, which it supplies. A communicating nerve continues from the posterior surface of cricothyroid, crosses the piriform fossa and enters thyroarytenoid, where it anastomoses with branches from the recurrent laryngeal nerve. It has been suggested that these communicating branches may provide both additional motor components to thyroarytenoid and sensory fibres to the mucosa in the region of the subglottis. An anastomosis between the external and internal laryngeal nerves has also been described (Kochilas et al 2008). The external laryngeal nerve also gives branches to the pharyngeal plexus and communicates with the superior cardiac nerve and superior cervical sympathetic ganglion.

The close relationship of the external laryngeal nerve to the superior thyroid artery puts the nerve at potential risk when the artery is clamped during thyroid lobectomy, particularly when it is close to the artery (in approximately 20% of cases), or where, instead of crossing the superior thyroid vessels approximately 1 cm or more above the superior pole of the gland, it actually passes below this point (in some 20% of cases) (Cernea et al 1992, Kierner et al 1998). The external laryngeal nerve is also at risk in parathyroidectomy, carotid endarterectomy and anterior cervical spine procedures.

Recurrent laryngeal nerve

The recurrent laryngeal nerve supplies all the laryngeal muscles except cricothyroid, communicates with the internal laryngeal nerve and carries sensory filaments from the laryngeal mucosa below the vocal folds and from laryngeal stretch receptors. The nerve differs in origin and course on the two sides. On the right, it almost always arises from the vagus anterior to the first part of the subclavian artery, and curves backwards below and then behind it to ascend obliquely to the side of the trachea behind the common carotid artery. Near the lower pole of the lateral lobe of the thyroid gland, it is closely related to the inferior thyroid artery and crosses either in front of, behind or between its branches. On the left, the recurrent laryngeal nerve arises from the vagus on the left of the aortic arch, curves below it immediately behind the attachment of the ligamentum arteriosum to the concavity of the aortic arch and ascends to the side of the trachea (see Fig. 57.61). As the recurrent laryngeal nerve curves round either the subclavian artery or the aortic arch, it gives cardiac filaments to the deep cardiac plexus.

On both sides, the recurrent laryngeal nerve ascends in or near the tracheo-oesophageal groove. It is closely related to the medial surface of the thyroid gland before it passes under the lower border of the inferior constrictor, and it enters the larynx behind the articulation of the inferior thyroid cornu with the cricoid cartilage, passing either deep to (usually) or between (sometimes) the fibres of cricopharyngeus at its attachment to the lateral aspect of the cricoid cartilage. The nerve supplies cricopharyngeus as it passes. At this point, the nerve is in intimate proximity to the posteromedial aspect of the thyroid gland. The main trunk divides into two or more branches, usually below the lower border of the inferior constrictor, although branching may take place higher up. The anterior branch is mainly motor and is sometimes called the inferior laryngeal nerve (a term that is best avoided to prevent any confusion with a former synonym for the recurrent laryngeal nerve). It ascends posterior to the cricothyroid joint and its ligament, usually covered by fibres of posterior cricoarytenoid, then bends over the joint and continues forwards over lateral cricoarytenoid before terminating within thyroarytenoid. It innervates posterior cricoarytenoid by one or more branches, and interarytenoid, lateral cricoarytenoid and thyroarytenoid (Maranillo et al 2005). The posterior branch of the recurrent laryngeal nerve is mainly sensory and ascends deep to posterior cricoarytenoid to join the descending branch of the internal laryngeal nerve.

The recurrent laryngeal nerve does not always lie in a protected position in the tracheo-oesophageal groove but may be slightly anterior to it (more often on the right), and it may be markedly lateral to the trachea at the level of the lower part of the thyroid gland. The upper part of the nerve has a close but variable relationship to the inferior thyroid artery. On the right, it is as often anterior to, or posterior to, or intermingled with, the terminal branches of the artery; on the left, the nerve is usually posterior to the artery, though occasionally lies anterior to it. The stated incidences of these relationships vary between different authors. The recurrent laryngeal nerve has a highly variable branching pattern (see Fig. 41.13) (Henry et al 2016).

A very rare anomaly of relevance to laryngeal pathology and surgery is the ‘non-recurrent’ laryngeal nerve, where the right recurrent laryngeal nerve arises directly from the vagus nerve trunk high up in the neck and enters the larynx close to the inferior pole of the thyroid gland. Only the right side is affected, and it is always associated with an abnormal origin of the right subclavian artery from the aortic arch on the left side. If unrecognized, a non-recurrent laryngeal nerve may be susceptible to injury during surgery. It may also potentially be compressed by small tumours of the thyroid gland (Friedman et al 1986).

Pharyngeal plexus

Almost all of the nerve supply to the pharynx, whether motor or sensory, is derived from the pharyngeal plexus, which is formed by the pharyngeal branches of the glossopharyngeal and vagus nerves with contributions from the superior cervical sympathetic ganglion. The plexus lies on the external surface of the pharynx, especially on the middle constrictor. Filaments from the plexus ascend or descend external to the superior and inferior constrictors before branching within the muscular layer and mucosa of the pharynx. Whether a ‘cranial root’ of the accessory nerve serves as the conduit for the major motor drive to the pharyngeal plexus, albeit via the vagus nerve, is a matter of debate. The plexiform connections that may be demonstrated between the accessory nerve and the vagus nerve within the posterior cranial fossa are too variable and insubstantial to support this function.

Laryngeal nerve anastomoses

Anastomotic communications between the internal, external and recurrent laryngeal nerves probably explain why normal or near normal voice function can be present following neck surgery when one or more branches of these nerves have been divided (Naidu et al 2014, Sanudo et al 1999, Henry et al 2017). Numerous communications have been described (Sanudo et al 1999, Furlan et al 2002). The ansa Galeni, lying on the interarytenoid muscles, forms a direct connection between the recurrent and internal laryngeal nerves: it may be a single or double trunk or a plexus. The cricoid communication connects branches that originate bilaterally from the recurrent laryngeal nerve with the superior branch of the deep portion of the arytenoid plexus. The thyroarytenoid communication links the ascending branch of the recurrent laryngeal nerve and the descending branch from the anterior branch of the internal laryngeal nerve. There are also communications between the external laryngeal and recurrent laryngeal nerves, the internal and external laryngeal nerves and the recurrent laryngeal and superior laryngeal nerves. The anastomosis between the recurrent laryngeal nerve and the sympathetic trunk probably explains why ptosis is a rare complication following thyroidectomy.

Lesions of the vagus nerve and recurrent laryngeal nerve paralysis

The consequences of vagal nerve lesions are complex, reflecting the long course of the nerve and the possible involvement of three of its branches, namely the pharyngeal, superior laryngeal and recurrent laryngeal nerves. Collectively these nerves innervate the muscles of the larynx, soft palate and pharynx, and injury may therefore have deleterious effects on phonation and/or soft palate movements and/or swallowing. A lesion of the vagus nerve above the level at which the pharyngeal branch is given off will affect both the superior and recurrent laryngeal nerves. This causes immobility of the vocal fold on the affected side and imparts a breathy voice with lack of pitch and limited loudness. The affected fold is paralysed and lies in the so-called ‘cadaveric’ position halfway between abduction and adduction. If the lesion is unilateral, the voice is weak and hoarse, but if it is bilateral, phonation is almost absent, the vocal pitch cannot be altered, and the cough is weak and ineffective. There will also be a degree of hypernasality because of the effects on movements of the soft palate caused by paralysis of levator veli palatini. Unilateral palsies impact very significantly on the quality of life of the patient because of impaired vocalization and a tendency to aspirate. Bilateral palsies are extremely serious and a tracheostomy may be required to protect the airway.

A lesion affecting the superior laryngeal nerve may be unilateral or bilateral. Complete section is most likely during the ligation of the vessels forming the vascular pedicle of the superior pole of the thyroid gland during thyroid lobectomy. Unilateral lesions may result in the vocal folds appearing relatively normal and the effect on voice is barely noticeable and is often overlooked. A more detailed examination may detect some shortening of the vocal folds on the affected side with asymmetric tilt of the epiglottis and the anterior larynx canted towards the unaffected side. The result is a mildly hoarse voice with loss of pitch control. Bilateral superior laryngeal nerve lesions result in shortening of both vocal folds, the overhanging of the epiglottis over the folds and reduced tilt between the thyroid and cricoid cartilage. Effects on the voice are correspondingly greater, with reduced loudness and pitch but variable breathiness.

Damage to the internal laryngeal nerve causes loss of mechanoreceptive and proprioceptive sensation from the larynx. Unilateral loss produces a feeling that something is stuck in the throat, whereas bilateral loss will result in aspiration and can cause dysphagia, with a risk of choking.

Unilateral complete palsy of the recurrent laryngeal nerve is more common on the left side, presumably because the nerve is longer on this side. There is isolated paralysis of all the laryngeal muscles on the affected side except cricothyroid, which is innervated by the external laryngeal nerve. The patient may be asymptomatic or have a hoarse, breathy voice and there will be diminished ability to manipulate pitch. The hoarseness may be permanent or may become less severe with time as the contralateral fold develops the ability to hyperadduct and oppose the paralysed fold, thereby closing the glottis during phonation and coughing, although this is seldom enough to restore full voice quality. There may be aspiration of food and drink. Bilateral lesions of the recurrent laryngeal nerve result in both vocal folds being paralysed and taking up a paramedian position. Phonation can be nearly normal because the vocal folds lie so close to the midline, but there will be audible stridor and a compromised airway.

Clinically the position of the vocal fold in the acute phase after section of the recurrent laryngeal nerve is very variable. Though stridor is more common after bilateral lesions and sometimes only audible to the educated ear, the folds may be sufficiently abducted so that there is little problem with airway obstruction at rest, although the voice is always weaker in this situation. The folds are slightly more widely separated in chronic lesions, which renders the voice weaker but with a less precarious airway. Atrophy and fibrosis of paraglottic muscles probably affect the position of paralysed vocal folds in chronic lesions to a greater degree than variations in the strength of the apposing adductor and abductor muscle groups.

For many years, conventional wisdom held that movements of abduction were affected to a greater degree than those of adduction when the recurrent laryngeal nerve was partially damaged (Semon’s law). This effect was thought to reflect the internal segregation within the recurrent laryngeal nerve of axons supplying the laryngeal abductor muscles. The hypothesis was later undermined by the demonstration that axons destined for particular laryngeal muscles are randomly distributed within the nerve. The weak abductive action of cricothyroid that is said to produce lengthening of the vocal folds has been suggested as the explanation for the relative sparing of abduction in these lesions, but is difficult to reconcile with the alternative view that cricothyroid may be a slight adductor of the vocal folds (Mu and Sanders 2009, Wadie et al 2013). It is likely that predicting the effect of partial lesions of the recurrent laryngeal nerve is complicated by the variable patterns of anastomoses between the laryngeal nerves. For further reading, see Aronson and Bless (2009) and Blitzer et al (2009).

Vagus nerve in the thorax

Preganglionic parasympathetic axons arise from neuronal cell bodies in the dorsal motor nucleus of the vagus in the medulla oblongata. Those destined for the thoracic viscera travel in the pulmonary, cardiac and oesophageal branches of the vagus nerve and synapse in minute ganglia in the walls of the target viscera. Axons travelling in cardiac branches join the cardiac plexuses and synapse in ganglia distributed freely over both atria, the interatrial septum and peri-nodal subepicardial tissue. Postganglionic fibres are distributed to the atria and the atrioventricular bundle and are concentrated around the sinuatrial and, to a lesser extent, the atrioventricular nodes. Cardiac branches slow the heart rate and diminish the force of contraction and may indirectly influence ventricular muscle via their effect on the atrioventricular node. The direct postganglionic parasympathetic innervation of the ventricles is sparse. The smaller branches of the coronary arteries are innervated mainly by parasympathetic vagal neurones, whereas the larger arteries are innervated mainly by sympathetic neurones. All cardiac branches of the vagus nerves contain both afferent and efferent fibres. Pulmonary branches contain axons that synapse in ganglia of the pulmonary plexuses: they are motor (bronchoconstrictor) to the circular non-striated muscle fibres of the bronchi and bronchioles (and therefore bring about bronchoconstriction), and secretomotor to the mucous glands of the respiratory epithelium.

Right vagus nerve

The right vagus nerve descends posterior to the right internal jugular vein in the neck and crosses the first part of the right subclavian artery to enter the thorax; the ansa subclavia is lateral, and the phrenic nerve is further lateral. After giving off the right recurrent laryngeal nerve, it descends through the superior mediastinum, at first posterior to the right brachiocephalic vein, and then lateral to the trachea and posteromedial to the superior vena cava. Superiorly, the right mediastinal part of the parietal pleura and superior lobe of the lung are lateral; inferiorly, the azygos vein and its arching terminal portion separate the right vagus nerve from the parietal pleura (see Fig. 56.7A). The nerve next passes posterior to the right main bronchus and lies on the posterior aspect of the right lung hilum. Here, it gives off posterior bronchial branches that unite with rami from the second to fifth/sixth thoracic sympathetic ganglia to form the right posterior pulmonary plexus. Two or three branches descend from the inferior part of this plexus on the posterior aspect of the oesophagus to join a left vagal branch and form the posterior oesophageal plexus. The anterior vagal trunk, containing nerve fibres from both vagus nerves, leaves the plexus and passes inferiorly on the posterior surface of the oesophagus, entering the abdomen by passing through the oesophageal hiatus in the respiratory diaphragm.

Left vagus nerve

The left vagus nerve enters the thorax posterior to the left brachiocephalic vein, between the left common carotid artery (anterior) and left subclavian artery (posterior). It descends through the superior mediastinum, crosses the left side of the aortic arch, gives off the left recurrent laryngeal nerve and then passes posterior to the left lung hilum (see Fig. 56.7B). Superior to the aortic arch, it is crossed anterolaterally by the left phrenic nerve, and on the arch, it is crossed laterally by the left superior intercostal vein and sometimes by a continuation of the accessory hemiazygos vein. Posterior to the hilum of the left lung, the left vagus nerve gives off posterior bronchial branches that unite with rami of the second to fourth thoracic sympathetic ganglia to form the left posterior pulmonary plexus. Two or three branches descend anteriorly on the oesophagus and join with a ramus from the right posterior pulmonary plexus to form the anterior oesophageal plexus. The posterior vagal trunk, containing nerve fibres from both vagus nerves, passes inferiorly on the anterior surface of the oesophagus and enters the abdomen through the oesophageal hiatus. Numerous branches from the anterior vagal and left sympathetic trunks are distributed to the descending thoracic aorta. This pathway transmits the typical intense, excruciating pain of an intramural aortic haematoma from aortic dissection or laceration.

Vagus nerve in the abdomen

The vagus nerves supply parasympathetic innervation to the abdominal viscera as far as the distal transverse colon, i.e. they supply the derivatives of the foregut and midgut, whereas the derivatives of the hindgut are supplied by parasympathetic fibres travelling via the pelvic splanchnic nerves; the overlap between these two supplies is variable. The vagal trunks are derived from the oesophageal plexus and enter the abdomen via the oesophageal hiatus, closely related to the anterior and posterior walls of the abdominal part of the oesophagus (see Fig. 56.6). The anterior vagal trunk is mostly derived from the left vagus and the posterior vagal trunk from the right vagus. The nerves supply the abdominal part of the oesophagus and stomach directly. The anterior vagal trunk gives off a hepatic branch, which innervates the liver and its vasculature, including the gallbladder and bile ducts, and the other structures in the free edge of the lesser omentum (hepatoduodenal ligament). The posterior vagal trunk supplies branches to the coeliac plexus: these fibres frequently constitute the largest portion of the fibres contributing to the plexus and arise directly from the posterior vagal trunk and from its gastric branch, and run beneath the peritoneum, deep to the posterior wall of the superior part of the omental bursa, to reach the coeliac plexus. Their synaptic relays with postganglionic neurones are situated in the myenteric (Auerbach’s) and submucosal (Meissner’s) plexuses in the wall of the hollow viscera.

Accessory nerve

The accessory nerve is the eleventh cranial nerve: its integrity is fundamental to thoracoscapular function and essential for scapulohumeral rhythm (Camp and Birch 2011).

Traditionally, it has been described as having a cranial root composed of a variable number of small rootlets that emerge from the post-olivary groove of the dorsolateral medulla, caudal to the rootlets of the vagus, and a spinal root composed of fibres derived from the cervical segments of the spinal cord (see below). According to this description, the cranial rootlets carry axons of motor neurones located in the caudal part of the nucleus ambiguus, and the spinal rootlets carry axons of motor neurones located in a nucleus in the ventral horn of the cervical spinal cord in line with the nucleus ambiguus. The spinal root ascends within the vertebral canal and enters the skull via the foramen magnum. The cranial and spinal roots join, either before or within the jugular foramen, and the bundle so formed then divides into internal and external branches on leaving the jugular foramen. The internal branch joins the vagus nerve and its fibres innervate branchiomeric muscles via the pharyngeal and laryngeal branches of the vagus nerve and the external branch descends to the neck and innervates sternocleidomastoid and trapezius.

There is an alternative view that the cranial root of the accessory nerve is anatomically and functionally part of the vagus nerve, and that the spinal root is, de facto, the accessory nerve. The issue is not simply one of contentious anatomical terminology; rather, it reflects the need to clarify the relevant microsurgical anatomy in order to minimize potential complications during surgery in the region. Paradoxically, meticulous cadaveric dissection studies, often undertaken stereomicroscopically, have failed to reach a consensus, finding either no connections between rootlets arising from the dorsolateral medulla and the spinal root of the accessory nerve because the cranial root was absent, or significant variations in the arrangement and size of plexiform connections between the cranial rootlets and the spinal root. Plexiform interconnections between neighbouring cranial nerves are not uncommon and are certainly not confined to the accessory and vagus nerves (Shoja et al 2014); their functional significance is often uncertain. (For further reading, see Krammer et al (1987), Lachman et al (2002), Ryan et al (2007), Wiles et al (2007), Benninger and McNeil (2010), Skinner (2011), Liu et al (2014), Tubbs et al (2014).)

Spinal nucleus

The (spinal) accessory nerve arises from an elongated nucleus of motor neurones in the lateral aspect of the ventral horn. Some rootlets emerge directly, while others turn cranially before exiting; their line of exit is irregular rather than linear. They join to form a trunk, the accessory nerve, which ascends intradurally within the vertebral canal between the ligamentum denticulatum and the dorsal roots of the spinal nerves. The nerve enters the skull via the foramen magnum, behind the vertebral artery. It then turns upwards and passes laterally to reach the jugular foramen, which it traverses in a common dural sheath with the vagus, but separated from that nerve by a fold of arachnoid mater.

Hypoglossal Nerve

The hypoglossal nerve is the twelfth cranial nerve and is motor to all the muscles of the tongue except palatoglossus.

Hypoglossal nucleus and central connections

The hypoglossal nucleus lies near the midline in the dorsal medullary grey matter. It is approximately 2 cm long and extends from the hypoglossal trigone in the floor of the fourth ventricle into the closed part of the medulla (see Figs 28.3, 28.5, 28.8). It consists of large motor neurones interspersed with myelinated fibres and is organized into dorsal and ventral nuclear tiers, each divisible into medial and lateral subnuclei. A musculotopic organization of motor neurones within the nuclei corresponds to the structural and functional divisions of tongue musculature. Experimental evidence suggests that motor neurones of the medial division of the hypoglossal nucleus innervate tongue muscles that are orientated in planes transverse to the long axis of the tongue (transverse and vertical intrinsics and genioglossus), whereas motor neurones of the lateral division innervate tongue muscles that are orientated parallel to this axis (styloglossus, hyoglossus, superior and inferior longitudinal).

The hypoglossal nucleus receives corticonuclear fibres from the precentral gyrus and adjacent areas, predominately from the contralateral hemisphere. The corticonuclear fibres synapse either directly on motor neurones of the nucleus or on interneurones. Most medial hypoglossal subnuclei receive projections from both cerebral hemispheres. The hypoglossal nucleus may connect with the cerebellum via the adjacent perihypoglossal nucleus, and perhaps also with the medullary reticular formation, the trigeminal sensory nucleus and the nucleus solitarius (Holstein 2012).

Hypoglossal fibres emerge from the ventral aspect of the nucleus and traverse the reticular formation lateral to both the medial lemniscus and the medial accessory olivary nucleus. They continue ventrally, between the medial accessory and the principal inferior olivary nuclei, and then curve laterally to emerge from the brainstem as a series of 10–15 rootlets arranged linearly along the preolivary sulcus (see Fig. 28.8) (Yousry et al 2002). These rootlets coalesce into two bundles that exit separately through the hypoglossal canal and unite extradurally.

Extracranial course

The hypoglossal rootlets run laterally behind the vertebral artery, collected into two bundles that perforate the dura mater separately opposite the hypoglossal canal in the occipital bone, and unite after traversing it. The canal is sometimes divided by a spicule of bone. The nerve emerges from the canal in a plane medial to the internal jugular vein, internal carotid artery and glossopharyngeal, vagus and accessory nerves, and passes inferolaterally behind the internal carotid artery and glossopharyngeal and vagus nerves to the interval between the artery and the internal jugular vein (see Fig. 35.8). Here, it makes a half-spiral turn round the inferior vagal ganglion, united to it by connective tissue. It then descends almost vertically between the vessels and anterior to the vagus to a point level with the angle of the mandible, becoming superficial below the posterior belly of digastric and emerging between the internal jugular vein and internal carotid artery. Often associated with a plexus of veins around the junction of the common facial and internal jugular veins (vena comitans nervi hypoglossi), excessive bleeding here during neck dissection can lead to nerve damage. The nerve loops round the inferior sternocleidomastoid branch of the occipital artery, crosses lateral to both internal and external carotid arteries and the loop of the lingual artery a little above the tip of the greater cornu of the hyoid, and is itself crossed by the facial vein (see Figs 35.7A, 35.8, 35.17). The nerve next inclines upwards and forwards on hyoglossus, passing deep to stylohyoid, the tendon of digastric and the posterior border of mylohyoid. Between mylohyoid and hyoglossus, the hypoglossal nerve lies below the deep part of the submandibular gland, the submandibular duct and the lingual nerve, with which it communicates. It then passes on to the lateral aspect of genioglossus, continuing forwards in its substance as far as the tip of the tongue (see Fig. 37.11A). It distributes fibres to styloglossus, hyoglossus and genioglossus and to the intrinsic muscles of the tongue. Cadaveric tongues stained using Sihler’s stain (a whole mount nerve staining technique that renders a large specimen transparent while counterstaining all nerves) or acetylcholinesterase or silver stains, show the basic mammalian intralingual pattern of hypoglossal nerve distribution but with notable differences, even from non-human primates. Thus, many muscle fibres, particularly in the transverse group of intrinsic muscles, contain multiple en grappe motor end-plates (suggesting that they are some variant of slow tonic muscle fibres). Presumably, these specializations facilitate the fine motor control of tongue shape that is required in speech and swallowing (Mu and Sanders 2010) (see Fig. 37.13).

The hypoglossal nerve has meningeal, descending, thyrohyoid, geniohyoid and communicating branches.

Meningeal branches

Meningeal branches leave the nerve in the hypoglossal canal and return through it to supply the diploë of the occipital bone, the dural walls of the occipital and inferior petrosal sinuses, and much of the floor of the anterior wall of the posterior cranial fossa, probably through pathways other than that of the hypoglossal nerve, e.g. upper cervical spinal nerves (see Fig. 25.3B).

Descending branch

The descending branch (descendens hypoglossi) contains fibres from the first cervical spinal nerve. It leaves the hypoglossal nerve when it curves around the occipital artery, and runs down on the carotid sheath. It provides a branch to the superior belly of omohyoid before joining the descendens cervicalis to form the ansa cervicalis (see Figs 35.7A, 35.8).

Nerves to thyrohyoid and geniohyoid

The nerves to thyrohyoid and geniohyoid arise near the posterior border of hyoglossus and are derived from the first cervical ventral ramus.

Communicating branches

The hypoglossal nerve communicates with the sympathetic trunk, the lingual, glossopharyngeal and vagus nerves and the pharyngeal plexus. Near the atlas it is joined by branches from the superior cervical sympathetic ganglion and a filament from the loop between the first cervical ventral ramus and the ascending branch of the second cervical ventral ramus that leaves the hypoglossal nerve as the upper root of the ansa cervicalis. The vagal connections are close to the skull; numerous filaments pass between the hypoglossal nerve and the inferior vagal ganglion in the connective tissue that unites them. As the hypoglossal nerve curves round the occipital artery it receives the ramus lingualis vagi from the pharyngeal plexus. Near the anterior border of hyoglossus it is connected with the lingual nerve by many filaments that ascend on the muscle.

Lesions of the hypoglossal nerve

The hypoglossal nerve may be damaged during neck dissection. Complete hypoglossal division causes unilateral lingual paralysis and eventual hemiatrophy; the protruded tongue deviates to the paralysed side, and, on retraction, the wasted and paralysed side rises higher than the unaffected side. The larynx may deviate towards the active side in swallowing, as a consequence of the unilateral paralysis of the hyoid depressors associated with loss of the first cervical ventral ramus, which runs with the hypoglossal nerve. If paralysis is bilateral, the tongue is motionless. Taste and tactile sensibility are unaffected but articulation is slow and swallowing very difficult.

The hypoglossal nerve is often used to reanimate the face in patients, particularly the elderly, when their facial nerves have been transected. Direct end-to-end, end-to-side or split-nerve grafts are reliable and offer a robust, effective and quick alternative to more complex reanimation procedures.

Spinal Nerves

Spinal nerves are the means by which the central nervous system receives information from, and controls the activities of, the trunk and limbs. There are 31 pairs of spinal nerves (8 cervical, 12 thoracic, 5 lumbar, 5 sacral, 1 coccygeal): they contain a mixture of sensory and motor fibres. The abbreviations C, T, L, S and Co, with appropriate numerals, are commonly applied to individual nerves as their ‘root value’.

Spinal nerves pass through intervertebral foramina. At thoracic, lumbar, sacral and coccygeal levels, the numbered nerve exits the vertebral canal by passing below the pedicle of the corresponding vertebra, e.g. the fourth lumbar nerve (L4) nerve exits the intervertebral foramen between the fourth and fifth lumbar vertebrae. However, in the cervical region, the upper seven cervical nerves (C1–C7) pass above their corresponding vertebrae. The first cervical nerve (C1) exits the vertebral canal between the occipital bone and atlas, and is often termed the suboccipital nerve. The last pair of cervical nerves does not have a correspondingly numbered vertebra and the eighth cervical nerve passes between the seventh cervical and first thoracic vertebrae.

Appearance and orientation of roots at each spinal level

The size and direction of spinal nerve roots vary. The upper four cervical roots are small, while the lower four are large. Cervical dorsal roots have a thickness ratio to the ventral roots of 3:1, which is greater than in other regions. The first dorsal root is an exception, because it is smaller than its ventral counterpart, and is occasionally absent. The first and second cervical spinal roots are short and run almost horizontally to their exits from the vertebral canal, whereas from the third to the eighth cervical levels the roots slope obliquely down. Obliquity and length increase successively, although the distance between spinal attachment and vertebral exit never exceeds the height of one vertebra. There is an alternative view that the upper cervical roots descend, the fifth is horizontal, the sixth to eighth ascend, the first two thoracic roots are horizontal, the next three ascend, the sixth is horizontal and the rest descend (Kubik and Müntener 1969): this view is based on the observation that the cervicothoracic part of the spinal cord grows more in length than other parts.

Thoracic roots, except the first, are small, and the dorsal root only slightly exceeds the ventral in thickness. They increase successively in length. In the lower thoracic region, the roots descend in contact with the spinal cord for at least two vertebrae before emerging from the vertebral canal.

Lower lumbar and upper sacral roots are the largest, and their rootlets are the most numerous. Coccygeal roots are the smallest. Lumbar, sacral and coccygeal roots descend with increasing obliquity to their exits (Kubik and Müntener 1969). The spinal cord ends near the lower border of the first lumbar vertebra, which means that the lengths of successive roots rapidly increase: the consequent collection of roots forms the cauda equina (see Fig. 47.1A). The largest roots, and hence the largest spinal nerves, are continuous with the spinal cervical and lumbar enlargements and innervate the upper and lower limbs.

Spinal ganglia (dorsal root ganglia)

Spinal ganglia (dorsal root ganglia, DRG) are large groups of sensory neurones on the dorsal spinal roots. Each is oval and reddish: its size is related to that of its root. A ganglion is bifid medially where the two fascicles of a dorsal root emerge to enter the spinal cord. Ganglia usually lie in the intervertebral foramina, immediately lateral to the perforation of the dura mater by the roots (see Fig. 47.6A). However, the first cervical ganglion (when present) lies on the vertebral arch of the atlas and the second lies posterior to the lateral atlanto-axial joint; the sacral ganglia lie inside the vertebral canal; and the coccygeal ganglion usually lies within the dura mater. Small aberrant ganglia sometimes occur on the upper cervical dorsal roots between the spinal ganglia and the cord.

Spinal nerves proper

Immediately distal to the spinal ganglia, ventral and dorsal roots unite to form spinal nerves. These very soon divide into dorsal and ventral rami, both of which receive fibres from both roots (see Fig. 47.6A). At all levels above the sacral, this division occurs within the intervertebral foramen. Division of the sacral spinal nerves occurs within the sacral vertebral canal, and the dorsal and ventral rami exit separately through posterior and anterior sacral foramina at each level. Spinal nerves trifurcate at some cervical and thoracic levels, in which case the third branch is called a ramus intermedius. At or distal to its origin, each ventral ramus gives off recurrent meningeal (sinuvertebral) branches and receives a grey ramus communicans from the corresponding sympathetic ganglion. All the thoracic and first and second lumbar ventral rami each contribute a white ramus communicans to the corresponding sympathetic ganglia. The second, third and fourth sacral nerves supply visceral branches that carry a preganglionic parasympathetic outflow direct to the pelvic plexuses.

Cervical spinal nerves enlarge from the first to the sixth nerve. The seventh and eighth cervical and the first thoracic nerves are similar in size to the sixth cervical nerve. The remaining thoracic nerves are relatively small. Lumbar nerves are large, increasing in size from the first to the fifth. The first sacral nerve is larger than the other sacral nerves, which progressively decrease in size. The coccygeal nerves are the smallest spinal nerves.

In the radicular (‘root’) canal and intervertebral foramen, a spinal nerve is related to the spinal artery of that level and its radicular branch, and to a small plexus of veins. At the outer end of the foramen, the nerve may lie above or below transforaminal ligaments. The size of a spinal nerve and associated structures within the intervertebral foramen is not in direct relation to the size of the foramen through which the nerve exits: the fifth lumbar nerve is the largest of the lumbar nerves but its foramen is smaller than those of the first four lumbar nerves, and so it is particularly liable to compression.

Meningeal nerves

Recurrent meningeal (or sinuvertebral) nerves (see Fig. 47.9) occur at all vertebral levels. They are mixed sensory and sympathetic nerves, represented by numerous fine filaments amongst which as many as four larger trunks may be evident. At cervical levels the autonomic roots arise from the grey rami that form the vertebral nerve. At thoracic and lumbar levels, each nerve is formed by a somatic root from the ventral ramus and by an autonomic root from the grey ramus communicans of that segment. Each nerve pursues a recurrent course through the intervertebral foramen, passing ventral to the spinal nerve, to enter the vertebral canal, where it divides into ascending, descending and transverse branches. These branches communicate with corresponding branches from the segments above and below, and from the contralateral side, forming arcades along the floor of the vertebral canal. Meningeal branches of the arcades form a plexus on the ventral surface of the dural sac and nerve root sleeves that attenuates laterally; the posterior paramedian dura is devoid of nerve endings. Skeletal branches are distributed to the posterior longitudinal ligament, the periosteum of the vertebral bodies, and to the posterior and posterolateral aspects of the intervertebral discs (Garcia-Cosamalon et al 2010). Vascular branches accompany the veins and arteries of the vertebral canal and those of the vertebral bodies. The upper three cervical meningeal nerves ascend through the foramen magnum into the posterior cranial fossa, where they innervate the dura mater that covers the clivus; en route, they innervate the median atlanto-axial joint and its ligaments.

Variations of spinal roots and nerves

The courses of spinal roots and nerves in relation to the thecal sac and vertebral and radicular canals may be aberrant. An individual intervertebral foramen may contain a duplicated sheath, nerve and roots, which will then be absent at an adjacent level. Abnormal communications between roots may occur within the vertebral canal. These anomalies have been described and classified for the lumbosacral spine by Neidre and Macnab (1983).

Functional components of spinal nerves

A typical spinal nerve contains somatic efferent fibres and somatic and visceral afferent fibres. Some, but not all, spinal nerves also contain preganglionic autonomic fibres.

Somatic components

Somatic efferent fibres innervate skeletal muscles and are axons of α, β and γ neurones in the spinal ventral grey column. Somatic afferent fibres are the peripheral processes of unipolar neurones in the spinal ganglia and convey impulses into the CNS from receptors in the skin, subcutaneous tissues, muscles, tendons, fasciae and joints.

Visceral components

Visceral efferent fibres

Preganglionic visceral efferent sympathetic fibres are axons of neurones in the spinal intermediolateral grey column throughout the thoracic and upper two or three lumbar segments; they join the sympathetic trunk via corresponding white rami communicantes and synapse with postganglionic neurones that are distributed to smooth muscle, myocardium or exocrine glands.

Preganglionic visceral efferent parasympathetic fibres are axons of neurones in the spinal lateral grey column of the second to fourth sacral segments; they leave the ventral rami of corresponding sacral nerves and synapse in pelvic ganglia. Postganglionic axons are distributed mainly to smooth muscle or glands in the walls of the pelvic viscera.

Visceral afferent fibres

General visceral afferent fibres from the viscera and blood vessels accompany their efferent counterparts. They respond to various stimuli including excessive muscular contraction or distension, ischaemia and inflammation; their neuronal somata are located in the glossopharyngeal and vagal ganglia and in thoracic and lumbosacral dorsal root ganglia (visceral afferent fibres that run mainly with sympathetic efferent fibres). Their central projections reach the brainstem and spinal cord, respectively. Sensory fibres in the vagus are more numerous in the derivatives of the foregut than those of the derivatives of the midgut and are concerned with physiological responses such as satiety, whereas pain and discomfort are mediated by spinal pathways.

The somata of glossopharyngeal general visceral afferents are in the glossopharyngeal ganglia. Their peripheral processes innervate the postsulcal lingual region, the palatine tonsils and pharynx, but they do not innervate taste buds. They also innervate the carotid sinus and the carotid body, which contain receptors sensitive to tension and changes in chemical composition of the blood. Impulses from these receptors are essential to circulatory and respiratory reflexes.

The somata of vagal general visceral afferent fibres are in the superior and inferior vagal ganglia. Their peripheral processes are distributed to terminals in the pharyngeal and oesophageal walls where, acting synergistically with glossopharyngeal visceral afferents in the pharynx, they are concerned with swallowing reflexes. Vagal afferents are also believed to innervate the thyroid and parathyroid glands. In the heart, vagal afferents innervate the walls of the great vessels, the aortic bodies and pressor receptors, where they are stimulated by raised intravascular pressure. In the lungs they are distributed via the pulmonary plexuses. They supply bronchial mucosa, where they are probably involved in cough reflexes; bronchial muscle, where they encircle myocytes and end in tendrils, which are sometimes regarded as muscle spindles and which are believed to be stimulated by change in the length of myocytes; interalveolar connective tissue, where their knob-like endings, together with terminals on myocytes, may evoke Hering–Breuer reflexes; the adventitia of pulmonary arteries, where they may be pressor receptors; and the intima of pulmonary veins, where they may be chemoreceptors. Vagal visceral afferent fibres also end in the gastric and intestinal walls, digestive glands and the kidneys. Fibres ending in the gut and its ducts respond to stretch or contraction. Gastric impulses may evoke sensations of hunger and nausea.

Visceral afferents that enter the spinal cord through spinal nerve roots branch extensively and synapse on viscerosomatic neurones in the dorsal horn and intermediate grey matter. Almost all the central processes of vagal and glossopharyngeal afferent fibres end in the nucleus solitarius of the medulla. About 5% of the vagal afferents project directly to, and terminate in, the upper cervical spinal cord (C1–C2), where they are believed to contribute to referred sensations, as well as to propriospinal mechanisms of nociceptive modulation. Visceral afferents establish connections within the CNS that mediate autonomic reflexes. In addition, afferent impulses probably mediate visceral sensations such as hunger, nausea, sexual excitement, vesical distension, etc. Visceral pain fibres may follow these routes. Although viscera are insensitive to cutting, crushing or burning, excessive tension in smooth muscle and some pathological conditions produce visceral pain. In visceral disease, vague pain may be felt near the viscus itself (visceral pain) or in a cutaneous area or other tissue whose somatic afferents enter spinal segments receiving afferents from the viscus, a phenomenon known as referred pain. If inflammation spreads from a diseased viscus to the adjacent parietal serosa (e.g. the peritoneum), somatic afferents will be stimulated, causing local somatic pain, which is commonly spasmodic. Referred pain is often associated with local cutaneous tenderness. For further reading on visceral pain, see Bielefeldt and Gebhart (2013).

Afferent fibres in pelvic splanchnic nerves innervate pelvic viscera and the distal part of the colon. Vesical receptors are widespread; those in muscle strata are associated with thickly myelinated fibres and are believed to be stretch receptors, possibly activated by contraction. Pain fibres from the bladder and proximal urethra traverse both the pelvic splanchnic nerves and the inferior hypogastric plexus, hypogastric nerves, superior hypogastric plexus and lumbar splanchnic nerves to reach their cell bodies in ganglia on the lower thoracic and upper lumbar dorsal spinal roots; the significance of this dual sensory pathway is uncertain. Lesions of the cauda equina abolish pain from vesical overdistension, but hypogastric section is ineffective. Pain fibres from the uterus traverse the hypogastric plexus and lumbar splanchnic nerves to reach somata in the lowest thoracic and upper lumbar spinal ganglia, and hypogastric division may relieve dysmenorrhoea. Afferents from the uterine cervix traverse the pelvic splanchnic nerves to reach their somata in the upper sacral spinal ganglia; stretching the cervix uteri causes pain but cauterization and biopsy excisions do not.

In general, afferent fibres that accompany pre- and postganglionic sympathetic fibres have a segmental arrangement and end in spinal cord segments from which preganglionic fibres innervate the region or viscus concerned. General visceral afferents entering thoracic and upper lumbar spinal segments are largely concerned with pain. Nociceptive impulses from the pharynx, oesophagus, stomach, intestines, kidneys, ureter, gallbladder and bile ducts seem to be carried in sympathetic pathways. Cardiac nociceptive impulses enter the spinal cord in the first to fifth thoracic spinal nerves, mainly via the middle and inferior cardiac nerves, but some fibres pass directly to the spinal nerves. It is said that there are no general visceral afferents in the superior cardiac nerves. Peripherally, the fibres pass through the cardiac plexuses and along the coronary arteries. Myocardial anoxia may evoke symptoms of angina pectoris in which pain is typically presternal, and is also referred to much of the left chest, and radiates to the left shoulder, the medial aspect of the left arm, along the left side of the neck to the jaw and occiput, and down to the epigastrium. Cardiac afferents carried in vagal cardiac branches are concerned with the reflex depression of cardiac activity. Ureteric pain fibres, also running with sympathetic fibres, are presumably involved in the agonizing renal colic that follows obstruction by calculi. Afferent fibres from the testis and ovary run through the corresponding plexuses to somata in the tenth and eleventh thoracic dorsal root ganglia.

Some primary afferent neurones, innervating the gut, lungs, heart and blood vessels, also appear to have an efferent function in that they release transmitters from their peripheral endings during the axon reflex. The primary substances released in this way are substance P, calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP) and ATP. These act on target cells to produce vasodilation, increased venular permeability, changes in smooth muscle contractility, degranulation of mast cells and a variety of effects on leukocytes and fibroblasts, a process collectively known as ‘peripheral neurogenic inflammation’. The local release of such substances may play a trophic role in the maintenance of tissue integrity and repair in response to injury (for further reading, see Xanthos and Sandkühler (2014)).

Rami of the Spinal Nerves

Spinal nerves exit from the vertebral canal via their corresponding intervertebral foramina. They then divide to form a large ventral (anterior) ramus and a smaller dorsal (posterior) ramus. In general terms, the ventral rami innervate the limbs and the muscles and skin of the anterolateral trunk. The axons within the ventral rami serving the neck, upper and lower limbs are redistributed within cervical, brachial and lumbosacral plexuses, respectively. Thoracic ventral rami run independently and retain a largely segmental distribution. Dorsal (posterior) rami of spinal nerves are usually smaller than the ventral rami and are directed posteriorly. Retaining a segmental distribution, all, except for the first cervical, fourth and fifth sacral and the coccygeal, divide into medial and lateral branches that supply the muscles and skin of the posterior regions of the neck and trunk (see Fig. 47.8).

Dorsal rami

Cervical dorsal spinal rami

Each cervical spinal dorsal ramus, except the first, divides into medial and lateral branches that all innervate muscles. In general, only medial branches of the second to fourth, and usually the fifth, supply the skin. Except for the first and second, each dorsal ramus passes posteriorly medial to a posterior intertransverse muscle (which it supplies), curving round the articular process into the interval between semispinalis capitis and semispinalis cervicis.

First cervical dorsal ramus (suboccipital nerve)

The first cervical dorsal ramus, the suboccipital nerve, is larger than the ventral (see Fig. 46.78). It emerges superior to the posterior arch of the atlas and inferior to the vertebral artery, and enters the suboccipital triangle to supply rectus capitis posterior major and minor, obliquus capitis superior and inferior, and semispinalis capitis. A filament from the branch to inferior oblique joins the second dorsal ramus. The suboccipital nerve occasionally has a cutaneous branch that accompanies the occipital artery to the scalp, and connects with the greater and lesser occipital nerves. It may also communicate with the accessory nerve.

Second cervical dorsal ramus

The second cervical dorsal ramus is slightly larger than the ventral and all the other cervical dorsal rami (see Figs 36.22, 46.78). It runs between the lamina of the axis and inferior oblique, below which it divides into a large medial and smaller lateral branch. The dorsal ramus or its medial branch receives communicating branches from the first cervical dorsal ramus that pass both through and around inferior oblique. A descending communicating branch crosses the facet joint between the second and third cervical vertebrae to reach the third cervical dorsal ramus.

Greater occipital nerve

The medial branch, termed the greater occipital nerve, passes transversely across inferior oblique deep to semispinalis capitis, which it innervates. Near the origin of inferior oblique, it turns rostrally along rectus capitis posterior major, where it receives a communicating branch from the third occipital nerve before turning dorsally to pierce semispinalis capitis. It emerges on to the scalp by passing above an aponeurotic sling between trapezius and sternocleidomastoid near their occipital attachments. It ascends with the occipital artery and divides into branches that connect with the third occipital and lesser occipital nerves, and which supply the back of the auricle and the skin of the scalp as far forwards as the coronal suture. The lateral branch of the second cervical dorsal ramus supplies longissimus capitis, semispinalis capitis and splenius capitis, and sends a communicating branch to the lateral branch of the third cervical dorsal ramus.

Greater occipital neuralgia

Greater occipital neuralgia is a syndrome of pain and paraesthesiae felt in the distribution of the greater occipital nerve. This is usually caused by damage or irritation to the greater occipital nerve but more rarely can result from a similar process in the lesser occipital nerve or both greater and lesser occipital nerves. A similar syndrome may be caused by upper facet joint arthritis involving the second cervical root (Vanelderen et al 2010).

Third cervical dorsal ramus

The third cervical dorsal ramus is intermediate in size between the second and fourth. It courses back round the articular pillar of the third cervical vertebra, medial to the posterior intertransverse muscle, and divides into medial and lateral branches. The lateral branch passes dorsally across the surface of semispinalis capitis to supply it and the overlying longissimus capitis and splenius capitis. It receives a communicating branch from the lateral branch of the second cervical dorsal ramus, and sends a similar branch to the lateral branch of the fourth cervical dorsal ramus. The deep medial branch curves dorsally and medially around the waist of the articular pillar before ending in multifidus. It sends an articular branch to the facet joint between the third and fourth cervical vertebrae, and may also send a branch into semispinalis capitis. The superficial medial branch, the third occipital nerve, curves around the lateral and dorsal surfaces of the facet joint between the second and third cervical vertebrae, which it supplies. It continues transversely, deep to semispinalis, which it supplies, and sends a communicating branch to the greater occipital nerve. Just above the second cervical spinal process, the third occipital nerve turns dorsally to pierce semispinalis capitis, splenius capitis and trapezius, and becomes cutaneous over a small area immediately below the superior nuchal line. Communicating branches join the cutaneous branches of the greater and lesser occipital nerves.

Dorsal rami of the lower five cervical nerves

The dorsal rami of the lower five cervical nerves curve back round the vertebral articular pillars and divide into lateral and medial branches. The lateral branches supply longissimus cervicis, splenius cervicis and iliocostalis cervicis. The medial branches curve around the lateral and dorsal surfaces of the articular pillar of their segment, deep to semispinalis capitis. They send articular branches to the facet joints above and below their course before entering and supplying multifidus. Terminal branches reach interspinalis at each segment. Cutaneous branches arise consistently from the fourth, and commonly from the fifth, sixth and eighth, but not usually from the seventh medial branches. These branches pass across multifidus or through semispinalis cervicis and turn dorsally around the medial border of semispinalis capitis, to pierce splenius cervicis and trapezius and reach the skin.

Thoracic dorsal spinal rami

The dorsal rami of the thoracic spinal nerves supply the intrinsic muscles of the back and the overlying postvertebral skin on a segmental basis (see Figs 46.3, 47.8). At each segmental level, they pass dorsally through an aperture bounded by the transverse processes superiorly and inferiorly, the facet joint medially and the superior costotransverse ligament laterally. Thereafter, each dorsal ramus follows a prolonged course laterally, between the anterior lamella of the superior costotransverse ligament anteriorly, and the costolamellar ligament and the posterior lamella of the superior costotransverse ligament posteriorly. In this narrow space, the dorsal ramus divides into lateral and medial branches. The lateral branches continue laterally as far as the costotransverse joint, above which they turn dorsally and inferiorly to supply levatores costarum, and enter longissimus thoracis and iliocostalis. Lateral branches from the upper six thoracic dorsal rami remain intramuscular. Those from the lower six levels emerge from iliocostalis lumborum to pierce serratus posterior inferior and latissimus dorsi in line with the costal angles. They descend across as many as four ribs before becoming superficial. The twelfth thoracic lateral branch sends a filament medially along the iliac crest and then passes down to the anterior gluteal skin. Some upper thoracic lateral branches may become cutaneous.

Each medial branch hooks dorsally around the lateral margin of the posterior lamella of the superior costotransverse ligament, lying a variable distance above the tip of the transverse process. At the first to fourth, and at the ninth and tenth thoracic levels, the medial branches cross the superior tip of the transverse process to turn inferiorly and medially across the posterior surface of the transverse process, lying between the attachment sites of multifidus medially and semispinalis laterally. Each nerve continues this oblique course to supply multifidus and semispinalis. At the fifth to eighth thoracic levels, the medial branches assume a course parallel to that of other levels, but do not reach the transverse process, instead passing superior and dorsal to the plane of the transverse processes. At the eleventh and twelfth levels, in keeping with the relatively short transverse processes at these levels, the medial branches run close to the superior articular processes. Each medial branch supplies articular branches to the facet joints above and below its course. Medial branches of the upper six thoracic dorsal rami furnish cutaneous branches that pierce trapezius and the rhomboids to reach the skin near the spinous processes. Cutaneous branches may occasionally arise from the medial branches of the lower six thoracic dorsal rami.

Lumbar dorsal spinal rami

After leaving its spinal nerve, each of the first to fourth lumbar dorsal rami passes through an aperture in the dorsal leaf of the intertransverse ligament just above a transverse process (see Fig. 47.10). Each dorsal ramus supplies the overlying medial intertransverse muscle before dividing into lateral and medial branches. The lateral branches supply the longissimus and iliocostalis components of the lumbar erector spinae. The upper three lumbar lateral branches emerge from the lateral border of iliocostalis lumborum and pierce the aponeurosis of latissimus dorsi to become cutaneous. They cross the iliac crest to reach the gluteal skin; some reach as far as the level of the greater trochanter. Medial branches cross the junction of the superior articular process and transverse process, and hook medially between the mammillary and accessory processes, deep to the mammillo-accessory ligament. Medial to the ligament, each medial branch sends articular branches to the facet joints above and below its course, before entering multifidus, which it supplies. Medial branch blocks are quite useful in the treatment of facet-mediated low back pain. Terminal branches reach interspinalis at each segment.

The fifth dorsal ramus has a longer course than other dorsal rami. It arches over the ala of the sacrum, lying against the root of the first sacral superior articular process. Opposite the base of the lumbosacral joint, it sends a branch into the lowest fibres of longissimus thoracis, and a communicating branch to the first sacral dorsal ramus, before terminating as a branch that hooks around the lumbosacral joint to end in multifidus.

Sacral dorsal spinal rami

Sacral dorsal rami are small, diminishing in size inferiorly; other than the fifth, all emerge through the dorsal sacral foramina. The upper three are covered at their exit by multifidus, and divide into medial and lateral branches. Medial branches are small and end in multifidus. Lateral branches join together and with branches of the last lumbar and fourth sacral dorsal rami to form loops dorsal to the sacrum. Branches from these loops run dorsal to the sacrotuberous ligament and form a second series of loops under gluteus maximus. From these, two or three gluteal branches pierce gluteus maximus (along a line from the posterior superior iliac spine to the coccygeal apex) to supply the posterior gluteal skin.

The dorsal rami of the fourth and fifth sacral nerves are small and lie caudal to multifidus. They unite with each other and with the coccygeal dorsal ramus to form loops dorsal to the sacrum; filaments from these supply the skin over the coccyx.

Coccygeal dorsal spinal ramus

The coccygeal dorsal spinal ramus does not divide into medial and lateral branches. It communicates with the fourth and fifth sacral dorsal rami.

Ventral rami

Ventral rami innervate the skin of the anterolateral neck and trunk and the skin covering the upper and lower limbs. The second to the fourth cervical ventral rami (C2– C4) innervate the skin of the neck (branches from the cervical plexus); the fifth to the eighth cervical ventral rami (C5–C8) and the first thoracic ventral ramus (T1) innervate the skin of the upper limb (branches from the brachial plexus); the second thoracic to the first lumbar ventral rami (T2–L1) innervate the skin of the anterolateral trunk; the first or second thoracic ventral rami to the third sacral ventral ramus (L1/2–S3) innervate the skin of the lower limb and perineum (branches of the lumbar and sacral plexuses). Ventral rami supply the flexor musculature of the neck and body wall segmentally and the infrahyoid muscles and the muscles of the limbs via cervical (C1–C4), brachial (C5–T1/2), lumbar (L1–L4/5) and sacral (L4/5–S3) plexuses.

Cervical ventral rami

Broadly speaking, cervical ventral rami innervate the anterior and lateral groups of prevertebral muscles; the respiratory diaphragm (via the phrenic nerve); the muscles and joints of the upper limb and most of the infrahyoid muscles; and the skin of the anterolateral neck, the radial side of the upper limb and the palmar and dorsal surfaces of the hand (via the cervical and brachial plexuses).

Cervical ventral rami, except the first, appear between the anterior and posterior intertransverse muscles. The upper four form the cervical plexus, and the lower four, together with most of the first thoracic ventral ramus, form the brachial plexus. Each receives at least one grey ramus communicans, the upper four from the superior cervical sympathetic ganglion, the fifth and sixth from the middle ganglion, and the seventh and eighth from the cervicothoracic ganglion.

The first cervical ventral ramus, the suboccipital nerve, emerges above the posterior arch of the atlas, and passes forwards lateral to its lateral mass and medial to the vertebral artery. It supplies rectus capitis lateralis, emerges medial to it, descends anterior to the transverse process of the atlas and posterior to the internal jugular vein, and joins the ascending branch of the second cervical ventral ramus.

The second cervical ventral ramus issues between the vertebral arches of the atlas and axis. It ascends between their transverse processes, passes anterior to the first posterior intertransverse muscle and emerges lateral to the vertebral artery, generally between longus capitis and levator scapulae. The ramus divides into an ascending branch, which joins the first cervical nerve, and a descending branch, which joins the ascending branch of the third cervical ventral ramus.

The third cervical ventral ramus appears between longus capitis and scalenus medius. The remaining ventral rami emerge between scalenus anterior and the scalenus medius.

Phrenic nerve

The phrenic nerve is a mixed somatic sensory and motor nerve that provides the sole motor supply to the respective hemirespiratory diaphragm. It is derived mostly from the ipsilateral fourth cervical ventral ramus, with contributions from the ipsilateral third and fifth cervical ventral rami (see Figs 35.17–35.18). The nerve is formed at the upper part of the lateral border of scalenus anterior and descends almost vertically across its anterior surface behind the prevertebral fascia. It descends posterior to sternocleidomastoid, the inferior belly of omohyoid (near its intermediate tendon), the internal jugular vein, transverse cervical and suprascapular arteries and, on the left, the thoracic duct. At the root of the neck, the phrenic nerve runs anterior to the second part of the subclavian artery, from which it is separated by scalenus anterior (some accounts state that on the left side the nerve passes anterior to the first part of the subclavian artery) and posterior to the subclavian vein. The phrenic nerve crosses serratus anterior from lateral to medial (lying under the prevertebral fascia) and enters the thorax by crossing medially anterior to the internal thoracic artery.

In the neck, each nerve receives variable filaments from the cervical sympathetic ganglia or their branches and may also connect with internal thoracic sympathetic plexuses.

Within the thoracic cavity, the right and left phrenic nerves descend anterior to the pulmonary hila, between the fibrous pericardium and mediastinal parietal pleura, accompanied by the pericardiacophrenic vessels. Each phrenic nerve supplies sensory branches to the mediastinal pleura, fibrous pericardium and parietal layer of serous pericardium: the right phrenic nerve supplies the part of the right crus that lies to the right of the oesophagus, and the left phrenic nerve supplies the left crus and the part of the right crus that lies on the left of the oesophagus.

The right and left phrenic nerves differ in their intrathoracic relationships ([Rajanna 1947]).

Right phrenic nerve

The right phrenic nerve is shorter and more vertical than the left. At the root of the neck it is separated from the second part of the right subclavian artery by scalenus anterior (see Fig. 55.10A). It then passes inferomedially through the superior thoracic aperture between the first part of the right subclavian artery and the right subclavian vein. Occasionally, the right or left phrenic nerves may pass anterior to, or through the anterior wall of, the respective subclavian vein (Paraskevas et al 2011). Around the level of the first rib or the first costal cartilage, the right phrenic nerve crosses the right internal thoracic artery either superiorly between the artery and the first rib, or inferiorly, pressed against the artery by the apex of the right lung and its covering pleura (Owens et al 1994). The nerve continues to descend, passing immediately lateral to the right brachiocephalic vein, the superior vena cava, the fibrous pericardium covering the right side of the right atrium and the inferior vena cava. It branches just superior to, or at the level of, the respiratory diaphragm.

Left phrenic nerve

At the root of the neck, the left phrenic nerve commonly leaves the medial border of scalenus anterior and passes anterior to the first part of the left subclavian artery and posterior to the left subclavian vein and the thoracic duct (see Fig. 55.10B). Sometimes the right and left phrenic nerves are symmetrical in their cervical course, in which case the left phrenic nerve is initially separated from the second part of the left subclavian artery by scalenus anterior. After passing through the superior thoracic aperture the left phrenic nerve crosses the left internal thoracic artery, most commonly superiorly, around the level of the first rib or the first costal cartilage (Owens et al 1994). It descends across the medial aspect of the apex of the left lung and its pleural covering to pass between the left common carotid and left subclavian arteries. The nerve then descends anteromedially and passes anterior and close to the left vagus nerve while in the region superior to the aortic arch and posterior to the left brachiocephalic vein. It continues inferiorly, passing anterior to the left superior intercostal vein, the aortic arch and the left pulmonary hilum, after which it passes inferolaterally and to the left, over the fibrous pericardium covering the left atrium and left ventricle (see Fig. 55.9). As it passes over the fibrous pericardium, the left phrenic nerve is located more anterior than the right phrenic nerve and is therefore at greater risk of damage during the placement of surgical incisions to access the pericardial cavity.

Diaphragmatic relationships

The right phrenic nerve passes through the central tendon of the respiratory diaphragm, either via the caval foramen or just lateral to it. The left phrenic nerve passes through the muscular part of the respiratory diaphragm anterior to the central tendon, just lateral to the fibrous pericardium covering the left pulmonary border of the heart, and posterior to the cardiac apex (see Fig. 55.9). At or slightly superior to the respiratory diaphragm each phrenic nerve supplies fine branches to the parietal pleura that lies above the central part of the diaphragm. Typically, the trunk of each nerve then divides into three branches (anterior or sternal, anterolateral and posterior) as it passes through the respiratory diaphragm (see Fig. 55.1A). The main branches may be submerged in diaphragmatic muscle or lie inferior to it. They supply motor fibres to the muscle and sensory fibres to the peritoneum and pleura related to the central part of the respiratory diaphragm. They also relay proprioceptive fibres from the musculature. The anterior (sternal) branch runs anteromedially towards the sternum and connects with its contralateral counterpart. The anterolateral branch runs to the lateral folia of the central tendon. The short posterior branch divides into a posterolateral ramus that passes posterior to the left or right folia of the central tendon and a posterior ramus that supplies the crura of the respiratory diaphragm. The posterolateral and posterior crural branches may arise separately from the phrenic nerve.

Phrenic ganglia

The right phrenic nerve continues its course inferior to the respiratory diaphragm and frequently connects to the right phrenic ganglion. An additional, smaller, right accessory phrenic ganglion is sometimes located proximally along the phrenic nerve, close to its exit from the caval foramen. The right phrenic ganglion has plexiform communications with the coeliac and aorticorenal ganglia and with the right suprarenal gland (see Fig. 55.11). A left phrenic ganglion is less commonly seen; when present, it exhibits plexiform communications to several autonomic ganglia. Both phrenic nerves and ganglia are closely related to the diaphragmatic crura, therefore sutures for crural approximation in the repair of hiatal hernia must be placed superior to the ganglia in order to avoid iatrogenic injuries to the autonomic supply of the respiratory diaphragm and abdomen (Loukas et al 2016).

Referred pain

Diaphragmatic irritation or pain is frequently felt at the tip of the shoulder, reflecting the common spinal nerve root origins of the phrenic and supraclavicular nerves (the ventral rami of the third and fourth cervical spinal nerves). It usually occurs when there is inflammation of the diaphragmatic parietal pleura, e.g. in basal pneumonia, pleural effusions, malignant disease, or irritation of the diaphragmatic parietal peritoneum, e.g. in pneumoperitoneum or subphrenic abscess, where involuntary diaphragmatic contraction (hiccups) may also occur.

Accessory phrenic nerve

The accessory phrenic nerve is composed of fibres from the fifth cervical ventral ramus that run in a branch of the nerve to subclavius. This lies lateral to the phrenic nerve and descends posterior (occasionally anterior) to the subclavian vein. The accessory phrenic nerve usually joins the phrenic nerve near the first rib but may not do so until near the pulmonary hilum or beyond. The accessory phrenic nerve may be derived from the fourth or sixth cervical ventral rami or from the ansa cervicalis.

Thoracic ventral rami

Thoracic ventral rami, unlike their cervical and lumbar counterparts, have retained a largely segmental distribution to the body wall (see Figs 24.10, 47.7, 53.3). The first to the eleventh intercostal nerves pass in the intercostal spaces between adjacent ribs, and the twelfth (subcostal nerve) passes below the twelfth rib. Each is connected with an adjacent ganglion of the sympathetic trunk by pre- and postganglionic branches (white and grey rami communicantes, respectively) (see Figs 24.13, 53.21). The majority of the intercostal nerves are distributed to the thoracic and, in the case of the more inferiorly located nerves, abdominal walls. The greater part of the first thoracic ventral ramus passes into the brachial plexus (see Fig. 48.6), together with variable proportions of the second and sometimes third thoracic ventral rami via the intercostobrachial nerves. The fourth to sixth intercostal nerves supply only the thoracic wall, whereas the seventh to eleventh nerves supply the thoracic and abdominal walls. The subcostal nerve is distributed to the abdominal wall and skin covering the superior part of the lateral aspect of the gluteal region and thigh. Communicating branches may link the intercostal nerves across the intercostal spaces posteriorly (see Fig. 56.6). The breast is mainly innervated by the anterior and lateral cutaneous branches of the fourth to sixth intercostal nerves. The nipple is innervated by a plexus formed primarily from cutaneous branches of the fourth intercostal nerve.

The ventral rami of the sixth to eleventh intercostal nerves, the subcostal nerve (twelfth thoracic) and first lumbar nerve (iliohypogastric and ilioinguinal nerves) innervate the muscles and skin of the anterior abdominal wall (Rozen et al 2008). The seventh to the twelfth thoracic ventral rami continue anteriorly into the abdominal wall (see Fig. 60.5). Approaching the costal arch, the seventh to tenth intercostal nerves curve medially across the deep surface of the costal cartilages between the digitations of the respiratory diaphragm and transversus abdominis. The subcostal nerve often gives a branch to the first lumbar ventral ramus (dorsolumbar nerve), and in these cases, therefore, contributes to the lumbar plexus. It accompanies the subcostal vessels along the inferior border of the twelfth rib, passing posterior to the lateral arcuate ligament and kidney, and anterior to the proximal part of quadratus lumborum.

All these segmental nerves run anteriorly within a thin layer of fascia in the neurovascular plane between transversus abdominis and internal abdominal oblique, where they branch and interconnect with adjacent nerves and give off branches to the lateral musculature (Rozen et al 2008). Cutaneous branches supply the skin of the lateral and anterior abdominal walls. The nerves enter the rectus sheath at its lateral margin by penetrating the posterior lamina of internal abdominal oblique and penetrating rectus abdominis on its posterior aspect. Here they give off muscular branches to rectus abdominis, transversus abdominis and pyramidalis and cutaneous branches that pierce the anterior layer of the rectus sheath to supply overlying skin.

The ninth intercostal nerve supplies skin proximal to the umbilicus, the tenth intercostal nerve supplies skin that consistently includes the umbilicus, and the eleventh intercostal nerve supplies skin distal to the umbilicus (see Figs 24.10, 60.5). The subcostal nerve supplies the skin over the anterior gluteal region just distal to the iliac crest and the skin of the distal abdomen and inguinal region (overlapping with the L1 dermatome in this region) (Lee et al 2008). A typical dermatome map of the anterior abdominal wall is shown in Fig. 24.10. The inferior intercostal nerves and subcostal nerve also provide sensory fibres to the costal parts of the respiratory diaphragm and parietal peritoneum.

The anterolateral abdominal wall muscles are innervated by several segmental nerves and injury to a single nerve rarely causes a clinically detectable loss of muscle tone. The overlap between sequential dermatomes means that significant cutaneous anaesthesia and muscle denervation are appreciated only after at least two sequential nerves have been surgically sectioned.

Peripheral Nerve Plexuses

Cervical plexus

The cervical plexus is formed by the ventral rami of the upper four cervical nerves, and supplies some neck muscles, including most of the infrahyoid group, and areas of skin on the head, neck and chest (see Figs 33.6, 35.5B). It lies in the neck opposite a line drawn down the side of the neck from the root of the auricle to the level of the upper border of the thyroid cartilage. It lies deep to the internal jugular vein, the deep fascia and sternocleidomastoid, and anterior to scalenus medius and levator scapulae. Each ramus, except the first, divides into ascending and descending parts, which unite in communicating loops. Cutaneous branches from the first loop (second and third cervical ventral rami) supply the head and neck, and those from the second loop (third and fourth cervical ventral rami) supply the shoulder and chest. Muscular and communicating branches arise from the same nerves. The branches are superficial or deep: superficial branches perforate the cervical fascia to supply the skin and either ascend (the lesser occipital, great auricular and transverse cervical nerves) or descend (supraclavicular nerves) (see Fig. 35.1B). Deep branches form medial and lateral series and generally supply muscles.

Lesser occipital nerve

The lesser occipital nerve is derived mainly from the second cervical ventral ramus (although fibres from the third cervical nerve may sometimes contribute). It first passes anterior to the plane of the accessory nerve before winding around it and becoming anterior to it. It next ascends along the posterior margin of sternocleidomastoid. Near the cranium it perforates the deep fascia and passes up on to the scalp behind the auricle to supply the skin and connect with the great auricular and greater occipital nerves and the auricular branch of the facial nerve. Its auricular branch supplies the skin on the upper third of the medial aspect of the auricle and connects with the posterior branch of the great auricular nerve. The auricular branch is occasionally derived from the greater occipital nerve. It has been suggested that compression or stretching of the lesser occipital nerve contributes to cervicogenic headache (Lucas et al 1994).

Great auricular nerve

The great auricular nerve is the largest ascending branch of the cervical plexus. It arises from the second and third cervical ventral rami, encircles the posterior border of sternocleidomastoid, perforates the deep fascia and ascends on the muscle beneath platysma with the external jugular vein. On reaching the parotid gland, it divides into anterior and posterior branches. The anterior branch is distributed to the facial skin over the parotid gland and connects in the gland with the facial nerve. This cross-innervation between somatic sensory fibres and parasympathetic secretomotor fibres is considered to be part of the anatomical basis for the phenomenon of gustatory sweating (Frey’s syndrome), seen after parotidectomy with its inherent disruption of the secretomotor nerve supply. The posterior branch supplies the skin over the mastoid process and on the back of the auricle (except its upper part); a filament pierces the auricle to reach the lateral surface, where it is distributed to the lobule and concha. Efforts are made to preserve the posterior branch at parotid surgery in order to avoid a sensory deficit of the auricle. The posterior branch communicates with the lesser occipital nerve, the auricular branch of the vagus and the posterior auricular branch of the facial nerve. Division of the greater auricular nerve during neck surgery results in loss of sensation of a variable amount of the lower half of the auricle, which some patients initially find unpleasant.

Transverse cervical nerve

The transverse cervical nerve arises from the second and third cervical ventral rami. It curves round the posterior border of sternocleidomastoid near its midpoint and runs obliquely forwards, deep to the external jugular vein, to the anterior border of the muscle. It perforates the deep cervical fascia, and divides under platysma into ascending and descending branches that are distributed to the anterolateral areas of the neck. The ascending branches ascend to the submandibular region, forming a plexus with the cervical branch of the facial nerve beneath platysma. Some branches pierce platysma and are distributed to the skin of the upper anterior areas of the neck. The descending branches pierce platysma and are distributed anterolaterally to the skin of the neck.

Supraclavicular nerves

The supraclavicular nerves arise from a common trunk formed from branches from the third and fourth cervical ventral rami and emerge at the posterior border of sternocleidomastoid. Descending under platysma and the deep cervical fascia, the trunk divides into medial, intermediate and lateral (posterior) branches, which diverge to pierce the deep fascia a little above the clavicle. The medial supraclavicular nerves run inferomedially across the external jugular vein and the clavicular and sternal heads of sternocleidomastoid to supply the skin as far as the midline and as low as the second rib. They also supply the sternoclavicular joint. The intermediate supraclavicular nerves cross the clavicle to supply the skin over pectoralis major and deltoid down to the level of the second rib, next to the area of supply of the second thoracic nerve. Overlap between these nerves is minimal. The lateral supraclavicular nerves descend superficially across trapezius and the acromion, supplying the skin of the upper and posterior parts of the shoulder.

Deep branches – medial series

Communicating branches

Communicating branches pass from the loop between the first and second cervical ventral rami to the vagus and hypoglossal nerves and to the sympathetic trunk. The hypoglossal branch later leaves the hypoglossal nerve as a series of branches, namely: the meningeal, superior root of ansa cervicalis, nerves to thyrohyoid and geniohyoid. A branch also connects the fourth and fifth cervical ventral rami. The first four cervical ventral rami each receive a grey ramus communicans from the superior cervical sympathetic ganglion.

The superior root of the ansa cervicalis (descendens hypoglossi) (see Figs 35.7A, 35.8) leaves the hypoglossal nerve where it curves round the occipital artery and then descends anterior to or in the carotid sheath. It contains fibres from the first cervical ventral ramus. After giving a branch to the superior belly of omohyoid, it is joined by the inferior root of the ansa from the second and third cervical ventral rami. The two roots form the ansa cervicalis (ansa hypoglossi), from which branches supply sternohyoid, sternothyroid and the inferior belly of omohyoid. Another branch is said to descend anterior to the vessels into the thorax to join the cardiac and phrenic nerves.

Muscular branches

Muscular branches supply rectus capitis lateralis (C1), rectus capitis anterior (C1, C2), longus capitis (C1–C3) and longus colli (C2–C4). The inferior root of the ansa cervicalis and the phrenic nerve are additional muscular branches.

The inferior root of the ansa cervicalis (nervus descendens cervicalis) (see Figs 35.7A, 35.8) is formed by the union of branches from the second and third cervical ventral rami. It descends on the lateral side of the internal jugular vein, crosses it a little below the middle of the neck, and continues forwards to join the superior root anterior to the common carotid artery, forming the ansa cervicalis (ansa hypoglossi), from which all infrahyoid muscles except thyrohyoid are supplied. The inferior root almost always comes from the second and third cervical ventral rami, but sometimes from the second to fourth, and occasionally from the third alone. Occasionally, it may be derived either from the second alone or from the first to third cervical ventral rami.

Deep branches – lateral series

Communicating branches

Lateral deep branches of the cervical plexus (C2–C4) may connect with the accessory nerve within sternocleidomastoid, the posterior triangle or beneath trapezius.

Muscular branches

Muscular branches are distributed to sternocleidomastoid (C2–C4), trapezius (C2 and possibly C3), levator scapulae (C3, C4) and scalenus medius (C3, C4). Branches to trapezius cross the posterior triangle obliquely below the accessory nerve.

Brachial plexus

The brachial plexus is formed by the union of the ventral rami of the lower four cervical nerves and the greater part of the ventral ramus of the first thoracic spinal nerve. It may also receive contributions from the fourth cervical and second thoracic ventral rami. As its name suggests, its branches supply the muscles, joints and skin of the upper limb.

At its origin, the brachial plexus lies in the posterior triangle of the neck, in the angle between the clavicle and the lower posterior border of sternocleidomastoid. It emerges between the scaleni anterior and medius, superior to the third part of the subclavian artery, and is covered by platysma, deep fascia and skin, through which it is palpable (see Fig. 35.17). It is crossed by the supraclavicular nerves, the nerve to subclavius, the inferior belly of omohyoid, the external jugular vein and the superficial ramus of the transverse cervical artery. The plexus passes posterior to the medial two-thirds of the clavicle, subclavius and the suprascapular vessels, and lies on the first digitation of serratus anterior and subscapularis. In the axilla, the lateral and posterior cords of the brachial plexus are anterior and lateral to the first part of the axillary artery, respectively, and the medial cord is behind the artery. The cords assume their appropriate relations around the second part of the artery, deep to pectoralis major. In the lower axilla, the cords divide into nerves that supply the upper limb (see Fig. 49.35). Other than the medial root of the median nerve, these nerves are related to the third part of the artery in the same way as their cords are related to the second part, i.e. branches of the lateral cord are lateral to the artery, branches of the medial cord are medial, and branches of the posterior cord are posterior.

Blood supply

The blood supply to the brachial plexus is derived from vessels that arise from the subclavian and vertebral arteries. Important branches pass from the vertebral artery to the fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami and the more proximal cervical nerves. Branches from the costocervical trunk provide a rich supply to the eighth cervical and first thoracic ventral rami. Extensive contributions come from the suprascapular and superficial cervical arteries that arise from the thyrocervical trunk. In at least one-third of cases the superficial cervical and dorsal scapular arteries arise from the thyrocervical trunk as the transverse cervical artery. In clinical terms, the arteries arising from the thyrocervical trunk have become the lifeline to the upper limb and must be preserved during operations in cases when the ruptured subclavian artery has not been repaired. The dorsal scapular artery may arise from the third part of the subclavian artery to pass between the upper and middle trunks of the brachial plexus.

Trunks of the brachial plexus

The upper trunk is formed by the fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami, where these nerves emerge from deep to scalenus anterior. The middle trunk is the continuation of the seventh cervical ventral ramus. The lower trunk is formed by the eighth cervical and first thoracic ventral rami, and passes over the anterosuperior surface of the first rib. The first thoracic ventral ramus takes an upward course across the deep face of the neck of the first rib behind the pleura and the vertebral and subclavian arteries towards the lower trunk. The formation of the trunks is fairly consistent; they lie in front of one another rather than side by side, with the subclavian artery passing anteromedially. The phrenic nerve crosses the fifth cervical ventral ramus to pass anteromedially on the surface of scalenus anterior. The upper trunk, its divisions and the suprascapular nerve can all be palpated in the supraclavicular fossa in a subject of normal physique. The examining finger identifies first the subclavian pulse and then the nerves, whilst rolling the fingertip laterally (see Video 48.1).

Divisions of the brachial plexus

The trunks divide into anterior and posterior divisions. The upper trunk divides 2–3 cm above the clavicle, and the divisions of the middle and lower trunks are formed deep to the clavicle. The posterior divisions of the upper and middle trunks are consistently larger than their anterior divisions. The posterior division of the lower trunk is consistently smaller than the anterior division and is absent in about 10% of cases.

Cords of the brachial plexus

The cords are formed by the confluence of divisions: the lateral cord from the anterior divisions of the upper and middle trunks; the posterior cord by all three posterior divisions; and the medial cord by the anterior division of the lower trunk and, sometimes, by a branch from the anterior division of the middle trunks. The divisions of the trunks and the formation of the cords represent an important anatomical and functional differentiation. The posterior divisions and posterior cord innervate postaxial (extensor) musculature; the anterior divisions and the lateral and medial cords innervate preaxial (flexor) musculature.

The formation and relations of the three cords are variable and, indeed, their designations somewhat misleading. Immediately inferior to the clavicle, the posterior cord is lateral, the medial cord is posterior, and the lateral cord is anterior, in relation to the axillary artery; the cords assume their appropriate relations about the axillary artery deep to pectoralis minor. There is considerable variation in this arrangement; most commonly, the axillary artery lies anterior to the three cords and the median nerve.

The branches of the posterior cord, the largest of the three trunks, are consistent. In sequence, they are the upper subscapular, thoracodorsal, lower subscapular, axillary and radial nerves. The branches of the medial cord are usually predictable; the medial pectoral nerve and medial cutaneous nerve of the forearm are succeeded by the division into the medial root of the median nerve and the ulnar nerve. The ulnar nerve may arise as two or three branches. The greatest variation in the formation of trunk nerves is found within the lateral cord. Occasionally, the musculocutaneous nerve arises more distally than usual, either directly from the lateral cord as two or three branches or even from the median nerve itself. Sometimes, the highest of these branches enters coracobrachialis no more than 2 or 3 cm below the coracoid process. The lateral root of the median nerve may arise as two or three branches, and in some cases, it appears as a branch of the musculocutaneous nerve.

Terminal branches of the brachial plexus

Suprascapular nerve

The suprascapular nerve (fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami) is a large branch of the upper trunk: it is usually the first branch of the upper trunk but frequently arises directly from the fifth cervical ventral ramus (see Figs 35.17, 49.35).

It runs laterally, deep to trapezius and omohyoid, and enters the supraspinous fossa through the suprascapular notch inferior to the superior transverse scapular ligament. It runs deep to supraspinatus and supplies it. It curves round the lateral border of the spine of the scapula with the suprascapular artery to reach the infraspinous fossa, where it gives two branches to infraspinatus and articular rami to the glenohumeral and acromioclavicular joints. The suprascapular nerve rarely has a cutaneous branch: when present, it pierces deltoid close to the tip of the acromion and supplies the skin of the proximal third of the arm within the territory of the axillary nerve.

The suprascapular nerve is essential for abduction and lateral rotation at the glenohumeral joint. When the nerve or the rotator cuff is torn, or both are injured, the ISHA is so reduced that the patient is unable to move the arm away from the body. At rest, the head of the humerus drops inferiorly and migrates proximally in attempted abduction (see Fig. 49.41). In isolated cuff tears, the ISHA opens to about 30° or even more. In isolated axillary palsy, the ISHA is sometimes normal, or, more often, reduced by about 20° (see Figs 49.42–49.43).

Nerve to subclavius

The slender nerve to subclavius (fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami) springs from the upper trunk and passes anteriorly. It descends anterior to the plexus and the subclavian artery and passes above the subclavian vein to supply subclavius.

Lateral pectoral nerve

The lateral pectoral nerve (fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami) is larger than the medial, and may arise either from the anterior divisions of the upper and middle trunks, or by a single branch from the lateral cord, just above or deep to the clavicle. It crosses anterior to the axillary artery and vein, pierces the clavipectoral fascia and supplies the deep surface of pectoralis major. It sends a branch to the medial pectoral nerve, forming a loop in front of the first part of the axillary artery to supply some fibres to pectoralis minor.

Medial pectoral nerve

The medial pectoral nerve (eighth cervical and first thoracic ventral rami) branches from the medial cord while the latter lies posterior to the axillary artery and curves forwards between the axillary artery and vein. Anterior to the artery, it joins a ramus of the lateral pectoral nerve and enters the deep surface of pectoralis minor, which it supplies. Two or three branches pierce pectoralis minor and others may pass round its inferior border to end in pectoralis major.

Upper (superior) subscapular nerve

The superior subscapular nerve is smaller than the inferior. It arises from the posterior cord (fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami), enters subscapularis at a high level, and is frequently double.

Lower (inferior) subscapular nerve

The inferior subscapular nerve arises from the posterior cord (fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami). It supplies the lower part of subscapularis and ends in teres major, which is sometimes supplied by a separate branch.

Thoracodorsal nerve

The thoracodorsal nerve arises from the posterior cord (sixth, seventh and eighth cervical ventral rami) between the subscapular nerves. It accompanies the subscapular artery along the posterior axillary wall and supplies latissimus dorsi, reaching its distal border (see Fig. 49.29). The muscles, joints and skin of the upper limb are innervated by the fifth, sixth, seventh and eighth cervical ventral rami and nearly all of the first thoracic ventral ramus, collectively forming the brachial plexus (see Figs 48.6–48.7). A branch from the fourth and fifth cervical rami, which contributes to the innervation of the glenohumeral and elbow flexor muscles, is seen occasionally at operation: a muscular contribution from the second thoracic ventral ramus is rare. The rami enter the posterior triangle of the neck between scalenus anterior and medius. Rami from the seventh and eighth cervical ventral rami are the largest (C8 contains about 30,000 myelinated axons) and those from the fifth cervical ventral ramus and the first thoracic ventral ramus are the smallest (between 15,000 and 20,000 myelinated axons). An adult brachial plexus contains between 120,000 and 150,000 myelinated axons, of which 25% innervate the shoulder girdle and glenohumeral joint. The proportion of motor fibres is greatest in the fifth and eighth cervical ventral rami; the sensory contribution is greatest in the seventh cervical ventral ramus. A complex interchange of branches, before the main nerves of the upper limb are formed, produces the trunks, divisions and cords of the brachial plexus.

Dorsal scapular nerve

The dorsal scapular nerve arises above the clavicle from the proximal segment of the fifth cervical ventral ramus. It passes posteriorly, piercing scalenus medius, to run down in the plane between levator scapulae and serratus posterior superior and the posterior scalene muscles. It continues along the anterior border of the rhomboid muscles about 1.5 cm medial to the vertebral border of the scapula and is closely related to the dorsal scapular artery. The dorsal scapular nerve innervates the rhomboid muscles and, together with branches from the third and fourth cervical ventral rami, it supplies levator scapulae.

Long thoracic nerve (nerve to serratus anterior)

The long thoracic nerve is formed by branches that arise above the clavicle from the proximal segments of the ventral rami of the fifth, sixth and seventh cervical ventral rami. It innervates serratus anterior, a muscle that is essential for the function of the thoracoscapular joint. The muscular branches from the rami join deep to scalenus medius, and the trunk passes down posterolateral to the muscle, on the floor of the posterior triangle deep to the suprascapular nerve. The branches from the fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami are the largest. The nerve follows a sinuous course deep to the investing fascia covering the anterior faces of the digitations of serratus anterior. It is accompanied here by a branch of the thoracodorsal artery, and inclines posterolaterally towards the mid-axillary line.

The long thoracic nerve is frequently injured during operations around the first rib, in the posterior triangle and in the axilla, and by misplaced intercostal drains. It is particularly susceptible to involvement in neuralgic amyotrophy. Serratus palsy is usual in preganglionic injury to the ventral rami of the fifth, sixth and seventh cervical ventral rami. Pain and loss of function are usual and are only slightly less than those seen after accessory nerve palsy. The signs are characteristic. The active ISHA is, on average, 130°; this is the only nerve lesion in which the active ISHA actually exceeds the total range of active abduction. The scapula is pulled upwards and towards the spine by the unopposed action of trapezius (see Fig. 49.39), an action that is increased by the weight of the limb, which contributes to the winging and is most notable in protraction.

Axillary (circumflex) nerve

The axillary nerve arises from the posterior cord (fifth and sixth cervical ventral rami) (see Figs 48.8, 49.33, 49.35) and innervates teres minor and deltoid, and the skin overlying deltoid on the lateral aspect of the shoulder. Initially it is lateral to the radial nerve, posterior to the axillary artery and anterior to subscapularis. At the lower border of subscapularis, it curves back inferior to the humeroscapular articular capsule and, together with the posterior circumflex humeral vessels, traverses a quadrangular space bounded above by subscapularis (anteriorly) and teres minor (posteriorly), below by teres major, medially by the long head of triceps, and laterally by the surgical neck of the humerus. It divides in the space into anterior and posterior branches. The anterior branch curves round the neck of the humerus with the posterior circumflex humeral vessels, deep to deltoid, to reach the anterior part of the muscle. At the level of the anterior border of the acromion, the nerve often consists of two or more thin filaments that supply the anterior deltoid; it gives off a few small cutaneous branches that pierce deltoid and ramify in the skin over its lower part. The posterior branch courses medially and posteriorly along the attachment of the lateral head of triceps, inferior to the glenoid rim. It usually lies medial to the anterior branch in the quadrangular space. It gives off the nerve to teres minor and the upper lateral cutaneous nerve of the arm at the lateral edge of the attachment of the long head of triceps. The nerve to teres minor enters the muscle on its inferior surface. The posterior branch frequently supplies the posterior aspect of deltoid, usually via a separate branch from the main stem, but occasionally from the superior lateral cutaneous nerve of the arm. However, the posterior part of deltoid has a more consistent supply from the anterior branch of the axillary nerve, which should be remembered when performing a posterior deltoid-splitting approach to the shoulder. The upper lateral cutaneous nerve of the arm pierces the deep fascia at the medial border of the posterior aspect of deltoid, and supplies the skin over the lower part of deltoid and the upper part of the long head of triceps. The posterior branch is intimately related to the inferior aspects of the glenoid and shoulder joint capsule. There is often an enlargement or pseudoganglion on the branch to teres minor. The axillary trunk supplies a branch to the shoulder joint below subscapularis.

Lesions of the axillary nerve

The axillary nerve innervates deltoid. Although a good range of elevation is usually maintained by an intact abductor mechanism, strength and stamina are greatly reduced. Early diagnosis of rupture of the axillary nerve can prove difficult; the nerve is deeply seated, which means that Tinel’s sign is rarely detectable. Active movement is restricted by pain and by the restraint of any sling. The loss of sensation varies and there may not be complete anaesthesia. Patients with an intact suprascapular nerve and an intact rotator cuff are able to initiate abduction and many can fully elevate the arm, or nearly so. The power of forward flexion and of abduction is reduced to, at most, 30–40% of normal, whereas extension, with the shoulder at 90° of abduction, is 10% or less. One useful test is to palpate the posterior third of deltoid with the fingers and ask the patient to move the elbow gently backwards. It should be possible to detect activity in the muscle when the arm is supported in a sling or by the examiner’s arm.

Musculocutaneous nerve

The musculocutaneous nerve (fifth, sixth and seventh cervical ventral rami) is one of the two terminal branches of the lateral cord, the other being the lateral root of the median nerve (see Fig. 48.13). This division usually occurs at the level of the third part of axillary artery, where the lateral cord lies lateral to the vessel, but it may occur more proximally, where the cord is anterior to the second part of the artery. The nerve may also arise as two or three branches from the cord, or even from the median nerve. It pierces coracobrachialis a variable distance below the tip of the coracoid process and then descends laterally between biceps brachii and brachialis to the lateral side of the arm. The first branch, to coracobrachialis, may pass into the muscle no more than 2 cm distal to the tip of the coracoid; fibres from C7 may branch directly from the lateral cord. Branches to biceps brachii and brachialis leave after the musculocutaneous nerve has pierced coracobrachialis. There are usually two branches to brachialis, and the lower branch also supplies the anterior aspect of the elbow joint. The nerve to biceps brachii is consistently accompanied by a vascular pedicle. The nerve now inclines lateral and deep, into the plane between brachialis posteriorly and biceps anteriorly, where it supplies a small branch to the humerus that enters the shaft with the nutrient artery. Below the branches to brachialis, the musculocutaneous nerve continues as the lateral cutaneous nerve of the forearm, deep to biceps, before emerging lateral to it about 11 cm above the lateral epicondyle, and then running down the lateral aspect of the forearm.

The musculocutaneous nerve has frequent variations. It may run behind coracobrachialis or adhere for some distance to the median nerve and pass behind biceps brachii. Some fibres of the median nerve may run in the musculocutaneous nerve, leaving it to join their proper trunk; less frequently, the reverse occurs, and the median nerve sends a branch to the musculocutaneous nerve. Occasionally, the musculocutaneous nerve also supplies pronator teres and may innervate the skin over the first metacarpal and the lateral part of the thenar eminence.

Lateral cutaneous nerve of the forearm

The lateral cutaneous nerve of the forearm is the cutaneous division of the musculocutaneous nerve. It lies between biceps brachii and brachialis, inclining from the medial to the lateral side, then passes through the cubital fossa lateral to the tendon of biceps brachii and deep to the cephalic vein and descends along the radial border of the forearm to the wrist (see Figs 49.33–49.34, 50.31–50.32). It supplies the skin of the anterolateral surface of the forearm (see Fig. 49.1) and connects with the posterior cutaneous nerve of the forearm and the terminal branch of the radial nerve by branches that pass around the radial border of the forearm. Its trunk gives rise to a slender recurrent branch that extends along the cephalic vein as far as the middle third of the upper arm, distributing filaments to the skin over the distal third of the anterolateral surface of the upper arm close to the vein. At the wrist joint, the lateral cutaneous nerve of the forearm is anterior to the radial artery. It gives off filaments that pierce the deep fascia and accompany the artery to the dorsum of the carpus. The nerve then passes to the base of the thenar eminence, where it ends in cutaneous rami, some of which connect with the terminal branch of the radial nerve and the palmar cutaneous branch of the median nerve.

Medial cutaneous nerve of the arm

The medial cutaneous nerve of the arm (eighth cervical ventral ramus and first thoracic ventral ramus) is the smallest and most medial branch of the brachial plexus, arising from the medial cord (see Fig. 49.35). It crosses the axilla, either anterior or posterior to the axillary vein, then passes medial to the axillary vein, communicates with the intercostobrachial nerve, and descends medial to the brachial artery and basilic vein. It pierces the deep fascia at the midpoint of the upper arm to supply the skin over the medial aspect of the distal third of the upper arm (see Fig. 49.34). It connects with the posterior branch of the medial cutaneous nerve of the forearm. Sometimes, the medial cutaneous nerve of the arm and the intercostobrachial nerve are connected in a plexiform manner in the axilla. The intercostobrachial nerve may be large and reinforced by part of the lateral cutaneous branch of the third intercostal nerve. In these cases, it replaces the medial cutaneous nerve of the arm and receives a connection representing the latter from the brachial plexus (occasionally, this connection is absent).

Medial cutaneous nerve of the forearm

The medial cutaneous nerve of the forearm comes from the medial cord (first thoracic ventral ramus) (see Fig. 49.34). It lies initially between the axillary artery and vein, and gives off a ramus that pierces the deep fascia to supply the skin over the biceps, almost to the elbow. The nerve descends medial to the brachial artery, pierces the deep fascia with the basilic vein midway in the arm, and divides into anterior and posterior branches before it enters the forearm (see Figs 49.34, 50.31–50.32). The larger anterior branch usually passes anterior to, or occasionally behind, the median cubital vein, and descends anteromedially in the forearm to supply the skin as far as the wrist. It curves round to the dorsum of the forearm, descending on its medial border to the wrist, supplying the skin (see Fig. 50.1). It connects with the medial cutaneous nerve of the arm, the posterior cutaneous nerve of the forearm and the dorsal branch of the ulnar nerve.

Ulnar nerve

The ulnar nerve (seventh and eighth cervical ventral rami and first thoracic ventral ramus) is the continuation of the medial cord (see Fig. 48.12). It usually has no branches in the arm, but occasionally may give a branch to the medial head of triceps. The nerve runs distally through the axilla, medial to the axillary artery and between it and the vein, and continues distally medial to the brachial artery as far as the mid-arm. Here it inclines posteromedially to perforate the medial intermuscular septum about 10 cm proximal to the medial epicondyle and passes through a fibrous canal, the arcade of Struthers, which is between 5 and 6 cm long. The walls of the canal include the medial intermuscular septum and the fascial sheath which invests the medial head of triceps brachii. The nerve passes behind the medial epicondyle in a groove where it is easily palpable (see Fig. 50.29) and runs through the cubital tunnel, between the capsule of the humero-ulnar joint and the overlying arcuate ligament of Osborne (joining the two heads of flexor carpi ulnaris). It gives off articular branches to the elbow as it lies between the medial epicondyle and the olecranon. The ulnar nerve enters the forearm between the two heads of flexor carpi ulnaris, which it supplies by two neurovascular pedicles, the first arising just distal to the cubital tunnel and the second about one-quarter of the way down the forearm: it is superficial to the posterior and oblique parts of the ulnar collateral ligament and deep to the tough deep fascia of flexor carpi ulnaris (Osborne’s fascia). The nerve descends on the medial side of the forearm on flexor digitorum profundus, to which it sends several branches (see Fig. 50.32). Proximally, it runs with the ulnar vessels in a well-defined sheath deep to the anterior margin of flexor carpi ulnaris; distally, it lies lateral to the muscle and is covered only by skin and fasciae. In the upper third of the forearm, the ulnar nerve is distant from the ulnar artery but it comes to lie close to the medial side of the artery more distally. Some 5–6 cm proximal to the ulnar styloid it gives off the dorsal cutaneous branch which winds around the ulna, at first deep to flexor carpi ulnaris, and then subcutaneously, and innervates the skin of the dorsum of the hand and little finger, and the medial side of the ring finger. At the wrist the ulnar nerve passes under the superficial part of the flexor retinaculum (in Guyon’s canal) with the ulnar artery and divides into superficial and deep branches (see Fig. 51.10). The superficial division innervates the skin of the medial two digits and palmaris brevis. The deep branch passes, with the deep branch of the ulnar artery, between abductor and flexor digiti minimi, pierces opponens digiti minimi and then runs across the deep palmar space with the deep palmar arch. It innervates all the muscles of the hand, except for the first and second (index and middle) lumbricals, abductor pollicis brevis, opponens pollicis and part of flexor pollicis brevis.

The ulnar nerve is accompanied by the superior collateral ulnar vessels in the lower third of the arm as far as the entrance to the cubital tunnel, and then by the posteroinferior ulnar collateral vessels. The anastomosis between these vessels permits the use of most of the ulnar nerve as a free vascularized graft, in cases where the parent roots, the seventh and eighth cervical ventral rami and the first thoracic ventral ramus, are irreparable.. The ulnar nerve is palpable in the lower arm and behind the medial epicondyle, where it is subcutaneous. There is an important relation here: a posterior branch of the medial cutaneous nerve of the forearm sweeps across the cubital tunnel and gets in the way of medial surgical exposures. Inadvertent injury may cause severe pain. The ulnar nerve is palpable at the wrist where it emerges from under flexor carpi ulnaris. The dorsal cutaneous branch can be palpated in those of slender physique where it crosses the subcutaneous ulna.

Muscular branches

There are two main muscular branches of the ulnar nerve in the forearm. They arise near the elbow and supply flexor carpi ulnaris and the medial half of flexor digitorum profundus.

Dorsal branch

The dorsal branch arises approximately 5 cm proximal to the wrist (see Fig. 51.9). It passes distally and dorsally, deep to flexor carpi ulnaris, perforates the deep fascia, descends along the medial side of the dorsum of the wrist and hand, and then divides into two, or often three, dorsal digital nerves. The first supplies the medial side of the little finger; the second, the adjacent sides of the little and ring fingers; while the third, when present, supplies adjoining sides of the ring and middle fingers. The latter may be replaced, wholly or partially, by a branch of the radial nerve, which communicates with it on the dorsum of the hand. In the little finger, the dorsal digital nerves extend only to the base of the distal phalanx; in the ring finger, they extend only to the base of the middle phalanx. The most distal parts of the little finger and of the ulnar side of the ring finger are supplied by dorsal branches of the proper palmar digital branches of the ulnar nerve. The most distal part of the lateral side of the ring finger is supplied by dorsal branches of the proper palmar digital branch of the median nerve.

Superficial terminal branch

The superficial terminal branch supplies palmaris brevis and the medial palmar skin. It divides into two palmar digital nerves. One supplies the medial side of the little finger; the other (a common palmar digital nerve) sends a branch to the median nerve and divides into two proper digital nerves to supply the adjoining sides of little and ring fingers. The proper digital branches within the digit are distributed like those derived from the median nerve.

Deep terminal branch

The deep terminal branch accompanies the deep branch of the ulnar artery as it passes between abductor digiti minimi and flexor digiti minimi, and then perforates opponens digiti minimi to follow the deep palmar arch dorsal to the flexor tendons. At its origin, it supplies the three short muscles of the little finger. As it crosses the hand, it supplies the interossei and the third and fourth lumbricals. It ends by supplying adductor pollicis, the first dorsal interosseous and, usually, flexor pollicis brevis.

The medial part of flexor digitorum profundus is supplied by the ulnar nerve, as are the third and fourth lumbricals, which are connected with the tendons of this part of the muscle. Similarly, the lateral part of flexor digitorum profundus and the first and second lumbricals are supplied by the median nerve. The third lumbrical is often supplied by both nerves. The deep terminal branch gives branches to some intercarpal, carpometacarpal and intermetacarpal joints; precise details are uncertain. Vasomotor branches, arising in the forearm and hand, supply the ulnar and palmar arteries.

Palmar cutaneous branch

The palmar cutaneous branch of the ulnar nerve arises in mid-forearm, descends on the ulnar artery, which it supplies, and then perforates the deep fascia. It communicates with the palmar branch of the median nerve and ends in the palmar skin. It sometimes supplies palmaris brevis.

Lesions of the ulnar nerve

The ulnar nerve is a mixed nerve and so patients may present with sensory or motor symptoms or a combination of the two, sometimes with additional physical signs of autonomic disturbance. There may be tenderness and a positive Tinel’s sign over the nerve at the point of compression. Numbness and paraesthesiae occur early, followed, in more severe cases, by weakness of power grip and, ultimately, atrophy of the lumbricals and interossei with clawing of ring and little fingers.

The ulnar nerve may be compressed by the arcade of Struthers at the level of the medial intermuscular septum; at the level of the flexor/pronator aponeurosis as it enters the forearm between the heads of flexor carpi ulnaris; or deep to the deep fascia of flexor carpi ulnaris which exhibits tough condensations extending up to 9 cm from the medial epicondyle (Siemionow et al 2007). The nerve is most often compressed at the level of the cubital tunnel by the Osborne’s arcuate ligament; this is the most common nerve compression syndrome after that of the median nerve in the carpal tunnel.

The cross-sectional area of the cubital tunnel has been shown to narrow by almost 55% in full flexion. Ultrasound studies have suggested that the ratio of the cross-sectional area of radial nerve : cubital tunnel is most strongly linked to reduced conduction velocity (Yoon et al 2007). Combining elbow flexion with direct pressure over the cubital tunnel for 60 seconds will elicit symptoms in most affected patients (Novak et al 1994). Other contributory factors are previous trauma, especially supracondylar and medial epicondyle fractures in childhood, valgus instability of the elbow in athletes involved in throwing sports, and degenerative disease.

The most reliable treatment for patients who fail to respond to non-surgical remedies is a simple release of the cubital tunnel. The release should be complete and include release of Osborne’s ligament and the deep fascia of flexor carpi ulnaris; care should be taken to avoid damage to branches of the medial cutaneous nerve of the forearm that usually cross the line of incision approximately 2  cm above the medial epicondyle and a mean 3.1 cm distal to the medial epicondyle in all patients (Lowe et al 2004). Anconeus epitrochlearis should be excised if present because it is a potential cause for recurrent symptoms. The ulnar nerve should not be circumferentially denuded of its retinaculum because this contains its intrinsic blood supply. Transposition of the nerve should be reserved for cases of persistent subluxation or of failure of a simple release to achieve symptomatic relief. This is relatively unusual and is said to occur in only 7% of cases.

The ulnar nerve can be compressed as it passes through Guyon’s canal at the wrist. Causes of compression at this site include a ganglion from the piso-triquetral joint, prolonged compression from a cyclist’s handlebars, hook of hamate fracture, and proximity of aberrant or accessory muscles. The symptoms depend on the precise level at which the ulnar nerve and its branches are compressed. Altered sensation is noted in the palmar aspect of the little finger and ulnar half of the ring finger; sensation on the ulnar aspect of the dorsum of the hand is normal due to preservation of the dorsal cutaneous branch. If the motor branch fibres are affected, there is weakness and wasting of the intrinsic muscles of the hand supplied by the ulnar nerve, with clawing posture in severe compression. Weakness of adductor pollicis and first dorsal interosseous substantially degrades pinch strength; if a slip of paper is held in the key pinch position between the pulp of the thumb and the radial side of the index proximal interphalangeal joint, the tip of the thumb involuntarily flexes as flexor pollicis longus contracts to compensate for the absent adductor pollicis and first dorsal interosseous (Froment’s sign). Surgical treatment involves decompression of the nerve by division of the roof of Guyon’s canal and removal of any causative lesion, such as a ganglion. Ulnar tunnel syndrome can be difficult to distinguish from more proximal causes of ulnar nerve compression, of which the most common is entrapment of the nerve in the cubital canal at the elbow. In this condition, sensory changes would include the dorso-ulnar aspect of the hand and motor changes would involve flexor carpi ulnaris and flexor digitorum profundus to the little and ring fingers. Clawing is less apparent with a more proximal failure of the ulnar nerve (the ‘ulnar paradox’) because flexor digitorum profundus also fails so there is less flexion force to expose the absent extensor moment of the paralysed intrinsics. In the absence of obvious clinical indicators, an unpleasant tingling sensation (Tinel’s sign) over the site of compression, electrophysiological studies and MRI scans may aid diagnosis.

Ulnar nerve division at the wrist paralyses all the intrinsic muscles of the hand (apart from the radial two lumbricals, abductor pollicis brevis, and part of flexor pollicis brevis and opponens pollicis). The intrinsic muscle action of flexing the metacarpophalangeal joint and extending the interphalangeal joints is lost. The unopposed action of the long extensors and flexors of the fingers cause clawing, with extension of the metacarpophalangeal joints and flexion of the interphalangeal joints. The clawing is less intense in the index and middle fingers because their lumbricals are supplied by the median nerve. There is sensory loss over the little finger and the ulnar half of the ring finger. The skin over the ulnar aspect of the dorsum of the hand is spared because the dorsal branch of the ulnar nerve is given off approximately 5 cm proximal to the wrist joint. A combined median and ulnar nerve palsy at the wrist results in a full claw hand with thenar and hypothenar flattening and thumb adduction and flexion (a simian hand).

Median nerve

The median nerve is formed by the union of the lateral root from the lateral cord (sixth and seventh cervical ventral rami), and the medial root from the medial cord (eighth cervical and first thoracic ventral rami), which meet anterior or lateral to the third part of the axillary artery (see Figs 48.7, 48.10, 49.29, 49.35, 49.44). Some fibres from C7 often leave the lateral root in the lower part of the axilla, pass distomedially posterior to the medial root, and usually anterior to the axillary artery, to join the ulnar nerve. Clinically, they are believed to be mainly motor and to supply flexor carpi ulnaris. If the lateral root is small, the musculocutaneous nerve (fifth, sixth and seventh cervical ventral rami) connects with the median nerve in the arm.

The first branch of the median nerve, to pronator teres, arises 2–3 cm above the medial epicondyle. A second branch, or leash of branches, arises at the level of the tip of the medial epicondyle and innervates palmaris longus, flexor carpi radialis and flexor digitorum superficialis. In the cubital fossa, the median nerve lies medial to the brachial artery, deep to the bicipital aponeurosis and anterior to brachialis. It usually enters the forearm between the heads of pronator teres, although, occasionally, it may pass posterior to both heads of the muscle, or it may pass through its humeral head (see Fig. 50.31; see also Figs 50.21–50.22). The nerve crosses to the lateral side of the ulnar artery, from which it is separated by the deep head of pronator teres, passes behind a tendinous bridge between the humero-ulnar and radial heads of flexor digitorum superficialis, and descends through the forearm posterior and adherent to flexor digitorum superficialis and anterior to flexor digitorum profundus. Just proximal to the tendinous arcade of flexor digitorum superficialis, the median nerve gives off the anterior interosseous nerve. Accompanied by the anterior interosseous vessels, this large branch dives deeply to pass down along the interosseous membrane and supplies flexor pollicis longus, the radial half of flexor digitorum profundus and pronator quadratus. There is no cutaneous distribution.

The main nerve continues in the plane between the superficial and deep digital flexors, supplying two or three branches to the former. About 5 cm proximal to the flexor retinaculum, the median nerve emerges from behind the lateral edge of flexor digitorum superficialis and becomes superficial just proximal to the wrist. Just proximal to the flexor retinaculum the median nerve is lateral and superficial to the tendons of flexor digitorum superficialis and lies between the tendons of flexor carpi radialis and palmaris longus (see Fig. 50.31). It passes under the retinaculum in the ‘carpal tunnel’, where it may be compressed in carpal tunnel syndrome, and enters the palm. Distal to the retinaculum, the nerve enlarges and flattens, and usually divides into five or six branches; the mode and level of division are variable. The recurrent (motor) nerve to the thenar muscles arises within, or just distal to, the carpal tunnel, usually on the lateral side of the main nerve. The palmar digital nerves are formed within the palm of the hand and pass distally, deep to the superficial palmar arch and its digital vessels, at first anterior to the tendons of the long flexors, to supply the palmar skin of the thumb, index and middle fingers and the lateral side of the ring finger. The palmar cutaneous branch arises 3.5–6 cm proximal to the most proximal wrist crease, and passes lateral to the main nerve and superficial to the flexor retinaculum to innervate the skin of the proximal palm.

Within the carpal tunnel and hand, the median nerve has been shown to glide by up to 3 mm, depending on the position of the elbow and the attitude of the forearm in pronation or supination (Echigo et al 2008). The greatest longitudinal excursion of the median nerve (15.5 mm) is seen just proximal to the carpal tunnel; similar excursion of the ulnar nerve has been recorded as 14.8 mm in cadavers (Wilgis and Murphy 1986).

The median nerve is palpable along its course in the arm, where it is covered by deep fascia and skin, after emerging from deep to coracobrachialis; on the flexor aspect of the elbow, deep to the bicipital aponeurosis; and at the wrist where it emerges from behind the superficial flexor tendons, just lateral to palmaris longus. It is closely related to the brachial artery in the anterior aspect of the elbow, where it courses anterior to brachialis and medial to the artery.

The median nerve has muscular, anterior interosseous, palmar cutaneous and palmar digital branches.

Muscular branches

Muscular branches are given off near the elbow to all the superficial flexor muscles except flexor carpi ulnaris. The branch to the part of flexor digitorum superficialis that serves the index finger is given off near the mid-forearm and may be derived from the anterior interosseous nerve.

Anterior interosseous nerve

The anterior interosseous nerve arises from the posterior aspect of the median nerve between the two heads of pronator teres, just distal to the branches to the superficial forearm flexors and proximal tendinous arch of flexor digitorum superficialis (see Figs 50.10, 50.22). It descends with the anterior interosseous artery anterior to the interosseous membrane, between and deep to flexor pollicis longus and flexor digitorum profundus (see Fig. 50.32), supplying flexor pollicis longus and the lateral part of flexor digitorum profundus (to the index and middle fingers). Terminally, the anterior interosseous nerve lies posterior to pronator quadratus, which it supplies via its deep surface. It also supplies articular branches to the distal radio-ulnar, radiocarpal and carpal joints.

Palmar cutaneous branch

The palmar cutaneous branch emerges from the radial side of the median nerve 3.5 cm to 6 cm proximal to the flexor retinaculum. It runs in a small tunnel alongside the ulnar edge of the sheath of flexor carpi radialis, radial and deep to palmaris longus, before piercing the deep fascia to enter the palm either through or superficial to the flexor retinaculum (see Fig. 51.27B). It usually ends in medial and lateral terminal branches that supply a patch of skin over and just beyond the anterior surface of the palm overlying the scaphoid tubercle and anterior aspect of the carpometacarpal joint of the thumb (Hobbs et al 1990, da Silva et al 1996). The lateral branches connect with the lateral cutaneous nerve of the forearm and the medial branches connect with the palmar cutaneous branch of the ulnar nerve (see Fig. 51.27B).

Muscular branch (recurrent motor branch)

The recurrent motor branch is short and thick, and arises from the lateral side of the nerve; it may be the first palmar branch or a terminal branch that arises level with the digital branches. It runs laterally, just distal to the flexor retinaculum and with a slight recurrent curve beneath the part of the palmar aponeurosis covering the thenar muscles (see Fig. 51.27B). It turns round the distal border of the retinaculum to lie superficial to flexor pollicis brevis, which it usually supplies, and either continues superficial to the muscle or traverses it. It gives a branch to abductor pollicis brevis that enters the medial edge of the muscle, and then passes deep to it to supply opponens pollicis, entering its medial edge. Its terminal part occasionally gives a branch to the first dorsal interosseous, and may be its sole or partial supply. The muscular branch may arise in the carpal tunnel and pierce the flexor retinaculum. Anomalies of the median nerve occur in approximately 10% of patients undergoing a carpal tunnel release. These branches usually arise from the ulnar side of the nerve and may be motor or sensory.

Palmar digital branches

The median nerve supplies palmar cutaneous digital branches to the radial three and a half digits (thumb, index, middle and the lateral side of the ring); sometimes, the radial side of the ring finger is supplied by the ulnar nerve. Occasionally, there is a communicating branch between the common digital nerve to the middle and ring fingers (derived from the median nerve) and the common digital nerve to the ring and little fingers (derived from the ulnar nerve); this may explain variations in sensory patterns that do not conform to the classic pattern.

Various patterns of termination of the palmar digital nerves have been described: the branches are commonly arranged as follows. Distal to the flexor retinaculum, the median nerve splits into a smaller lateral portion and a larger medial portion. The lateral portion gives rise to a recurrent motor branch and divides into three proper digital nerves that supply the thumb and radial index finger. The branch that supplies the radial side of the index finger also supplies the first lumbrical. The medial portion divides into two common palmar digital nerves which each further divide into two proper digital nerves that supply the adjacent sides of the index, middle and ring fingers. The lateral common digital nerve supplies the second lumbrical, and the medial receives a communicating twig from the common palmar digital branch of the ulnar nerve and may supply the third lumbrical. In the distal part of the palm, the digital arteries pass deeply between the divisions of the digital nerves; the nerves lie anterior to the arteries on the sides of the digits.

The digital nerves pass distally, deep to the superficial palmar arch and its digital vessels, at first anterior to the tendons of the long flexors. Together with the lumbricals and palmar digital arteries, they pass dorsal to the superficial transverse metacarpal ligament and ventral to the deep transverse metacarpal ligament. In the digits, the nerves run distally beside the long flexor tendons (outside their fibrous sheaths), level with the anterior phalangeal surfaces and anterior to the digital arteries, between Grayson’s and Cleland’s ligaments. Each nerve gives off several branches to the skin on the volar and lateral aspects of the digit and sends branches to the metacarpophalangeal and interphalangeal joints.

The digital nerves supply the fibrous sheaths of the long flexor tendons, blood vessels (vasomotor) and sweat glands (sudomotor). Distal to the base of the distal phalanx, each digital nerve gives off a branch that passes dorsally to the nail bed (see Fig. 51.9). The main nerve frequently trifurcates to supply the pulp and skin of the terminal part of the digit. Distal to the base of the proximal phalanx, each proper digital nerve also gives off a dorsal branch to supply the skin over the dorsum of the middle and distal phalanges. The proper palmar digital nerves to the thumb and the lateral side of the index finger emerge with the tendons of the long flexors from under the lateral edge of the palmar aponeurosis. They are arranged in the digits as described above, except that, in the thumb, small distal branches supply the skin on the dorsum of the distal phalanx only.

Other branches

In addition to the branches of the median nerve described above, variable vasomotor branches supply the radial and ulnar arteries and their branches. Some of the intercarpal, carpometacarpal and intermetacarpal joints are said to be supplied by the median nerve or its anterior interosseous branch; the precise details are uncertain.

Martin–Gruber nerve connection

A motor communicating branch between the median and ulnar nerves in the forearm occurs in approximately one-quarter of patients. The most common variant has a branch passing from the anterior interosseous to the ulnar nerve. A number of patterns have been described where branches pass between flexors digitorum superficialis and profundus, deep to the ulnar artery, to join the ulnar nerve; such branches may explain the variations in innervation of the intrinsic muscles.

Lesions of the median nerve

The median nerve may be compressed at four sites in the elbow and forearm. The most proximal is the ligament of Struthers, where, if the median nerve is accompanied by the brachial artery, vascular symptoms and signs may also be present. More distally, it may become entrapped by a thickened bicipital aponeurosis. The other sites of compression are between the superficial and deep heads of pronator teres, and the proximal fibrous arch of flexor digitorum superficialis.

Median nerve division at the wrist leads to paralysis of the lumbricals to the index and middle fingers and of the thenar muscles (apart from flexor pollicis brevis and adductor pollicis), as well as loss of sensation to the thumb, index, middle and radial half of the ring fingers. The thenar muscles waste, and the adductor pollicis, which is no longer antagonized by flexor pollicis brevis and opponens pollicis, produces an adducted posture of the thumb. Division of the median nerve distal to the origin of its palmar cutaneous branch, which arises somewhere between 3.5 and 6 cm proximal to the proximal edge of the flexor retinaculum and the distal transverse wrist crease, will leave the branch intact to supply the skin over the thenar eminence and radial side of the proximal part of the hand. Careful clinical examination of the sensibility of the skin in this region should help to clarify the level of the lesion. High division of the nerve will, as with compressive lesions at this level, result in weakness of pronation of the forearm, radial flexion of the wrist and the lateral two fingers.

Patients essentially present with one of two syndromes. The anterior interosseous nerve syndrome presents as a failure of pinch grip due to weakness of flexor pollicis longus and the radial portion of flexor or digitorum profundus. This reduces the flexion power of the interphalangeal joint of the thumb and the distal interphalangeal joint of the index finger. The pronator syndrome presents with symptoms and signs that mimic carpal tunnel syndrome. Patients present with pain and altered sensation in the radial three and a half fingers of the hand that are aggravated by activity. However, a Tinel’s sign will be positive over the proximal forearm, and sensation over the thenar eminence may be diminished, because the palmar cutaneous branch of the nerve arises above the carpal tunnel. The clinical presentation may vary in the presence of a Martin–Gruber anastomosis (Rodriguez-Niedenführ et al 2002).

Most patients will respond to non-operative treatment but those who fail to do so usually respond well to surgical decompression. Exploration and decompression should address all the potential areas of compression.

Carpal tunnel syndrome

Carpal tunnel syndrome is the most common entrapment mononeuropathy. It is caused by compression of the median nerve as it passes through the fibro-osseous tunnel beneath the flexor retinaculum (see Fig. 51.38).

Carpal tunnel syndrome is usually idiopathic, however, certain diagnoses may predispose to the condition. The carpal tunnel may be narrowed by arthritic changes in the wrist joint, by thickening of the synovium (especially in rheumatoid disease) by soft tissue thickening, as may occur in myxoedema and acromegaly; it is associated with diabetes, oedema, obesity, pregnancy and vibration. The association with repetitive use is controversial and has probably been overestimated. Normally, the median nerve slides smoothly in and out of the carpal tunnel during flexion and extension of the wrist, but when the nerve is compressed this sliding is restricted by traction that aggravates the conduction block. Typically, the syndrome produces painful paraesthesia and numbness in the thumb, index, middle and medial side of the ring fingers, which is worse at night and when performing manoeuvres such as holding a book or telephone. The palmar branch of the median nerve is spared because it does not pass through the carpal tunnel. With time, the compression leads to wasting and weakness of abductor pollicis brevis and loss of sweating in the cutaneous territory of the median nerve, sparing the patch overlying the scaphoid tubercle and palmar side of the carpometacarpal joint which is supplied by the palmar cutaneous nerve. Treatment depends on the cause. If present just at night, due to involuntary flexion of the wrist (which increases pressure in the carpal canal) then a splint may suffice. If the syndrome is of recent onset, especially in association with pregnancy or synovial thickening, then a steroid injection can be curative. For more persistent symptoms, and especially if there is evidence of axonal failure (numbness, loss of sweating, wasting of abductor pollicis brevis) then surgery is recommended. This involves dividing the flexor retinaculum. The most common hazards of decompression are inadequate decompression because of failure to divide the most distal or most proximal part of the flexor retinaculum, damage to the motor branch causing weakness, or palmar cutaneous branch or one or more terminal sensory branches causing scar tenderness and a patch of numbness and damage to the superficial palmar arch causing a haematoma.

Anatomical anomalies of the median nerve in the carpal tunnel are very common (Henry et al 2015) and occur in up to 12% of hands. The most common are variations in the course of the recurrent motor branch in relation to the flexor retinaculum. These may be transligamentous (11.3%), subligamentous (13.5%) or extraligamentous (75.2%). Damage may also occur to the palmar cutaneous branch of the median nerve and to the superficial connections between the median and ulnar nerves (Martin et al 1996), (the Berrettini branch, division of which will leave the patient with numbness in the middle and ring fingers). Stancič et al (1999) noted that this connection was present in 81% of dissected hands and proposed that it should be regarded as a normal anatomical finding.

Radial nerve

The radial nerve (fifth, sixth, seventh and eighth cervical and first thoracic ventral rami) is the terminal branch of the posterior cord (see Fig. 48.9). It is the largest nerve in the upper limb and the most commonly damaged. Between its origin at the level of the base of the coracoid and its entrance into the spiral groove, where it is accompanied by the profunda brachii artery, the radial nerve is supplied by fewer arteries than elsewhere along its course. The first 8–10 cm of the nerve may not have a nutrient artery and will, therefore, be relatively avascular if the nerve is transected at its origin. The nerve lies closest to the bone where it pierces the lateral intermuscular septum to pass through a short tunnel bounded by bone and unyielding fascia. The nerve is tethered here, a common level of rupture, entrapment or compression.

The radial nerve descends behind the third part of the axillary artery and the upper part of the brachial artery, anterior to subscapularis above and the tendons of latissimus dorsi and teres major below, giving branches to the medial head of triceps at this level. With the profunda brachii artery, it inclines dorsally, passing through the lower triangular space below the lower border of teres major, between the long head of triceps and the humerus. It then spirals obliquely across the posterior shaft of the humerus, lying posterior to the uppermost fibres of the medial head of triceps, which separate the nerve from the bone in the first part of the spiral groove. The nerve(s) to the lateral head of triceps arise(s) within the spiral groove; that to the lateral head just before the radial nerve re-enters the anterior compartment. Two cutaneous nerves, the lower lateral cutaneous nerve of the arm and the posterior cutaneous nerve of the forearm, pass away from the main nerve in the final part of the spiral groove and course along the anterior face of the lateral head of triceps to perforate the deep fascia about four fingers’ breadths above the lateral epicondyle. They innervate the skin of the lower lateral arm and the posterior aspect of the forearm, respectively. The radial nerve at the elbow lies in the deep groove between brachialis medially and brachioradialis and extensor carpi radialis longus laterally (see Fig. 50.21). The nerve to brachioradialis arises about three fingers’ breadths proximal to the lateral epicondyle; the nerve to extensor carpi radialis longus about one finger’s breadth more distal; and the nerve to extensor carpi radialis brevis about one finger’s breadth above the epicondyle. These branches arise from the main radial nerve as it runs between brachialis anteriorly and brachioradialis posteriorly; the nerve may be palpable at this level. On reaching the lateral side of the humerus, the radial nerve pierces the lateral intermuscular septum to enter the anterior compartment of the arm. At the level of the tip of the lateral epicondyle, the nerve divides into the posterior interosseous and superficial radial nerves. Another branch to extensor carpi radialis brevis is usually given off here. There is some variation in the level at which branches of the radial nerve arise from the main trunk in different individuals. Branches to extensor carpi radialis brevis and supinator may arise from the main trunk of the radial nerve or from the proximal part of the posterior interosseous nerve, but almost invariably above the arcade of Frohse.

The superficial radial nerve innervates the skin over the dorsum of the radial half of the ring, middle and index fingers, and that of the thumb as far as the distal interphalangeal joint. It often provides important sensation on the skin of the thumb web space and the skin on the adjacent sides of the thumb and index finger.

The branches of the radial nerve are: muscular, cutaneous, articular, superficial radial and posterior interosseous.

Muscular branches

Muscular branches supply triceps, anconeus, brachioradialis, extensor carpi radialis longus and brachialis in medial, posterior and lateral groups. Medial muscular branches arise from the radial nerve on the medial side of the arm and supply the medial and long heads of triceps. The branch to the medial head is a long, slender filament that lies close to the ulnar nerve as far as the distal third of the arm, and is often termed the ulnar collateral nerve. A large posterior muscular branch arises from the nerve as it lies in the humeral groove and divides to supply the medial and lateral heads of triceps and anconeus. The branch to anconeus is a long nerve that descends in the medial head of triceps and partially supplies it; the nerve is accompanied by the middle collateral branch of the profunda brachii artery and passes behind the elbow joint to end in anconeus. Lateral muscular branches arise anterior to the lateral intermuscular septum and supply the lateral part of brachialis, brachioradialis and extensor carpi radialis longus.

Cutaneous branches

Cutaneous branches are the posterior and lower lateral cutaneous nerves of the arm and the posterior cutaneous nerve of the forearm.

Posterior cutaneous nerve of the arm

The small posterior cutaneous nerve of the arm arises in the axilla and passes medially to supply the skin on the dorsal surface of the arm nearly as far as the olecranon. It crosses posterior to, and communicates with, the intercostobrachial nerve.

Lower lateral cutaneous nerve of the arm

The lower lateral cutaneous nerve of the arm perforates the lateral head of triceps distal to the deltoid tuberosity, passes to the front of the elbow close to the cephalic vein, and supplies the skin of the lateral part of the lower half of the arm.

Posterior cutaneous nerve of the forearm

The posterior cutaneous nerve of the forearm arises with the lower lateral cutaneous nerve of the arm. Perforating the lateral head of triceps, it descends first lateral in the arm, then along the dorsum of the forearm to the wrist, supplying the skin in its course. It supplies the central forearm skin along its course and, near its termination, joins the dorsal branches of the lateral cutaneous nerve of the forearm.

Superficial radial nerve

The superficial radial nerve descends from the lateral epicondyle anterolaterally in the proximal two-thirds of the forearm, initially lying on supinator, lateral to the radial artery and behind brachioradialis. In the middle third of the forearm, it lies behind brachioradialis, close to the lateral side of the artery. It runs anterior to pronator teres, the radial head of flexor digitorum superficialis and flexor pollicis longus, and usually leaves the artery 7 cm proximal to the wrist and passes deep to the tendon of brachioradialis. It curves round the lateral side of the radius as it descends, pierces the deep fascia and divides into five, sometimes four, dorsal digital nerves. On the dorsum of the hand, it usually communicates with the posterior and lateral cutaneous nerves of the forearm.

Dorsal digital nerves

There are usually four or five small dorsal digital nerves (see Fig. 51.9).The first supplies the skin of the radial side of the thumb and the adjoining thenar eminence, and communicates with branches of the lateral cutaneous nerve of the forearm. The second supplies the medial side of the thumb; the third, the lateral side of the index finger; the fourth, the adjoining sides of the index and middle fingers. The fifth communicates with a ramus of the dorsal branch of the ulnar nerve and supplies the adjoining sides of the middle and ring fingers, where it is frequently replaced by the dorsal branch of the ulnar nerve. The digital nerves of the thumb reach only to the root of the nail; those in the index finger, midway along the middle phalanx; and those to the middle and the lateral part of the ring finger may reach no further than the proximal interphalangeal joints. The remaining distal dorsal areas of the skin in these digits are typically supplied by palmar digital branches of the median and ulnar nerves. However, the superficial terminal branch of the radial nerve may supply the whole dorsum of the hand.

Posterior interosseous nerve

The posterior interosseous nerve is the deep terminal branch of the radial nerve (see Figs 48.9, 50.21). It reaches the back of the forearm by passing round the lateral aspect of the radius between the two heads of supinator (see Figs 50.25–50.26). It supplies supinator both before entering the muscle and as it passes through it. As it emerges from supinator posteriorly, the nerve gives off three short branches to extensor digitorum, extensor digiti minimi and extensor carpi ulnaris, and two longer branches, a medial branch to extensor pollicis longus and extensor indicis, and a lateral branch that supplies abductor pollicis longus and extensor pollicis brevis. The nerve at first lies between the superficial and deep extensor muscles, but at the distal border of extensor pollicis brevis, it passes deep to extensor pollicis longus and, diminished to a fine thread, descends on the interosseous membrane to the dorsum of the carpus. Filaments arising from its flattened termination supply the carpal ligaments and articulations. Articular branches from the posterior interosseous nerve supply carpal, distal radio-ulnar and some intercarpal and intermetacarpal joints. Digital branches supply the metacarpophalangeal and proximal interphalangeal joints.

The distal portion of the nerve lies in a separate fascial sheath in the radial, deep, aspect of the fourth dorsal compartment of the extensor retinaculum of the wrist, where it is located deep to extensor digitorum and extensor indicis.

Branches of the superficial branch of the radial nerve reach the hand by curving around the wrist over the tendons of abductor pollicis longus and extensor pollicis brevis, and dividing into dorsal digital nerves (see Fig. 51.37). They usually communicate with the posterior and lateral cutaneous nerves of the forearm on the dorsum of the hand.

Lesions of the radial nerve

Radial nerve compression may occur at several sites in the elbow and forearm. The most proximal of these is within the radial tunnel which starts where the deep branch of the radial nerve lies over the radiohumeral joint and ends at the point where the deep branch becomes the posterior interosseous nerve at the distal border of supinator. At the level of the radial head, the nerve may be compressed by fibrous bands. More distally, it has been suggested that branches of the radial recurrent artery may compress the posterior interosseous nerve. Other sites of compression are the tendinous edge of the deep surface of extensor carpi radialis brevis and the point at which the nerve passes under the arcade of Frohse and between the two heads of supinator. Rarely, the nerve can be compressed at the level of the distal border of supinator.

Patients present with one of two syndromes: the radial tunnel syndrome, in which the presentation is that of pain along the lateral border of the elbow and upper forearm (Roles and Maudsley 1972), or the posterior interosseous nerve syndrome, which presents with motor weakness in the distribution of the nerve particularly affecting the extensors digitorum and carpi ulnaris. Primary treatment is non-operative and involves the avoidance of activities that cause pain, aided by appropriate splintage. In resistant cases, surgical decompression may be necessary. A complete release of all potential areas of compression is essential.

The elbow is a notorious site for nerve injuries, especially in children. The close proximity of all the major nerve trunks to bone makes them vulnerable. The ulnar nerve is particularly at risk in elbow dislocation, especially when the medial epicondyle is displaced into the joint. All three nerves are at risk of displacement into a dislocated joint. The posterior interosseous and radial nerves are particularly at risk from a Monteggia fracture-dislocation. Any nerve may become entrapped within a fracture, e.g. the median nerve is often accompanied by the brachial artery in cases of supracondylar fracture. Pain that persists, or worsens, after reduction of a fracture suggests impending critical ischaemia, continuing irritation of the nerve, or both. The nerves are at risk during operations or other medical interventions, particularly so when normal anatomical planes are distorted by haematoma, fibrosis or bone fragments.

Lumbar and sacral plexuses

Nerves derived from the lumbar and sacral plexuses innervate the lower limb (see Fig. 76.11). The lumbar plexus lies deep within psoas major, anterior to the transverse processes of the first three lumbar vertebrae. The sacral plexus lies in the pelvis on the anterior surface of piriformis, external to the pelvic fascia, which separates it from the inferior gluteal and internal pudendal vessels. The lumbosacral trunk (fourth and fifth lumbar ventral rami) emerges medial to psoas major on the posterior abdominal wall and lies on the ala of the sacrum before crossing the pelvic brim to join the first sacral ventral ramus. Contributions to the lumbosacral trunk may also be derived from the third lumbar nerve ([Apaydin 2016]).

Lesions of the lumbar and sacral plexuses

The deep and protected situation of the plexuses means that lesions are not common. The lumbar plexus may be involved in retroperitoneal pathology and the sacral plexus may be invaded by pelvic malignancies and both may be involved in the reticuloses, affected by plexiform neuromas, or damaged in fractures of the lumbar spine and pelvis or in other conditions that cause severe retroperitoneal and pelvic haemorrhage. Temporary lesions may occur after pregnancy and childbirth, e.g. after difficult forceps delivery of a large baby. Pain, which may be diffuse, is the most common feature. Iatrogenic injury can occur during surgical approaches to the abdomen and pelvis, particularly when operating within the retroperitoneal space and also during the lateral approach to spine.

Sciatica is pain in the lower back and hip region, radiating inferiorly along the posterior thigh to the leg. It is often caused by a herniated intervertebral disc, compressing the fifth lumbar or first sacral ventral rami. The so-called piriformis syndrome, which may result from a variant or anomalous relationship between piriformis and the sciatic nerve, may also produce hip pain that radiates inferiorly along the course of the sciatic nerve. Diagnosis of specific nerve injuries relies on the distribution and characteristics of clinical findings in combination with supportive electrophysiological studies and/or MRI and CT scans. The clinical presentation of lesions can vary as a result of anatomical variation and overlapping innervation patterns. Generally, loss of hip flexion and knee extension indicates a lumbar lesion; loss of hip abduction, knee flexion and plantarflexion and dorsiflexion are symptoms of sacral lesions (Ahmadian et al 2015).

Lumbar plexus

The lumbar plexus is formed by the first three and most of the fourth lumbar ventral rami, usually together with a contribution from the twelfth thoracic ventral ramus (see Fig. 61.16). The lumbar ventral rami pass laterally into the posterior part of psoas major, anterior to the transverse processes of the lumbar vertebrae (Moro et al 2003, Benglis et al 2009). Although there are many variations, the most common arrangement of the plexus is described here (Tubbs et al 2018).

The first lumbar ventral ramus is often joined by a branch from the twelfth thoracic ventral ramus, and these roots contribute to the formation of the iliohypogastric and ilioinguinal nerves, which run laterally on the posterior abdominal wall. A branch from the first lumbar ventral ramus unites with a branch from the second lumbar ventral ramus to form the genitofemoral nerve. The second, third and most of the fourth lumbar ventral rami divide into ventral and dorsal divisions; the ventral divisions unite to form the obturator nerve, while most of the nerve fibres in the dorsal divisions form the femoral nerve. The remaining fibres from the fourth lumbar ventral ramus join the fifth lumbar ventral ramus to form the lumbosacral trunk, which descends to join the sacral plexus. Branches from the dorsal divisions of the second and third lumbar ventral rami unite to form the lateral femoral cutaneous nerve. The accessory obturator nerve, when present, usually arises from the third and fourth ventral rami. The lumbar plexus is supplied by branches from the lumbar vessels that supply psoas major.

The division of constituent ventral rami into ventral and dorsal branches is not as clear in the lumbar and sacral plexuses as it is in the brachial plexus. Lateral cutaneous branches of the twelfth thoracic and first lumbar ventral rami are drawn into the gluteal skin, but otherwise these nerves are similar to intercostal nerves. The second lumbar ventral ramus is more complex. It contributes substantially to the femoral and obturator nerves, and also has an anterior terminal branch (the genital branch of the genitofemoral) and a lateral cutaneous branch that contributes to the lateral femoral cutaneous nerve and the femoral branch of the genitofemoral nerve. Anterior terminal branches of the third to fifth lumbar and first sacral ventral rami are suppressed, but the corresponding branches of the second and third sacral ventral rami supply the perineal skin.

The furcal nerve is an independent nerve with its own ventral and dorsal rootlets most commonly arising alongside the fourth lumbar spinal nerve. Its branches contribute to the femoral and obturator nerves arising from the lumbar plexus and to the lumbosacral trunk (Harshavardhana and Dabke 2014). The term ‘furcal’ refers to its forked nature, since it links the lumbar and sacral plexuses. Occasionally, the furcal nerve arises at the level of either the third or the fifth lumbar spinal nerves, in which case the sacral plexus is considered prefixed or postfixed, respectively.

Inflammatory processes, such as retrocaecal appendicitis on the right and diverticular abscess on the left, can occur in the posterior abdominal wall in the tissues immediately anterior to psoas major. These may irritate one or more branches of the lumbar plexus, causing pain or sensory disturbance in the distribution of the affected nerves, e.g. the skin of the thigh, hip or buttock.

Terminal branches of the lumbar plexus

Muscular branches

Small branches from the lumbar ventral rami supply adjacent muscles such as psoas major and quadratus lumborum (Mahan et al 2017).

Iliohypogastric nerve

The iliohypogastric nerve usually originates from the first lumbar ventral ramus but may arise wholly or in part from the twelfth thoracic ventral ramus (Klaassen et al 2011). It emerges from the upper lateral border of psoas major and crosses obliquely posterior to the inferior pole of the kidney on the anterior surface of quadratus lumborum. Above the iliac crest it enters the posterior part of transversus abdominis and then runs anteriorly between transversus abdominis and internal abdominal oblique, which it supplies. It gives off a lateral cutaneous branch that pierces internal and external abdominal oblique above the iliac crest and supplies the posterolateral gluteal skin. It continues forwards, pierces internal abdominal oblique approximately 3 cm medial and 1 cm inferior to the anterior superior iliac spine (in adults), and then penetrates the external abdominal oblique aponeurosis approximately 3 cm above and medial to the superficial inguinal ring to supply the skin of the hypogastric region. The iliohypogastric nerve frequently connects with the ilioinguinal nerve and less commonly with the subcostal nerve. Motor branches of the iliohypogastric nerve innervate transversus abdominis and internal abdominal oblique. Cutaneous branches innervate the posterolateral gluteal and skin of the hypogastric region.

Lesions of the iliohypogastic nerve

The iliohypogastric nerve is occasionally injured by a surgical incision in the right inguinal region, e.g. during an inguinal hernia repair, open appendicectomy or abdominal wall trocar placement, but there is rarely any noticeable sensory loss because the skin of the hypogastric region is innervated from several sources. Division of the iliohypogastric nerve above the anterior superior iliac spine may weaken the posterior wall of the inguinal canal and predispose to formation of a direct inguinal hernia.

Ilioinguinal nerve

The ilioinguinal nerve usually originates from the first lumbar ventral ramus but may receive a contribution from the twelfth thoracic or second lumbar ventral rami (Klaassen et al 2011). It emerges from the lateral border of psoas major, with or just inferior to the iliohypogastric nerve, passes obliquely across the anterior aspect of quadratus lumborum and the superior part of iliacus and enters transversus abdominis about 3 cm medial and 4 cm inferior to the anterior superior iliac spine (in the adult); at this site, it is readily blocked by local anaesthetic. In this region, a branch may connect with the iliohypogastric or lateral femoral cutaneous nerve. It pierces internal abdominal oblique more inferiorly, supplies it and then traverses the remainder of the inguinal canal superficial to the spermatic cord or round ligament of the uterus. It emerges with the spermatic cord from the superficial inguinal ring and divides into terminal cutaneous branches.

Numerous anatomical variations have been described (Al-dabbagh 2002, Ndiaye et al 2007). The ilioinguinal and genitofemoral nerves may interconnect within the inguinal canal, so that each innervates the skin of the genitalia to a variable extent (Rab et al 2001, Cesmebasi et al 2015). The ilioinguinal nerve may pierce the aponeurosis of external abdominal oblique proximal to the superficial inguinal ring or divide into terminal branches within the inguinal canal. It may form a common trunk with the iliohypogastric nerve as far as the midpoint of the inguinal canal or may be very small or absent, in which case the iliohypogastric nerve and genital branch of the genitofemoral nerve supply its territory. Rarely, it arises as a branch of the genitofemoral nerve. Motor branches of the ilioinguinal nerve supply transversus abdominis and internal abdominal oblique; the fibres are given off before the nerve enters the lateral aspect of the inguinal canal. Sensory branches innervate the skin of the proximal medial thigh and the skin over the root of the penis and proximal part of the scrotum in males (anterior scrotal nerve), or the skin covering the mons pubis and the adjoining labium majus in females (anterior labial nerve).

Lesions of the ilioinguinal nerve

The ilioinguinal nerve may be injured or entrapped during inguinal surgery, particularly for inguinal hernia repair, leading to sensory disturbances including pain from the external genitalia and proximal medial thigh (Ndiaye et al 2007).

Genitofemoral nerve

The genitofemoral nerve originates from the first and second lumbar ventral rami and is formed within the substance of psoas major. It descends obliquely anteriorly through the muscle to emerge on its anterior surface nearer the medial border, opposite the third or fourth lumbar vertebra (Moro et al 2003). It then descends deep to the posterior parietal peritoneum overlying psoas major, crosses obliquely posterior to the ureter, and divides into genital and femoral branches; it may divide close to its origin such that its branches emerge separately from psoas major. The genital branch crosses the distal part of the external iliac artery, enters the inguinal canal through the deep ring and accompanies the spermatic cord or round ligament of the uterus. It exits the superficial inguinal ring, usually posterior to the spermatic cord or round ligament of the uterus, and supplies cremaster and the skin of the external genitalia. The femoral branch descends lateral to the external iliac artery before crossing the deep circumflex iliac artery to pass deep to the inguinal ligament (occasionally, through it) (Rab et al 2001) and enter the femoral sheath lateral to the femoral artery. It pierces the anterior aspect of the femoral sheath and fascia lata and supplies the skin over the proximal part of the femoral triangle. It may connect with the lateral femoral cutaneous nerve and anterior femoral cutaneous branches of the femoral nerve. Motor branches of the genitofemoral nerve innervate cremaster via its genital branch. Sensory fibres travelling in the genital branch innervate the skin of the scrotum in males and of the mons pubis and labium majus in females; there is considerable variability and overlap with the cutaneous distribution of the ilio-inguinal nerve (Cesmebasi et al 2015).

Lesions of the genitofemoral nerve

The genital branch of the genitofemoral nerve may be injured during inguinal hernia repair (open or laparoscopic), leading to neuralgia (Cesmebasi et al 2015).

Lateral femoral cutaneous nerve

The lateral femoral cutaneous nerve (lateral femoral cutaneous nerve of the thigh) is usually derived from the dorsal branches of the second and third lumbar ventral rami, but variable contributions from the first to the third lumbar ventral rami have been described (de Ridder et al 1999). The nerve emerges from the posterolateral border of psoas major and crosses iliacus obliquely, running towards the anterior superior iliac spine. It supplies sensory fibres to the parietal peritoneum in the iliac fossa. On the right, the nerve passes posterolateral to the caecum, from which it is separated by the iliac fascia and peritoneum; on the left, it passes posterior to the inferior part of the descending colon. Both nerves usually pass posterior to the inguinal ligament about 1–2 cm medial to the anterior superior iliac spine; occasionally they pass through or, rarely, anterior to the ligament (Tubbs et al 2016): a separate fascial canal for this nerve has been described ([Hanna 2017]). Occasionally, the nerve lies anterior or superior to the anterior superior iliac spine as it enters the thigh, where it usually passes anterior or lateral to sartorius, but may also pierce the muscle. It divides into anterior and posterior branches. The anterior branch becomes superficial approximately 10 cm distal to the anterior superior iliac spine and supplies the skin of the anterior and lateral thigh as far distally as the knee. It connects terminally with the cutaneous branches of the anterior division of the femoral nerve and the infrapatellar branch of the saphenous nerve, forming the peripatellar plexus. The posterior branch pierces the fascia lata higher than the anterior, and divides to supply the skin on the lateral surface from the greater trochanter to about mid-thigh. It may also supply skin of the gluteal region.

Lesions of the lateral femoral cutaneous nerve

The lateral femoral cutaneous nerve may become entrapped at three sites along its course: close to the vertebral column; within the abdominal cavity as the nerve travels across the pelvis; and as it leaves the pelvis. This last site is where the nerve is most commonly damaged, and entrapment is thought to occur as the nerve passes through or deep to the inguinal ligament just medial to the anterior superior iliac spine. The angulation of the nerve as it crosses the iliac crest means that it is vulnerable to compression during movement, e.g. hip extension may increase angulation and tension on the nerve.

Injury produces an area of impaired sensation, often with pain and paraesthesia on the anterolateral aspect of the thigh (meralgia paraesthetica) in the distal cutaneous distribution of the nerve. This area does not extend across the midline anteriorly, it does not extend below the knee and it does not extend behind the hamstring tendons laterally. Symptoms may be exacerbated when wearing tight belts or tight-waisted clothes or as a result of a recent weight gain or pregnancy. Exceptionally, the posterior branch of the lateral femoral cutaneous nerve, which supplies a thin strip from the greater trochanter of the femur down about two-thirds of the way to the knee, may be affected separately. This branch leaves the main trunk of the nerve, usually distal to the inguinal ligament, and it then turns laterally to pierce tensor fasciae latae, where it may become entrapped.

Accessory obturator nerve

The accessory obturator nerve is sometimes present, more often on the left (Turgut et al 2017). It arises from the ventral branches of the third and fourth lumbar ventral rami, emerges from the medial border of psoas major, lateral to the obturator nerve, descends along the medial border of psoas major, crosses the superior pubic ramus behind pectineus and divides into branches; one branch enters the deep surface of pectineus, another supplies the hip joint, and a third connects with the anterior branch of the obturator nerve. Sometimes the accessory obturator nerve is very small and only supplies pectineus. Any branch may be absent and others may occur; an additional branch sometimes supplies adductor longus.

Femoral nerve

The femoral nerve is the largest branch of the lumbar plexus and is the nerve of the anterior compartment of the thigh. It has motor branches to iliacus, pectineus, sartorius and quadriceps femoris; articular branches to the hip, knee and ankle joints; cutaneous branches that supply most of the skin covering the anterior thigh, medial leg and medial foot and branches to the femoral artery (see Fig. 61.16). It arises from the dorsal branches (posterior divisions) of the second to fourth lumbar ventral rami (see Figs 76.11A, 77.44, 77.49) and descends through psoas major, emerging on or deep to its lateral border, about 4 cm above the inguinal ligament (Moore and Stringer 2011). It next passes between psoas major and iliacus deep to the iliac fascia, lying lateral to the femoral artery and sheath. As it passes behind the inguinal ligament into the thigh, the femoral nerve is split into anterior and posterior divisions by the lateral circumflex femoral artery. The branches of the anterior division are the intermediate and medial femoral cutaneous nerves and the nerve to sartorius. The branches of the posterior division are the saphenous nerve, muscular branches to quadriceps femoris and articular branches to the hip and knee joint. The terminal branches of the femoral nerve form in the femoral triangle about 2 cm distal to the inguinal ligament.

Nerve to pectineus

The nerve to pectineus branches from the medial side of the femoral nerve near the inguinal ligament. It passes behind the femoral sheath and enters the anterior aspect of the muscle.

Medial femoral cutaneous nerve of the thigh

The medial femoral cutaneous nerve (medial cutaneous nerve of the thigh) is at first lateral to the femoral artery. It crosses anterior to the artery at the apex of the femoral triangle and divides into anterior and posterior branches. Before doing so, it sends a few fibres through the fascia lata to supply the skin of the medial side of the thigh, near the long saphenous vein; one branch emerges via the saphenous opening, while another becomes subcutaneous about mid-thigh. The anterior branch descends on sartorius, perforates the fascia lata beyond mid-thigh, and divides into a branch that supplies the skin as low as the medial side of the knee, and another that runs lateral to the former and connects with the infrapatellar branch of the saphenous nerve. The posterior branch descends along the posterior border of sartorius to the knee, pierces the fascia lata, connects with the saphenous nerve and gives off several cutaneous rami, some as far as the medial side of the leg. The nerve contributes to the subsartorial plexus (see below).

Intermediate cutaneous nerve of the thigh

The intermediate femoral cutaneous nerve (intermediate cutaneous nerve of the thigh) usually pierces the fascia lata some 8 cm below the inguinal ligament, either as two branches or as one trunk that quickly divides into two. These descend on the anterior thigh, supplying the skin as far as the knee and ending in the peripatellar plexus. The lateral branch of the intermediate cutaneous nerve communicates with the femoral branch of the genitofemoral nerve, frequently piercing sartorius and sometimes supplying it.

Nerve to sartorius

The main nerve to sartorius arises from the femoral nerve in common with the intermediate femoral cutaneous nerve.

Saphenous nerve

The saphenous nerve is the largest and longest cutaneous branch of the femoral nerve and the longest nerve in the body (see Figs 76.11, 77.48). It descends lateral to the femoral artery in the femoral triangle and enters the adductor canal, where it crosses anterior to the artery to lie medial to it. At the distal end of the canal, it leaves the artery and emerges through the aponeurotic covering with the saphenous branch of the descending genicular artery. As it leaves the adductor canal, the saphenous nerve gives off an infrapatellar branch that contributes to the peripatellar plexus and then pierces the fascia lata between the tendons of sartorius and gracilis, becoming subcutaneous to supply the skin anterior to the patella. It descends along the medial border of the tibia with the long saphenous vein and divides distally into a branch that continues along the tibia to the ankle and a branch that passes anterior to the ankle to supply the skin on the medial side of the foot, often as far as the first metatarsophalangeal joint. The saphenous nerve connects with the medial branch of the superficial fibular nerve. Near the mid-thigh, it contributes a branch to the subsartorial plexus. The nerve may become entrapped as it leaves the adductor canal.

Muscular branches

The muscular branches of the posterior division of the femoral nerve supply quadriceps femoris. A branch to rectus femoris enters its proximal posterior surface and also supplies the hip joint. A larger branch to vastus lateralis forms a neurovascular bundle with the descending branch of the lateral circumflex femoral artery in its distal part and also supplies the knee joint. A branch to vastus medialis descends through the proximal part of the adductor canal, lateral to the saphenous nerve and femoral vessels, and enters the muscle at about its midpoint, sending a long articular filament distally along the muscle to the knee. Two or three branches to vastus intermedius enter its anterior surface about mid-thigh, and a small branch from one of these descends through the muscle to supply articularis genus and the knee joint.

Vascular branches

Vascular branches of the femoral nerve supply the femoral artery and its branches.

Lesions of the femoral nerve

Partial or complete injury can occur during surgery directed to the hip, pelvis or spine; with femoral artery catheterization; from trauma; or as a result of a retroperitoneal haematoma or mass. The most striking feature of femoral neuropathy is wasting and weakness of quadriceps femoris, resulting in difficulty in walking and a tendency for the leg to collapse. Pain and paraesthesia may occur on the anterior and medial aspect of the thigh, extending down the medial aspect of the leg in the distribution of the saphenous branch of the femoral nerve.

Obturator nerve

The obturator nerve is the nerve of the medial compartment of the thigh: it arises from the ventral branches of the second to fourth lumbar ventral rami. The branch from the third is the largest while that from the second is often very small. The nerve descends within the substance of psoas major, emerging from its posteromedial border near the fifth lumbar vertebra (Kirchmair et al 2008). It passes posterior to the common iliac vessels and lateral to the internal iliac vessels, descends on the lateral wall of the pelvis attached to the obturator fascia, and lies anterosuperior to the obturator vessels before running into the obturator canal to enter the thigh. Near the foramen, it divides into anterior and posterior branches, separated initially by part of obturator externus and further distally by adductor brevis.

The obturator nerve is said to have no branches in the abdomen or pelvis, although it has been reported to send articular branches to the anterior aspect of the sacroiliac joint. Its sensory branches innervate the hip and knee joints, and a small, variable patch of skin on the proximal medial thigh, and its motor branches innervate obturator externus, adductor longus, adductor brevis, adductor magnus, gracilis and sometimes pectineus (see Fig. 61.16) (Tubbs et al 2016).

Anterior branch

The anterior branch (see Fig. 77.49) leaves the pelvis anterior to obturator externus, and descends anterior to adductor brevis, behind pectineus and adductor longus. At the lower border of adductor longus it communicates with the medial cutaneous and saphenous branches of the femoral nerve, to form a subsartorial plexus that supplies the skin on the medial side of the thigh. It descends on, and supplies, the femoral artery. Near the obturator foramen, the anterior branch supplies the hip joint. Behind pectineus it supplies adductor longus, gracilis, usually adductor brevis and often pectineus, and connects with the accessory obturator nerve (when present). Occasionally the communicating branch to the femoral medial cutaneous and saphenous branches continues as a cutaneous branch to the thigh and leg. When this occurs the nerve emerges from behind the distal border of adductor longus to descend along the posterior margin of sartorius to the knee, where it pierces the deep fascia and connects with the saphenous nerve to supply the skin halfway down the medial side of the leg.

Subsartorial nerve plexus

The medial cutaneous nerve of the thigh forms a subsartorial plexus with branches of the saphenous and obturator nerves, deep to the fascia lata, at the lower border of adductor longus. When the communicating branch of the obturator nerve is large and reaches the leg, the posterior branch of the medial cutaneous nerve is small, and ends in the plexus from which it gives rise to a few cutaneous filaments.

Posterior branch

The posterior branch pierces obturator externus anteriorly, supplies it and passes behind adductor brevis to the front of adductor magnus, dividing into branches to this and adductor brevis when the latter is not supplied by the anterior division. It usually sends an articular filament to the knee joint, which either perforates adductor magnus distally or traverses its opening with the femoral artery to enter the popliteal fossa. Within the fossa, the nerve descends on the popliteal artery to the back of the knee, pierces its oblique posterior ligament and supplies the articular capsule. It gives filaments to the popliteal artery.

Lesions of the obturator nerve

Isolated lesions of the obturator nerve are rare. However, it may be injured together with other nerves in retroperitoneal lesions that occur close to the origins of the lumbar plexus, or by an acetabular fracture, pelvic tumour, obturator hernia, prolonged labour or direct trauma. It can be damaged iatrogenically following manipulation, transection or retraction during pelvic surgery and can become entrapped within the fascia overlying adductor brevis. Compression of the nerve by herniated bowel loops at the obturator foramen can result in pain referred to the hip, medial thigh and knee, the so-called Howship–Romberg sign. A more distal nerve entrapment syndrome causing chronic medial thigh pain has been described in athletes with large adductor muscles.

Sacral plexus

The sacral plexus is formed by the lumbosacral trunk, the first to third sacral ventral rami, and part of the fourth sacral ventral ramus (the remainder of the fourth sacral ventral ramus joins the coccygeal plexus). The lumbar part of the lumbosacral trunk contains part of the fourth and all of the fifth lumbar ventral rami; it appears at the medial margin of psoas major and descends over the linea terminalis, at first medial to and then distally crossing anterior to the sacroiliac joint, to join the first sacral ventral ramus. The greater parts of the second and third sacral rami converge on the inferomedial aspect of the lumbosacral trunk in the greater sciatic foramen to form the sciatic nerve. The ventral and dorsal divisions of the nerves do not separate physically from each other but their fibres remain separate within the rami; the ventral and dorsal divisions of each contributing root join within the sciatic nerve. The fibres of the dorsal divisions will go on to form the common fibular nerve, and the fibres of the ventral division form the tibial nerve. Occasionally, the sciatic nerve divides into common fibular and tibial nerves inside the pelvis; when this occurs, the common fibular nerve usually runs through piriformis.

The sacral plexus lies against the posterior pelvic wall anterior to piriformis, posterior to the internal iliac vessels and ureter, and posterior to the sigmoid colon on the left. The superior gluteal vessels run either between the lumbosacral trunk and first sacral ventral ramus, or between the first and second sacral rami, while the inferior gluteal vessels lie between either the first and second, or the second and third, sacral ventral rami.

The sacral plexus is not commonly involved in malignant tumours of the pelvis because it lies behind the relatively dense presacral fascia, which resists all but locally very advanced malignant infiltration. When it occurs, there is intractable pain in the distribution of the branches of the plexus, which can be very difficult to treat. The plexus can also be involved in reticuloses or be affected by plexiform neuromas. The branches of the sacral plexus are shown in Table 77.1.

Sacral visceral and muscular branches

Visceral branches, the pelvic splanchnic nerves, arise from the second to fourth sacral verntral rami and innervate the pelvic viscera.

Several muscular branches arise from the fourth sacral ventral ramus to supply the superior surface of levator ani and the upper part of the external anal sphincter. The branches to levator ani enter the superior surface of the muscle. The branch to the external anal sphincter (also referred to as the perineal branch of the fourth sacral nerve) reaches the ischio-anal fossa by running either through ischiococcygeus or between ischiococcygeus and iliococcygeus: it also supplies the skin between the anus and coccyx.

Superior gluteal nerve

The superior gluteal nerve arises from the dorsal branches of the fourth and fifth lumbar and first sacral ventral rami. Accompanied by the superior gluteal vessels, the nerve leaves the pelvis via the greater sciatic foramen above piriformis, and divides into superior and inferior branches (see Fig. 77.47). The superior branch accompanies the upper branch of the deep division of the superior gluteal artery to supply gluteus medius and occasionally gluteus minimus. The inferior branch runs with the lower ramus of the deep division of the superior gluteal artery across gluteus minimus, supplies the glutei medius and minimus, and ends in tensor fasciae latae.

Inferior gluteal nerve

The inferior gluteal nerve arises from the dorsal branches of the fifth lumbar and first and second sacral ventral rami. It leaves the pelvis via the greater sciatic foramen below piriformis, and divides into branches that enter the deep surface of gluteus maximus (see Fig. 77.47).

Lesions of the superior and inferior gluteal nerves

Focal lesions of the superior and inferior gluteal nerves usually occur concurrently with those of the sciatic nerve, posterior femoral cutaneous nerve and/or pudendal nerve. However, both gluteal nerves are vulnerable to injury during total hip replacement, and less commonly due to blunt trauma or misplaced gluteal injections. Injury to the superior gluteal nerve causing paralysis of gluteus medius and minimus can result in Trendelenburg’s sign, where the pelvis drops on the unsupported side (in the coronal plane) when standing on the affected limb. Injury to the inferior gluteal nerve results in weakness of gluteus maximus causing impaired hip extension (Kretschmer and Heinen 2015).

Pudendal nerve

The pudendal nerve arises from the ventral divisions of the second, third and fourth sacral ventral rami and is formed just above the superior border of the sacrotuberous ligament and the upper fibres of ischiococcygeus ([Klink 1953], [Sato 1980]). It leaves the pelvis via the greater sciatic foramen between piriformis and ischiococcygeus (see Fig. 71.10), enters the gluteal region and passes dorsal to the sacrospinous ligament, close to its attachment to the ischial spine, where it lies medial to the internal pudendal vessels. It accompanies the internal pudendal artery through the lesser sciatic foramen into the pudendal canal on the lateral wall of the ischio-anal fossa. In the posterior part of the canal, it gives rise to the inferior anal (rectal) and perineal nerves; the dorsal nerve of the penis or clitoris continues anteriorly from this origin.

The course of the branches of the pudendal nerve parallels that of the pudendal vessels (see Figs 74.24, 75.4). Muscular branches that arise directly from the pudendal nerve supply the superficial transverse perineal muscles, bulbospongiosus, ischiocavernosus, the external urethral sphincter and the anterior parts of the external anal sphincter and levator ani. In males, the branch to bulbospongiosus pierces this muscle to supply the corpus spongiosum penis, and ends in the urethral mucosa. For the innervation of the female genitalia, see Table 75.2.

The pudendal nerve occupies a constant position over the ischial spine and it can be ‘blocked’ by infiltration with a local anaesthetic applied via a needle passed through the lateral wall of the vagina to anaesthetize the perineal and anal skin. It can also be palpated over the ischial spine through the lateral wall of the rectum.

Inferior anal nerve

The inferior anal (rectal) nerve runs either through the medial wall of the pudendal canal with the inferior anorectal vessels, or behind the sacrospinous ligament directly from the fourth sacral ventral ramus without passing through the pudendal canal (Maldonado et al 2015), or occasionally it arises directly from the sacral plexus and crosses the sacrospinous ligament or rejoins the pudendal nerve. The nerve crosses the ischio-anal fossa to supply the external anal sphincter, the lining of the distal part of the anal canal and the skin around the anus. It frequently breaks into terminal branches before reaching the lateral border of the external anal sphincter. Its cutaneous branches distributed around the anus overlap the branches of the perineal branch of the posterior femoral cutaneous nerve and of the posterior scrotal or labial nerves. In females, the inferior anal nerve can supply sensory branches to the distal part of the vagina.

Perineal nerve

The perineal nerve is the inferior and larger terminal branch of the pudendal nerve in the pudendal canal. It runs anteriorly, inferior to the internal pudendal artery and accompanies the perineal artery, dividing into posterior scrotal or posterior labial and muscular branches. The posterior scrotal or labial nerves are usually double; they have medial and lateral branches that run over the perineal membrane and pass anteriorly in the lateral part of the urogenital triangle with the posterior scrotal or posterior labial branches of the perineal artery. They supply the skin of the scrotum or labia majora, respectively, overlapping the distribution of the perineal branch of the posterior femoral cutaneous nerve and inferior anal nerve. In females, the posterior labial branches also supply sensory fibres to the skin of the distal vagina.

Dorsal nerve of the penis or clitoris

The dorsal nerve of the penis or clitoris runs anteriorly above the internal pudendal artery along the ischiopubic ramus, deep to the perineal membrane. It supplies the corpus cavernosum and accompanies the dorsal artery of the penis or clitoris between the layers of the suspensory ligament of the penis or clitoris. The dorsal nerve of the penis runs on the dorsum of the penis to end in the glans penis.

Perforating cutaneous nerve

The perforating cutaneous nerve usually arises from the posterior aspects of the second and third sacral ventral spinal rami. It pierces the sacrotuberous ligament, curves round the inferior border of gluteus maximus and supplies the skin over the inferomedial aspect of this muscle. The nerve may arise from the pudendal nerve or it may be absent, in which case it may be replaced either by a branch from the posterior femoral cutaneous nerve or from the third and fourth, or fourth and fifth, sacral ventral rami.

Nerve to quadratus femoris

The nerve to quadratus femoris arises from the ventral branches of the fourth lumbar to the first sacral ventral rami. It leaves the pelvis via the greater sciatic foramen below piriformis, descends on the ischium deep to the sciatic nerve, the gemelli and the tendon of obturator internus, and supplies gemellus inferior, quadratus femoris and the hip joint.

Nerve to obturator internus

The nerve to obturator internus arises from the ventral branches of the fifth lumbar and first and second sacral ventral rami. It leaves the pelvis via the greater sciatic foramen below piriformis, supplies a branch to the upper posterior surface of gemellus superior, crosses the ischial spine lateral to the internal pudendal vessels, re-enters the pelvis via the lesser sciatic foramen, and enters the pelvic surface of obturator internus.

Posterior femoral cutaneous nerve (posterior cutaneous nerve of the thigh)

The posterior femoral cutaneous nerve (posterior cutaneous nerve of the thigh) arises from the dorsal branches of the first and second, and the ventral branches of the second and third sacral rami. It leaves the pelvis via the greater sciatic foramen below piriformis and descends under gluteus maximus with the inferior gluteal vessels, lying posterior or medial to the sciatic nerve (see Fig. 77.47). It descends in the back of the thigh superficial to the long head of biceps femoris, deep to the fascia lata. It pierces the deep fascia behind the knee and accompanies the short saphenous vein to mid-calf, its terminal twigs connecting with the sural nerve. Its branches are cutaneous and are distributed to the gluteal region, perineum, posterior thigh and proximal posterior leg.

Three or four gluteal branches (inferior clunial nerves) curl round the lower border of gluteus maximus to supply the skin over the inferolateral portion of the muscle. The perineal branch supplies the superomedial skin in the thigh, curves forwards across the hamstrings below the ischial tuberosity, pierces the fascia lata and then runs in the superficial perineal fascia to the scrotal or labial skin. It communicates with the inferior anal (rectal) and posterior scrotal or labial branches of the perineal nerve, and gives numerous branches to the skin of the back and medial side of the thigh, the popliteal fossa and the proximal part of the back of the leg. One study found the perineal branch of the posterior cutaneous nerve of the thigh in about one-half of specimens (Tubbs et al 2009).

Nerve to piriformis

The nerve to piriformis usually arises from the dorsal branches of the first and second sacral ventral rami (sometimes only the second) and enters the anterior surface of piriformis.

Sciatic nerve

The sciatic nerve is typically 2 cm wide at its origin and is the thickest nerve in the body. It travels in the posterior compartment of the thigh and supplies the leg and foot. It leaves the pelvis via the greater sciatic foramen, usually inferior to piriformis, and descends between the greater trochanter and ischial tuberosity, along the back of the thigh, dividing into the tibial and common fibular nerves at a varying level proximal to the knee (see Fig. 77.50; see also Fig. 76.11B). Superiorly, it lies deep to gluteus maximus, resting first on the posterior ischial surface with the nerve to quadratus femoris between them. It then crosses posterior to obturator internus, the gemelli and quadratus femoris, separated by the latter from obturator externus and the hip joint. It is accompanied medially by the posterior femoral cutaneous nerve and the inferior gluteal artery. More distally, it lies behind adductor magnus and is crossed posteriorly by the long head of biceps femoris. Its course corresponds to a line drawn from just medial to the midpoint between the ischial tuberosity and greater trochanter to the apex of the popliteal fossa. Articular branches arise proximally to supply the hip joint through its posterior capsule; these are sometimes derived directly from the sacral plexus. Muscular branches are distributed to biceps femoris, semitendinosus, semimembranosus and the ischial part of adductor magnus.

The point of division of the sciatic nerve into its tibial and common fibular components is very variable: the two large nerves are only loosely held together as the sciatic nerve and the level of their separation in the thigh is variable. The common site is at the junction of the middle and lower thirds of the thigh, near the apex of the popliteal fossa, but the division may occur at any level above this point and, rarely, may occur below it: the common variations of the sciatic nerve have been classified into six types (Beaton and Anson 1937). The tibial nerve is derived from the anterior divisions of the sacral plexus and the common fibular nerve is derived from the posterior divisions of the plexus. The medial (tibial) component innervates the posterior thigh muscles, including the ischial part of adductor magnus, but not the short head of biceps femoris, which is supplied by the lateral (common fibular) component.

Blood supply to the sciatic nerve

In the gluteal region, the sciatic nerve is supplied by the inferior gluteal artery and cruciate anastomosis (the medial and lateral circumflex femoral arteries, inferior gluteal artery and the first perforating branch of the profunda femoris artery) (see Fig. 77.47). On rare occasions, it is supplied by branches from the superior gluteal or internal pudendal arteries, which reach the nerve on its medial side. Lower in the thigh, arterial branches derived from the perforating branches of the profunda femoris artery or the anastomotic chain between them or, occasionally, from the popliteal artery, enter the nerve on its lateral or anterolateral side (Sunderland 1945). The numerous arterial branches to the sciatic nerve anastomose with each other to form extraneural and intraneural arterial chains (Sunderland 1945, Ugrenovic et al 2013).

Lesions of the sciatic nerve

The sciatic nerve supplies the posterior thigh muscles and all the muscles below the knee, which means that a complete palsy of the sciatic nerve results in a flail foot and severe difficulty in walking. Fortunately, complete sciatic nerve palsy is very rare. The nerve is vulnerable in posterior dislocation of the hip. As it leaves the pelvis, it passes either inferior to piriformis or sometimes through the muscle, and at that point it may very rarely become entrapped or tethered; the piriformis syndrome is a controversial condition in which an anomalous relationship between piriformis and the sciatic nerve is thought to cause pain in the buttocks and along the course of the sciatic nerve. External compression over the buttock, e.g. in patients who lie immobile on a hard surface for a considerable length of time, can injure the nerve. However, the most common cause of serious sciatic nerve injury (and of the resulting major medicolegal claims) is iatrogenic (Dillow et al 2013). The nerve may be iatrogenically damaged in misplaced therapeutic injections into gluteus maximus. Sciatic nerve palsy occurs after total hip replacement or similar surgery in 1% of cases, and may be caused by sharp injury, burning from bone cement, traction from instruments, manipulation of the hip, inadvertent lengthening of the femur, or haematoma surrounding the nerve. For some reason, possibly anatomical, the common fibular component of the sciatic nerve is more usually affected, resulting in a foot drop and a high-stepping gait.

Tibial nerve

The tibial nerve, the larger component of the sciatic nerve, is derived from the ventral branches (anterior divisions) of the fourth and fifth lumbar and first to third sacral ventral rami. It descends along the posterior thigh and popliteal fossa to the distal border of popliteus. It then passes anterior to the arch of soleus with the popliteal artery and continues into the leg. In the thigh, it is overlapped proximally by the hamstring muscles but it becomes more superficial in the popliteal fossa, where it is lateral to the popliteal vessels. At the level of the knee, the tibial nerve becomes superficial to the popliteal vessels and crosses to the medial side of the artery. In the distal popliteal fossa, it is overlapped by the junction of the two heads of gastrocnemius.

In the leg, the tibial nerve is the nerve of the posterior compartment. It descends with the posterior tibial vessels to lie between the heel and the medial malleolus (see Fig. 78.4). Proximally, it is deep to soleus and gastrocnemius, but in its distal third is covered only by skin and fasciae, and overlapped sometimes by flexor hallucis longus. At first medial to the posterior tibial vessels, it crosses behind them and descends lateral to them until it bifurcates. It lies on tibialis posterior for most of its course except distally, where it adjoins the posterior surface of the tibia. The tibial nerve ends under the flexor retinaculum by dividing into the medial and lateral plantar nerves.

The branches of the tibial nerve are articular, muscular (to gastrocnemius, plantaris, soleus, popliteus, tibialis posterior, flexor digitorum longus and flexor hallucis longus), sural, medial calcaneal and medial and lateral plantar nerves.

Articular branches

Articular branches to the knee joint accompany the superior and inferior medial genicular arteries and the middle genicular artery; they form a plexus with a branch from the obturator nerve and also supply the oblique popliteal ligament. The branches accompanying the superior and inferior medial genicular arteries supply the medial part of the capsule. A branch of the nerve to popliteus (tibial nerve) supplies the posterior portion of the superior tibiofibular joint. Just before the tibial nerve bifurcates, it gives off branches that supply the ankle joint.

Muscular branches

Proximal muscular branches arise between the heads of gastrocnemius and supply gastrocnemius, plantaris, soleus and popliteus. The nerve to soleus enters its superficial aspect. The branch to popliteus descends obliquely across the popliteal vessels, curling round the distal border of the muscle to its anterior surface. It also supplies tibialis posterior, the superior tibiofibular joint and the tibia, and gives off an interosseous branch that descends near the fibula to reach the distal tibiofibular joint.

Muscular branches in the leg, either independently or by a common trunk, supply soleus (on its deep surface), tibialis posterior, flexor digitorum longus and flexor hallucis longus. The branch to flexor hallucis longus accompanies the fibular vessels.

Sural nerve

The sural nerve descends between the heads of gastrocnemius, pierces the deep fascia proximally in the leg, and is joined at a variable level by the sural communicating branch of the common fibular nerve. Some authors term this branch the lateral sural cutaneous nerve, and call the main trunk (from the tibial nerve) the medial sural cutaneous nerve. The sural nerve descends lateral to the calcaneal tendon, near the short saphenous vein, to the region between the lateral malleolus and the calcaneus, and supplies the posterior and lateral skin of the distal third of the leg. It then passes distal to the lateral malleolus along the lateral side of the foot and fifth toe, supplying the overlying skin. It connects with the posterior femoral cutaneous nerve in the leg and with the superficial fibular nerve on the dorsum of the foot.

The sural nerve is often used as an autologous peripheral nerve graft on the grounds that it is easily harvested, readily identified and exclusively cutaneous.

Medial calcaneal nerve

The medial calcaneal nerve arises from the tibial nerve and perforates the flexor retinaculum to supply the skin of the heel and medial side of the sole.

Medial plantar nerve

The medial plantar nerve is the larger terminal division of the tibial nerve, and lies lateral to the medial plantar artery. From its origin under the flexor retinaculum, it passes deep to abductor hallucis, then appears between it and flexor digitorum brevis, gives off a medial proper digital nerve to the great toe, and divides near the metatarsal bases into three common plantar digital nerves (see Fig. 79.27; see also Fig. 79.22).

Cutaneous branches pierce the plantar aponeurosis between abductor hallucis and flexor digitorum brevis to supply the skin of the sole of the foot. Muscular branches supply abductor hallucis, flexor digitorum brevis, flexor hallucis brevis and the first lumbrical. The first two arise near the origin of the nerve and enter the deep surfaces of the muscles. The branch to flexor hallucis brevis is from the hallucal medial digital nerve, and that to the first lumbrical from the first common plantar digital nerve. Articular branches supply the joints of the tarsus and metatarsus.

Three common plantar digital nerves pass between the slips of the plantar aponeurosis, each dividing into two proper digital branches. The first supplies adjacent sides of the great and second toes; the second supplies adjacent sides of the second and third toes; and the third supplies adjacent sides of the third and fourth toes, and also connects with the lateral plantar nerve. The first gives a branch to the first lumbrical. Each proper digital nerve has cutaneous and articular branches: near the distal phalanges, a dorsal branch supplies structures around the nail. Abductor hallucis, flexor hallucis brevis and the first lumbrical are all supplied by the medial plantar nerve.

Lateral plantar nerve

The lateral plantar nerve supplies the skin of the fifth toe, the lateral half of the fourth toe, and most of the deep muscles of the foot (see Fig. 79.22). It is located medial to the lateral plantar artery and courses anteriorly towards the tubercle of the fifth metatarsal. Next, it passes between flexor digitorum brevis and flexor accessorius, and ends between flexor digiti minimi brevis and abductor digiti minimi by dividing into superficial and deep branches. Before division, it supplies flexor accessorius and abductor digiti minimi, and gives rise to small branches that pierce the plantar aponeurosis to supply the skin of the lateral part of the sole (see Fig. 79.27). The superficial branch splits into two common plantar digital nerves: the lateral supplies the lateral side of the fifth toe, flexor digiti minimi brevis and the two interossei in the fourth intermetatarsal space; the medial connects with the third common plantar digital branch of the medial plantar nerve and divides into two to supply the adjoining sides of the fourth and fifth toes. The deep branch accompanies the lateral plantar artery deep to the flexor tendons and adductor hallucis, and supplies the second to fourth lumbricals, adductor hallucis and all the interossei (except those of the fourth intermetatarsal space). Branches to the second and third lumbricals pass distally deep to the transverse head of adductor hallucis, and travel around its distal border to reach them (see Video 79.1).

Lesions of the tibial nerve

The tibial nerve is vulnerable to direct injury in the popliteal fossa, where it lies superficial to the popliteal vessels at the level of the knee, or to compression at the tendinous arch of the soleus. It may be damaged in compartment syndrome that affects the deep flexor compartment of the calf. All nerves of the foot can be affected by entrapment, leading classically to a burning sensation in the distribution of that nerve. Tarsal tunnel syndrome is much less common than carpal tunnel syndrome. The flexor retinaculum may compress the tibial nerve or either of its branches (medial and lateral plantar nerves); entrapment at this level is most commonly due to a space-occupying lesion, e.g. a ganglion, or to compression by either a leash of vessels or the deep fascia associated with abductor hallucis. Compression of the first branch of the lateral plantar nerve (Baxter’s nerve) by the deep fascia that covers abductor hallucis has been implicated as a possible cause of chronic heel pain and of plantar fasciitis. (Plantar fasciitis, often caused by repetitive high-impact injury to the foot, may be associated with pain, especially over the medial calcaneal process, which may be exacerbated by passive ankle or great toe flexion.) The medial plantar nerve can be compressed at the ‘knot of Henry’, which is the point where the tendon of flexor hallucis longus crosses deep to the tendon of flexor digitorum longus, to reach its medial side in the sole of the foot. It may also be compressed between abductor hallucis and the navicular bone (‘jogger’s foot’). Sural nerve entrapment is usually not due to compression by fascial elements. Entrapment of the third common digital nerve as it passes deep to the intermetatarsal ligament of the third (or less commonly the second) web space can result in a Morton’s neuroma, which is probably the most common form of nerve entrapment in the foot.

Depending on the level of the injury, damage to the tibial nerve can produce weakness of knee flexion, plantarflexion, inversion and toe flexion, accompanied by sensory loss in the lower lateral leg, heel and sole of the foot.

Common fibular nerve

The common fibular nerve (common peroneal nerve) is the nerve of the anterior and lateral compartments in the leg. It is approximately half the size of the tibial nerve and is derived from the dorsal (posterior) branches of the fourth and fifth lumbar and first and second sacral ventral rami. It descends obliquely along the lateral side of the popliteal fossa to the fibular head, medial to biceps femoris. It lies between the tendon of biceps femoris, to which it is bound by fascia, and the lateral head of gastrocnemius (see Fig. 78.41). The nerve then passes into the anterolateral compartment of the leg through a tight opening in the thick fascia overlying tibialis anterior. It curves lateral to the neck of the fibula, lying on the bone deep to fibularis longus, and divides into superficial and deep fibular nerves; an articular trunk, derived from the deep fibular nerve, provides an articular branch that travels with the anterior tibial recurrent artery and a proximal branch to tibialis anterior.

The common fibular nerve supplies the anterolateral part of the knee joint capsule and the proximal tibiofibular joint and the skin on the anterior, posterior and lateral surfaces of the proximal leg. The superficial peroneal nerve supplies fibulares longus and brevis and the skin of the lower leg before dividing into medial and intermediate dorsal cutaneous nerves. The deep fibular nerve supplies muscular branches to tibialis anterior, extensors hallucis longus and digitorum longus and fibularis tertius, and an articular branch to the ankle joint, before dividing into lateral and medial terminal branches.

The common fibular nerve has articular and cutaneous branches, and terminates as the superficial and deep fibular nerves.

Articular branches

There are three articular branches. Two accompany the superior and inferior lateral genicular arteries; they may arise in common. The third, the recurrent articular branch, arises near the termination of the common fibular nerve. It ascends with the anterior recurrent tibial artery through tibialis anterior and supplies the anterolateral part of the knee joint capsule and the proximal tibiofibular joint.

Cutaneous branches

The two cutaneous branches, often from a common trunk, are the lateral sural and sural communicating nerves. The lateral sural cutaneous nerve (lateral cutaneous nerve of the calf) supplies the skin on the anterior, posterior and lateral surfaces of the proximal leg. The sural communicating nerve arises near the head of the fibula and crosses the lateral head of gastrocnemius to join the sural nerve. It may descend separately as far as the heel.

Lesions of the common fibular nerve

The common fibular nerve is relatively unprotected as it traverses the lateral aspect of the neck of the fibula and is easily compressed at this site, e.g. by plaster casts or ganglia. The nerve may also become entrapped by a fascial band beneath fibularis longus within the so-called fibular tunnel, between the attachments of fibularis longus to the head and shaft of the fibula. Traction lesions can accompany dislocations of the lateral compartment of the knee, and are most likely to occur if the distal attachments of biceps femoris and the ligaments that insert on to the fibular head are avulsed, possibly with a small part of the fibular head; the nerve is tethered to the tendon of biceps femoris by dense fascia and so is pulled proximally. Severe traction lesions may produce longitudinal injuries affecting a long segment of the common fibular nerve. Torsional injury following ankle injury (sprain or fracture) may result in common fibular neuropathy; the injury is transmitted from the ankle along the interosseous membrane to the proximal leg (Lalezari et al 2012). Patients with such injury present with a foot drop. Physical examination reveals weakness or paralysis of ankle dorsiflexion, toe extension and eversion of the foot, but inversion and plantar flexion are normal. Sensation on the dorsum of the foot, including the first dorsal web space, is diminished. The ankle reflex is preserved. Since the common fibular nerve divides at the fibular neck into the superficial and deep fibular nerves, injuries to the nerve at this level may damage either the main trunk or its branches. Electrodiagnostic studies can help localize a common fibular nerve injury to the fibular neck region. At this level, nerve conduction studies may show slowed velocities and electromyography would demonstrate denervation in the muscles innervated by the common fibular nerve (such as tibialis anterior or fibularis longus), whereas more proximally innervated muscles (particularly the short head of biceps femoris) would be normal. Injury specifically to the superficial fibular nerve will result in paralysis of eversion and sensory loss in the lower lateral aspect of the leg extending onto the dorsum of the foot. Damage to the deep fibular nerve results in paralysis of dorsiflexion and toe extension with sensory loss in the first interdigital web space.

Superficial fibular nerve

The superficial fibular nerve (superficial peroneal nerve) begins at the bifurcation of the common fibular nerve. It lies deep to fibularis longus at first, then passes anteroinferiorly between fibularis longus and brevis and extensor digitorum longus, and pierces the deep fascia in the distal third of the leg (see Fig. 78.41). It divides into a large medial dorsal cutaneous nerve and a smaller, more laterally placed, intermediate dorsal cutaneous nerve, usually after piercing the deep fascia, but sometimes while it is still deep to the fascia. As the nerve lies between the muscles it supplies fibularis longus, fibularis brevis and the skin of the lower leg. The deep course, i.e. the compartmental localization, and the peripheral digital distribution of the superficial fibular nerve are subject to considerable variation (see Kosinksi’s classification; Kosinski 1926, Solomon et al 2001).

Cutaneous branches

The medial dorsal cutaneous nerve passes in front of the ankle joint and divides into two dorsal digital branches; one of these supplies the medial side of the hallux and the other supplies the adjacent side of the second and third toes. It communicates with the saphenous and deep fibular nerves. The smaller intermediate branch crosses the dorsum of the foot laterally. It divides into dorsal digital branches that supply the contiguous sides of the third to fifth toes and the skin of the lateral aspect of the ankle, where it connects with the sural nerve. Both branches, especially the intermediate, are at risk during the placement of portal skin incisions for arthroscopy and during surgical approaches to the lateral malleolus. Branches of the superficial fibular nerve supply the skin of the dorsum of all the toes except that of the lateral side of the fifth toe (supplied by the sural nerve) and the adjoining sides of the great and second toes (supplied by the medial terminal branch of the deep fibular nerve). Some of the lateral branches of the superficial fibular nerve are frequently absent and are replaced by sural nerve branches.

Accessory fibular nerves

An accessory superficial fibular nerve and an accessory deep fibular nerve have been described as variant branches of the superficial fibular nerve; both are probably the product of atypical branching of the parent nerve deep to the deep fascia (see above).

Lesions of the superficial fibular nerve

A lesion of the superficial fibular nerve causes weakness of foot eversion and sensory loss on the lateral aspect of the leg that extends onto the dorsum of the foot. The nerve can be subject to entrapment as it penetrates the deep fascia of the leg, be involved in compartment syndrome that affects the lateral compartment of the leg, or be damaged in severe inversion injuries of the ankle.

Deep fibular nerve

The deep fibular nerve (deep peroneal nerve) begins at the bifurcation of the common fibular nerve, between the fibula and the proximal part of fibularis longus. It passes obliquely forwards deep to extensor digitorum longus to the front of the interosseous membrane and reaches the anterior tibial artery in the proximal third of the leg. It descends with the artery to the ankle, where it divides into lateral and medial terminal branches. As it descends, the nerve is first lateral to the artery, then anterior, and finally lateral again at the ankle.

Cutaneous and muscular branches

The deep fibular nerve supplies muscular branches to tibialis anterior, extensor hallucis longus, extensor digitorum longus and fibularis tertius, and an articular branch to the ankle joint.

The lateral terminal branch crosses the ankle deep to extensor digitorum brevis, enlarges as a pseudoganglion and supplies extensor digitorum brevis. From the enlargement, three minute interosseous branches supply the tarsal and metatarsophalangeal joints of the middle three toes.

The medial terminal branch runs distally on the dorsum of the foot lateral to the dorsalis pedis artery, and connects with the medial branch of the superficial fibular nerve in the first interosseous space. It divides into two dorsal digital nerves, which supply adjacent sides of the great and second toes. Before dividing, it gives off an interosseous branch, which supplies the first metatarsophalangeal joint. The deep fibular nerve may end as three terminal branches.

Lesions of the deep fibular nerve

Isolated injury to the deep fibular nerve may result from compartment syndrome that affects the anterior compartment of the leg or from an intraneural ganglion cyst (mucinous cyst within the nerve derived from the superior tibiofibular joint via the articular branch that travels with the anterior tibial recurrent artery (Spinner et al 2003)). The nerve is sometimes compressed by osteophytes in the region of the second tarsometatarsal joint.

Individuals with lesions of the deep fibular nerve have weakness of ankle dorsiflexion and extension of all toes but normal foot eversion. Sensory impairment is confined to the first interdigital web space.

Coccygeal plexus

The coccygeal plexus is formed by a small descending branch from the fourth sacral ventral ramus and by the fifth sacral and coccygeal ventral rami. The fifth sacral ventral ramus emerges from the sacral hiatus, curves round the lateral margin of the sacrum inferior to its cornu, and pierces ischiococcygeus inferiorly to reach its pelvic surface. Here it is joined by a descending branch of the fourth sacral ventral ramus; the small trunk so formed descends on the pelvic surface of ischiococcygeus, joins the minute coccygeal ventral ramus that emerges from the sacral hiatus, and curves round the lateral coccygeal margin, piercing ischiococcygeus to reach the pelvis. The small trunk that is formed in this way is the coccygeal plexus. Anococcygeal nerves arise from it and form a few fine filaments that pierce the sacrotuberous ligament to supply the adjacent skin.

Autonomic Nervous System

The autonomic nervous system represents the visceral component of the nervous system. It consists of neurones located within the CNS and the PNS that are concerned with the control of the internal environment, through the innervation of secretory glands and cardiac and smooth muscle. Its functions are, however, closely integrated with those of the somatic nervous system.

Visceral efferent pathways differ from their somatic equivalents in that the former are interrupted by peripheral synapses, there being a sequence of at least two neurones between the CNS and the target structure (see Fig. 24.11). These are referred to as preganglionic and postganglionic neurones, respectively. The somata of preganglionic neurones are located in the visceral efferent nuclei of the brainstem and in the lateral horn of the spinal cord. Their axons, which are usually finely myelinated, exit from the CNS in certain cranial and spinal nerves, and then pass to peripheral ganglia, where they synapse with postganglionic neurones. The axons of postganglionic neurones are usually unmyelinated. Postganglionic neurones are more numerous than preganglionic ones; one preganglionic neurone may synapse with 15–20 postganglionic neurones, which permits the wide distribution of many autonomic effects.

The autonomic nervous system is traditionally divided into the sympathetic and parasympathetic systems that coordinate the neural regulation of visceral and homeostatic functions. In general, sympathetic activity results in the constriction of cutaneous arteries (increasing blood supply to the heart, muscles and brain), cardiac acceleration, an increase in blood pressure, contraction of sphincters and depression of peristalsis, all of which mobilize body energy stores for dealing with increased activity. Parasympathetic activity results in cardiac slowing and an increase in intestinal glandular and peristaltic activities, which may be considered to conserve body energy stores.

Sympathetic Nervous System

Preganglionic sympathetic axons originate from neuronal somata in the intermediolateral nucleus (lateral horn) of the spinal cord from the first thoracic to the second lumbar spinal segments (T1–L2) (see Fig. 24.12). Postganglionic sympathetic axons arise from neuronal somata in the sympathetic (paravertebral) trunk or in a more peripheral plexus. There are between 10 and 12 (usually 11) thoracic ganglia, four lumbar ganglia, and four or five ganglia in the sacral region. Cervical sympathetic ganglia are usually reduced to three by fusion.

Preganglionic axons are myelinated with diameters of 1.5–4 μm and release acetylcholine as their principal neurotransmitter. They travel initially with the corresponding ventral roots and leave the latter as white rami communicantes to enter the adjacent sympathetic ganglion in the sympathetic trunk (see Fig. 24.13). Their targets vary; some synapse in the sympathetic ganglion that they enter, whereas others ascend or descend in the sympathetic trunk to synapse in cervical or lumbar ganglia, respectively. Axons destined for the cervical ganglia are mainly derived from preganglionic neurones in the first thoracic spinal nerve. Many of the preganglionic axons that originate in the lower thoracic spinal segments (T5–T12) do not synapse locally but enter the abdominal cavity as the thoracic splanchnic nerves. These nerves pass through the posterior mediastinum and respiratory diaphragm to enter the abdominal cavity where they synapse either in prevertebral ganglia that surround the origin of the major visceral arteries arising from the abdominal aorta, e.g. the coeliac and superior mesenteric ganglia, or around the medullary chromaffin cells of the suprarenal gland.

The axons of postganglionic neurones are unmyelinated and generally longer than those of preganglionic neurones, an exception being some of those that innervate pelvic viscera. Postganglionic axons are distributed to target organs in various ways. Those from a ganglion of the sympathetic trunk may return to the spinal nerve of preganglionic origin through a grey ramus communicans, which usually joins the nerve just proximal to the white ramus, and are then distributed through ventral and dorsal spinal rami to blood vessels, sweat glands, hairs, etc., in their zone of supply. Segmental areas vary in extent and overlap considerably and the extent of innervation of different effector systems, e.g. vasomotor, sudomotor, etc., by a particular nerve may differ (a single preganglionic fibre probably synapses with the postganglionic neurones in only one effector system). Alternatively, postganglionic fibres can pass in a medial branch of a ganglion direct to particular viscera, or innervate adjacent blood vessels, or pass along them externally to their peripheral distribution. They may ascend or descend before leaving the sympathetic trunk as described above. Many fibres are distributed along arteries and ducts as plexuses to distant effectors, e.g. the internal carotid nerve, a continuation of the sympathetic trunk, issues from the cranial pole of the superior ganglion and accompanies the internal carotid artery through its canal into the cranial cavity.

The principal neurotransmitter released by postganglionic sympathetic neurones is noradrenaline (norepinephrine). The sympathetic system has a much wider distribution than the parasympathetic system: it innervates all sweat glands, the arrector pili muscles, the muscular walls of many blood vessels, the heart, lungs and respiratory tree, the abdominopelvic viscera, the oesophagus, the muscles of the iris, and the non-striated muscle of the urogenital tract, eyelids and elsewhere. Postganglionic sympathetic fibres that return to the spinal nerves are vasoconstrictor to blood vessels, secretomotor to sweat glands and motor to the arrector pili muscles within their dermatomes. Most, if not all, peripheral nerves contain postganglionic sympathetic fibres. Those reaching the viscera are concerned with general vasoconstriction, bronchial and bronchiolar dilation, modification of glandular secretion, pupillary dilation, inhibition of gastrointestinal muscle contraction, etc.

Sympathetic trunk

The sympathetic trunk is a ganglionated nerve cord that extends on the side of the vertebral column from the cranial base to the coccyx. The ganglia are joined to spinal nerves by short connecting nerves called white and grey rami communicantes. Preganglionic axons join the trunk through the white rami communicantes, while postganglionic axons leave the trunk in the grey rami. In the thorax, the trunks are anterior to the heads of the ribs, in the abdomen they lie anterolateral to the bodies of the lumbar vertebrae, and in the pelvis they are anterior to the sacrum and medial to the anterior sacral foramina. Anterior to the coccyx the two trunks meet in a single, median, terminal ganglion.

Cervical sympathetic system

In the neck, each sympathetic trunk lies posterior to the carotid sheath and anterior to the transverse processes of the cervical vertebrae. The cervical sympathetic trunk lies on the prevertebral fascia behind the carotid sheath and contains three interconnected ganglia: the superior, middle and inferior (stellate or cervicothoracic) (see Figs 35.17–35.18). There may occasionally, however, be two or four ganglia. The cervical sympathetic ganglia send grey rami communicantes to all the cervical spinal nerves but receive no white rami communicantes from them. Their spinal preganglionic fibres emerge in the white rami communicantes of the upper five thoracic spinal nerves (mainly the upper three), and ascend in the sympathetic trunk to synapse in the cervical ganglia. In their course, the grey rami communicantes may pierce longus capitis or scalenus anterior.

Superior cervical ganglion

The superior cervical ganglion is the largest of the three ganglia (see Fig. 35.17). It lies on the transverse processes of the second and third cervical vertebrae and is probably formed from four fused ganglia, judging by its grey rami communicantes to the upper four cervical spinal nerves. The internal carotid artery within the carotid sheath is anterior, and longus capitis is posterior. The lower end of the ganglion is united by a connecting trunk to the middle cervical ganglion. Postganglionic branches are distributed in the internal carotid nerve, which ascends with the internal carotid artery into the carotid canal to enter the cranial cavity, and in lateral, medial and anterior branches. They supply vasoconstrictor and sudomotor nerves to the face and neck, dilator pupillae and smooth muscle in the eyelids and orbitalis.

Lateral branches

The lateral branches of the superior cervical ganglion are grey rami communicantes to the upper four cervical spinal nerves and to some of the cranial nerves. Branches pass to the inferior vagal ganglion, the hypoglossal nerve, the superior jugular bulb and associated jugular glomus or glomera, and to the meninges in the posterior cranial fossa. Another branch, the jugular nerve, ascends to the cranial base and divides into two; one part joins the inferior glossopharyngeal ganglion and the other joins the superior vagal ganglion.

Medial branches

The medial branches of the superior cervical ganglion are the laryngopharyngeal and cardiac branches. The laryngopharyngeal branches supply the carotid body and pass to the side of the pharynx, joining glossopharyngeal and vagal rami to form the pharyngeal plexus. A cardiac branch arises by two or more filaments from the lower part of the superior cervical ganglion and occasionally receives a twig from the trunk between the superior and middle cervical ganglia. It is thought to contain only efferent fibres, the preganglionic outflow being from the upper thoracic segments of the spinal cord, and to be devoid of pain fibres from the heart. It descends behind the common carotid artery, anterior to longus colli, and crosses anterior to the inferior thyroid artery and recurrent laryngeal nerve. The courses on the two sides then differ. The right cardiac branch usually passes posterior, but sometimes anterior, to the subclavian artery and runs posterolateral to the brachiocephalic trunk to join the deep (dorsal) part of the cardiac plexus behind the aortic arch. It has other sympathetic connections. About mid-neck, it receives filaments from the external laryngeal nerve. Inferiorly, one or two vagal cardiac branches join it. As it enters the thorax, it is joined by a filament from the recurrent laryngeal nerve. Filaments from the nerve also communicate with the thyroid branches of the middle cervical ganglion. The left cardiac branch, in the thorax, is anterior to the left common carotid artery and crosses anterior to the left side of the aortic arch to reach the superficial (ventral) part of the cardiac plexus. It may descend on the right of the aorta to end in the deep (dorsal) part of the cardiac plexus. It communicates with the cardiac branches of the middle and inferior cervical sympathetic ganglia and sometimes with the inferior cervical cardiac branches of the left vagus nerve, and forms a plexus on the ascending aorta with branches from these mixed nerves

Anterior branches

The anterior branches of the superior cervical ganglion ramify on the common and external carotid arteries and the branches of the external carotid, and form a delicate plexus around each, in which small ganglia are occasionally found. The plexus around the facial artery supplies a filament to the submandibular ganglion; the plexus on the middle meningeal artery sends one ramus to the otic ganglion and another, the external petrosal nerve, to the facial ganglion. Many of the fibres coursing along the external carotid and its branches ultimately leave them to travel to facial sweat glands via branches of the trigeminal nerve.

Middle cervical ganglion

The middle cervical ganglion is the smallest of the three cervical sympathetic ganglia and is occasionally absent, in which case it may be replaced by minute ganglia in the sympathetic trunk or may be fused with the superior ganglion. It is usually found at the level of the sixth cervical vertebra, anterior or just superior to the inferior thyroid artery, or it may adjoin the inferior cervical ganglion. It probably represents a coalescence of the ganglia of the fifth and sixth cervical segments, judging by its postganglionic rami, which join the fifth and sixth cervical spinal nerves (but sometimes also the fourth and seventh). It is connected to the inferior cervical ganglion by two or more very variable cords. The posterior cord usually splits to enclose the vertebral artery, while the anterior cord loops down anterior to, and then below, the first part of the subclavian artery, medial to the origin of its internal thoracic branch, and supplies rami to it. This loop is the ansa subclavia and is frequently multiple, lies in close contact with the cervical pleura, and typically connects with the phrenic nerve, and sometimes with the vagus nerve (see Fig. 35.18).

The middle cervical ganglion gives off thyroid and cardiac branches. The thyroid branches accompany the inferior thyroid artery to the thyroid gland. They communicate with the superior cardiac, external laryngeal and recurrent laryngeal nerves, and send branches to the parathyroid glands. Fibres to both glands are largely vasomotor but some reach the secretory cells. The cardiac branch, the largest sympathetic cardiac nerve, arises either from the ganglion itself or more often from the sympathetic trunk cranial or caudal to it. On the right side, it descends behind the common carotid artery and anterior or posterior to the subclavian artery, to the trachea, where it receives a few filaments from the recurrent laryngeal nerve before joining the right half of the deep (dorsal) part of the cardiac plexus. In the neck, it connects with the superior cardiac and recurrent laryngeal nerves. On the left side, the cardiac nerve enters the thorax between the left common carotid and subclavian arteries to join the left half of the deep (dorsal) part of the cardiac plexus. Fine branches from the middle cervical ganglion also pass to the trachea and oesophagus.

Inferior (cervicothoracic/stellate) ganglion

The inferior cervical ganglion (cervicothoracic/stellate) is irregular in shape and much larger than the middle cervical ganglion (see Figs 35.18, 48.16). It is probably formed by a fusion of the lower two cervical and first thoracic segmental ganglia, sometimes including the second and even third and fourth thoracic ganglia. The first thoracic ganglion may be separate, leaving an inferior cervical ganglion above it. The sympathetic trunk turns backwards at the junction of the neck and thorax, and so the long axis of the cervicothoracic ganglion becomes almost anteroposterior. The ganglion lies on or just lateral to the lateral border of longus colli between the base of the transverse process of the seventh cervical vertebra and the neck of the first rib (which are both posterior to it). The vertebral vessels are anterior, and the ganglion is separated from the posterior aspect of the cervical pleura inferiorly by the suprapleural membrane. The costocervical trunk of the subclavian artery branches near the lower pole of the ganglion, and the supreme intercostal artery is lateral.

A small vertebral ganglion may be present on the sympathetic trunk anterior or anteromedial to the origin of the vertebral artery and directly superior to the subclavian artery. When present, it may provide the ansa subclavia. It is also joined to the inferior cervical ganglion by fibres enclosing the vertebral artery and is usually regarded as a detached part of the middle cervical or inferior cervical ganglion. Like the middle cervical ganglion, it may supply grey rami communicantes to the fourth and fifth cervical spinal nerves. The inferior cervical ganglion sends grey rami communicantes to the seventh and eighth cervical and first thoracic spinal nerves, and gives off a cardiac branch, branches to nearby vessels and sometimes a branch to the vagus nerve.

The grey rami communicantes to the seventh cervical spinal nerve vary from one to five (two being the usual number). A third often ascends medial to the vertebral artery in front of the transverse process of the seventh cervical vertebra. It connects with the seventh cervical nerve, and sends a filament upwards through the transverse foramen of the sixth cervical vertebra in company with the vertebral vessels to join the sixth cervical spinal nerve as it emerges from the intervertebral foramen. An inconstant ramus may traverse the transverse foramen of the seventh cervical vertebra. Grey rami to the eighth cervical spinal nerve vary from three to six in number.

The cardiac branch descends behind the subclavian artery and along the anterior aspect of the trachea to the deep cardiac plexus. Behind the artery, it connects with the recurrent laryngeal nerve and the cardiac branch of the middle cervical ganglion (the latter is often replaced by fine branches of the inferior cervical ganglion and ansa subclavia).

The branches to blood vessels form plexuses on the subclavian artery and its branches. The subclavian supply is derived from the inferior cervical ganglion and ansa subclavia, and typically extends to the first part of the axillary artery, although a few fibres may extend further. An extension of the subclavian plexus to the internal thoracic artery may be joined by a branch of the phrenic nerve.

Within the foramina transversaria and intertransverse spaces, the cervical grey rami communicantes form intersegmental arcades as they communicate with one another and the ventral rami of the upper five or six cervical spinal nerves. These arcades accompany the second part of the vertebral artery and create the appearance of a long nerve known as the vertebral nerve. Fine filaments from this nerve and the grey rami communicantes form the vertebral plexus on the surface of the vertebral artery. This plexus contains not only sympathetic efferent fibres but also somatic sensory fibres from the adventitia of the artery with cell bodies in the cervical dorsal root ganglia. The vertebral nerve sends filaments to the posterolateral corners of the cervical intervertebral discs (Bogduk et al 1988), and gives rise to the meningeal branches (sinuvertebral nerves) at each cervical segment. The vertebral plexus, which contains some neuronal cell bodies, continues into the skull along the vertebral and basilar arteries and their branches as far as the posterior cerebral artery, where it meets a plexus from the internal carotid artery. The plexus on the inferior thyroid artery reaches the thyroid gland and connects with the recurrent and external laryngeal nerves, the cardiac branch of the superior cervical ganglion and the common carotid plexus.

Horner’s syndrome

Any condition or injury that destroys the sympathetic trunk ascending from the thorax through the neck into the face results in Horner’s syndrome (Bernard–Horner syndrome, oculosympathetic palsy), characterized by a drooping eyelid (ptosis), sunken globe (enophthalmos), narrow palpebral fissure, contracted pupil (meiosis), and vasodilation and lack of thermal sweating (anhydrosis) of the face on the affected side. Classically, this is seen in patients with bronchial carcinomas that have invaded the sympathetic trunk and it is a recognized complication of cervical sympathectomy or a radical neck dissection. Avulsion of the first thoracic nerve from the spinal cord may be diagnosed by development of the syndrome after closed traction lesion of the supraclavicular brachial plexus. Congenital Horner’s syndrome has been reported in association with ipsilateral internal carotid artery agenesis (Fons et al 2009). Special features of congenital Horner’s syndrome are unilateral straight hair and abnormalities of iris pigmentation in one or both eyes (heterochromia iridis or heterochromia iridum), usually inherited as an autosomal dominant trait and attributed to disruption of the postganglionic sympathetic pathway producing a neurotropic dysgenesis of iris melanocytes ([Rennie 2011]). Connections between the recurrent laryngeal nerve, the vagus and cervical sympathetic have been linked with Horner’s syndrome complicating thyroidectomy.

Thoracic sympathetic system

The left and right thoracic sympathetic trunks and associated ganglia (commonly 11 in number) sit posterior to the costal part of the parietal pleura on either side of the vertebral column. The majority of the thoracic sympathetic ganglia lie anterior to the head of a rib; the first thoracic and inferior cervical ganglia are fused, and the inferior two or three thoracic ganglia are often located lateral to their correspondingly numbered vertebral bodies (see Fig. 56.6). A tumour of the superior pulmonary sulcus (apex of lung) may compress the ventral ramus of the first thoracic spinal nerve, the cervicothoracic ganglion or the sympathetic trunk (see Fig. 54.2) resulting in a loss of sympathetic innervation to the ipsilateral side of the head (Horner’s syndrome) (Nikolaos et al 2014) and pain radiating to the medial aspect of the ipsilateral forearm (Bruzzi et al 2008).

Preganglionic sympathetic axons originate from neuronal somata in the intermediolateral nucleus (lateral horn) of the spinal cord from T1 to L2. They travel initially with the corresponding ventral roots (rami) and leave the latter as white rami communicantes to enter the adjacent sympathetic ganglion in the sympathetic trunk. Their targets vary; some synapse in the sympathetic ganglion that they enter, whereas others ascend or descend in the sympathetic trunk to synapse in cervical or lumbar ganglia, respectively. Many of the preganglionic axons that originate in the lower thoracic spinal segments (T5–T12) do not synapse locally but enter the abdominal cavity as the thoracic splanchnic nerves. These nerves pass through the posterior mediastinum and respiratory diaphragm to enter the abdominal cavity where they synapse either in prevertebral ganglia that surround the origin of the major visceral arteries arising from the abdominal aorta, e.g. the coeliac and superior mesenteric ganglia, or around the medullary chromaffin cells of the suprarenal gland. Axons destined for the cervical ganglia are mainly derived from preganglionic neurones in the first thoracic spinal nerve.

Greater thoracic splanchnic nerve

On each side, the greater thoracic splanchnic nerve is derived from the medial, branches of the fifth to ninth thoracic ganglia. It gives off branches to the descending thoracic aorta and enters the abdomen through the fibres of the ipsilateral crus of the respiratory diaphragm, on which it descends anteroinferiorly. The main trunk of the nerve enters the superior aspect of the coeliac ganglion, where most of the preganglionic fibres synapse (but not those destined for the medulla of the suprarenal gland).

Lesser thoracic splanchnic nerve

On each side, the lesser thoracic splanchnic nerve is derived from the medial branches of the tenth and eleventh (or ninth and tenth) thoracic ganglia. It enters the abdomen running through the most inferior fibres of the ipsilateral crus of the respiratory diaphragm or under the medial arcuate ligament, and then lies on the crus as it runs anteroinferiorly. The trunk of the nerve joins the aorticorenal ganglion and may give branches to the lateral aspect of the coeliac ganglion. It occasionally joins the greater and least splanchnic nerves as a single splanchnic nerve.

Least thoracic splanchnic nerve

On each side, the least thoracic splanchnic nerve is derived from the medial branches of the eleventh and/or twelfth thoracic ganglion. It enters the abdomen medial to the sympathetic trunk under the medial arcuate ligament of the respiratory diaphragm and runs inferiorly to join the renal plexus. The trunk of the nerve enters the aorticorenal ganglion and may give branches to the lateral aspect of the coeliac ganglion. It is sometimes part of the lesser splanchnic nerve, when it forms a twig that enters the renal plexus just below the aorticorenal ganglion.

The thoracic splanchnic nerves show considerable individual variation in their origin and distribution (Loukas et al 2010). For example, the greater splanchnic nerve can receive a contribution from the fourth or tenth thoracic ganglion of the sympathetic trunk or originate only from the sixth to ninth ganglia.

Lumbar sympathetic system

The lumbar part of each sympathetic trunk usually contains four ganglia lying on the anterolateral aspects of the lumbar vertebrae along the medial margin of psoas major (see Figs 59.2–59.4) (Murata et al 2003). Superiorly, it is continuous with the thoracic part of the sympathetic trunk posterior to the medial arcuate ligament. Inferiorly, it passes posterior to the common iliac vessels and is continuous with the sacral part of the sympathetic trunk. On the right side, it lies posterior to the inferior vena cava; on the left, it is posterior to the lateral aortic nodes. It is anterior to most of the lumbar vessels but may pass behind some lumbar veins.

On each side, the first, second and sometimes the third lumbar ventral rami are connected to the lumbar part of the sympathetic trunk by white rami communicantes. All lumbar ventral rami are joined near their origins by long, slender, grey rami communicantes from the four lumbar ganglia. Their arrangement is irregular: one ganglion can give rami to two or three lumbar ventral rami, one lumbar ventral ramus can receive rami from two ganglia, or grey rami can leave the sympathetic trunk between ganglia (Murata et al 2003).

Somatic and vascular branches

Sympathetic nerve branches accompany the lumbar arteries round the sides of the vertebral bodies, medial to the fibrous arches to which psoas major is attached, to provide sympathetic innervation to the segmental distribution of the lumbar arteries. Branches from the lumbar ganglia innervate the abdominal aorta and common, external and internal iliac arteries, forming delicate nerve plexuses that extend along the vessels. Other postganglionic sympathetic nerves to vessels and skin travel with somatic nerves. Thus, the femoral nerve carries vasoconstrictor sympathetic nerves to the femoral artery and its branches in the thigh, as well as sympathetic fibres in its cutaneous branches. Postganglionic fibres travelling with the obturator nerve supply the obturator artery and a variable patch of skin of the medial thigh. Sympathetic denervation of vessels in the lower limb can occur by removing or ablating the proximal three lumbar ganglia and intervening parts of the sympathetic trunk; this procedure can be useful for treating some varieties of vascular insufficiency of the lower limb.

Lumbar splanchnic nerves

Four lumbar splanchnic nerves pass as medial branches from the ganglia to join the coeliac, inferior mesenteric and superior hypogastric plexuses (see Fig. 59.4). The first lumbar splanchnic nerve, from the first ganglion of the lumbar part of the sympathetic trunk, gives branches to the coeliac, renal and inferior mesenteric plexuses. The second lumbar splanchnic nerve joins the inferior part of the intermesenteric or inferior mesenteric plexus. The third lumbar splanchnic arises from the third or fourth ganglion and joins the superior hypogastric plexus. The fourth lumbar splanchnic nerve from the lowest ganglion joins the distal part of the superior hypogastric plexus, or the hypogastric nerves. It is important to note that lumbar splanchnic nerves contribute to the superior and inferior hypogastric plexuses and therefore to the innervation of the neck of the urinary bladder, ductus deferens and prostate, among other structures. Injury to these nerves, e.g. during aortoiliac surgery, can result in sexual dysfunction.

Pelvic sympathetic system

The sacral part of the sympathetic trunk supplies the pelvic organs and vascular system. It usually consists of four or five interconnected ganglia located medial or anterior to the anterior sacral foramina beneath the presacral fascia (Oh et al 2004) (see Fig. 71.11). Occasionally, one or two coccygeal ganglia are present. The first sacral ganglion is the largest and succeeding ganglia become progressively smaller (Blaszczyk 1981). The sacral sympathetic trunk is often asymmetric, with absent or fused ganglia, and cross-communications between sides are frequent. Each ganglion sends at least one grey ramus communicans to its adjacent spinal nerve but up to eleven such branches from a single ganglion have been reported ([Potts 1925]).

Superiorly, the sacral part of the sympathetic trunk is continuous with the lumbar part of the sympathetic trunk, and preganglionic fibres descend from the distal lumbar spinal cord segments via this route. The right and left trunks converge distal to the most inferior ganglia and unite to form a solitary retroperitoneal structure, the ganglion impar (ganglion of Walther), which lies at a variable level between the sacrococcygeal joint and the tip of the coccyx; it is occasionally paired, unilateral or absent (Oh et al 2004). Grey rami communicantes pass from the ganglia to sacral and coccygeal spinal nerves and there are no white rami communicantes. Medial branches connect across the midline, and twigs from the first two ganglia join the inferior hypogastric plexus or the hypogastric nerve. Other branches form a plexus on the median sacral artery.

Nociceptive afferents from the perineum and terminal urogenital regions pass to the ganglion impar and the sacral parasympathetic trunks: anaesthetic blockade of the ganglion impar can be used to treat intractable perineal pain carried by visceral afferent fibres in patients with pelvic cancers (Toshniwal et al 2007).

Vascular branches

Preganglionic fibres for the vessels supplying the pelvis and lower limb are derived from the lower three thoracic and upper two or three lumbar spinal cord segments. They reach the lower thoracic and upper lumbar ganglia through white rami communicantes and descend through the sympathetic trunk to synapse in the lumbar ganglia. Postganglionic fibres pass from these ganglia via grey rami communicantes to the second, third and fourth lumbar ventral rami and then to the femoral nerve, which carries them to the femoral artery and its branches. Some fibres descend through the lumbar ganglia to synapse in the upper two or three sacral ganglia, from which postganglionic axons pass through grey rami communicantes to the roots of the sacral plexus. Those in the pudendal and superior and inferior gluteal nerves accompany the arteries of the same name to the gluteal and perineal tissues; branches can also supply the pelvic nodes. Those joining the tibial nerve are carried to the popliteal artery and are distributed via its branches to the leg and foot.

Sympathetic denervation of vessels in the lower limb is used, rarely, for treating vascular insufficiency of the lower limb; it can be effected by removing or ablating the upper three lumbar sympathetic ganglia and the intervening parts of the sympathetic trunk.

Sacral splanchnic nerves

Sacral splanchnic nerves pass directly from the ganglia of the sacral part of the sympathetic trunk to the inferior hypogastric plexus and, from there, to pelvic viscera; they usually arise from the first two sacral ganglia.

Autonomic innervation of the limbs

The autonomic nerve supply to the limbs is exclusively sympathetic. The preganglionic sympathetic inflow to the upper limb is derived from neurones in the intermediolateral nucleus of spinal cord segments from T2 to T6/7. Myelinated preganglionic axons pass from the spinal nerves to the thoracic sympathetic trunk via white rami communicates and pass up the trunk to the middle cervical and inferior cervical (stellate or cervicothoracic) ganglia, where they relay. The unmyelinated postganglionic fibres are distributed by grey rami communicantes to the nerves of origin of the brachial plexus; innervation is particularly rich in the palmar skin of the hand and in the skin of the axilla. C5 and C6 receive grey rami from the middle cervical ganglion; C7 and C8 receive grey rami from the inferior cervical ganglion; T1 not only receives a grey ramus from the inferior cervical ganglion but also contributes a white ramus to it (see Fig. 48.16). Interruption of this white ramus is one cause of Horner’s (Bernard–Horner) syndrome.

The preganglionic sympathetic outflow to the lower limb is derived from neurones in the intermediolateral nucleus of spinal cord segments T10–T12 and L1, L2. Fibres pass in white rami communicantes to the sympathetic trunk and synapse in the lumbar and sacral ganglia. Postganglionic fibres pass in grey rami communicantes to enter the lumbar and sacral plexuses; many are distributed to the skin via the cutaneous branches of the nerves derived from these plexuses. Blood vessels to the lower limb receive their sympathetic nerve supply via adjacent peripheral nerves. Postganglionic fibres accompanying the iliac arteries are destined mainly for the pelvis but may supply vessels in the proximal thigh

Parasympathetic Nervous System

Preganglionic parasympathetic neurones are located in the Edinger–Westphal and superior and inferior salivatory nuclei in the brainstem (see Fig. 28.3) and in the intermediate grey matter of the second to fourth sacral segments of the spinal cord. Their axons, which are myelinated, emerge from the CNS only in the oculomotor, facial, glossopharyngeal and vagus nerves, and as the pelvic splanchnic nerves in the second to fourth sacral spinal nerves. Preganglionic parasympathetic neurones are cholinergic. The somata of postganglionic parasympathetic neurones are mostly sited distant from the CNS, either in discrete ganglia located near the structures innervated, or dispersed in the walls of viscera.

Cranial part of the parasympathetic system

The cranial part of the parasympathetic system contains four small paired peripheral ganglia, ciliary, pterygopalatine, submandibular and otic, in which preganglionic axons relay. (These efferent parasympathetic ganglia are unlike the trigeminal, facial, glossopharyngeal and vagal sensory ganglia, all of which are concerned exclusively with afferent impulses and contain the cell bodies of sensory neurones.) The cranial parasympathetic ganglia are also traversed by afferent fibres, postganglionic sympathetic fibres and, in the case of the otic ganglion, by branchial efferent fibres; however, none of these fibres synapses in the ganglia. Postganglionic parasympathetic fibres are usually unmyelinated and shorter than their counterparts in the sympathetic system because the ganglia in which the parasympathetic fibres synapse are either in or near the viscera they supply. Postganglionic parasympathetic neurones are cholinergic. In the head, parasympathetic fibres are secretomotor to the lacrimal and parotid, submandibular and sublingual salivary glands and innervate intraocular smooth muscle (sphincter pupillae and the ciliary muscle).

Otic ganglion

The otic ganglion is a small (major diameter 3–4 mm), oval, flat reddish-grey ganglion situated just below the foramen ovale. It is a peripheral parasympathetic ganglion related topographically to the mandibular nerve but connected functionally with the glossopharyngeal nerve (see Fig. 42.11). Near its junction with the trigeminal motor root, the mandibular nerve lies lateral to the ganglion, tensor veli palatini lies medially, separating the ganglion from the cartilaginous part of the pharyngotympanic tube, and the middle meningeal artery is posterior to the ganglion. The otic ganglion usually surrounds the origin of the nerve to medial pterygoid. It has three roots, parasympathetic motor, sympathetic and sensory: only the parasympathetic fibres relay in the ganglion (see Fig. 33.7). The parasympathetic fibres arise from cell bodies in the inferior salivatory nucleus and travel in the lesser petrosal branch of the glossopharyngeal nerve. The lesser petrosal nerve runs intracranially in the middle cranial fossa on the anterior surface of the petrous temporal bone and passes through either the foramen ovale or the sphenopetrosal fissure or the innominate canal of Arnold (a canal in the greater wing of the sphenoid close to the foramen spinosum), to join the otic ganglion where it synapses. Postganglionic fibres pass by a communicating branch to the auriculotemporal nerve to reach the parotid gland. The sympathetic root arises from a plexus on the middle meningeal artery. It contains postganglionic vasomotor fibres from the superior cervical sympathetic ganglion that pass through the otic ganglion and join the parasympathetic fibres to travel via the auriculotemporal nerve to the parotid gland. Sensory fibres from the parotid gland are derived from the auriculotemporal nerve. Clinical observations suggest that in humans the parotid gland also receives secretomotor parasympathetic fibres through the chorda tympani.

Branches

The otic ganglion is connected by branches to the chorda tympani nerve and the nerve of the pterygoid canal. These branches may form an additional pathway by which gustatory fibres from the anterior two-thirds of the tongue reach the geniculate ganglion without passing through the middle ear: they do not synapse in the otic ganglion. Motor branches to tensor veli palatini and tensor tympani, derived from the nerve to medial pterygoid, pass through the ganglion without synapsing. (For further reading, see Senger et al (2014).)

Ciliary ganglion

The ciliary ganglion is a parasympathetic ganglion concerned with the innervation of the ciliary muscle and sphincter pupillae. It is a small, flat, reddish-grey swelling, 1–2 mm in diameter, connected to the nasociliary nerve, and located near the apex of the orbit in loose fat approximately 1 cm in front of the medial end of the superior orbital fissure. It lies between the optic nerve and lateral rectus, usually lateral to the ophthalmic artery. Its neurones, which are multipolar, are larger than those found in typical autonomic ganglia; a very small number of more typical neurones are also present.

Its connections or roots (motor, sensory and sympathetic) enter or leave the ganglion posteriorly (see Fig. 44.18). Eight to ten delicate filaments, termed the short ciliary nerves, emerge anteriorly from the ganglion, arranged in two or three bundles, the lower being larger. They run forwards sinuously with the ciliary arteries, above and below the optic nerve, and divide into 15–20 branches that pierce the sclera around the optic nerve and run in small grooves on the internal scleral surface. They convey parasympathetic, sympathetic and sensory fibres between the eyeball and the ciliary ganglion; only the parasympathetic fibres synapse in the ganglion.

The parasympathetic root, derived from the branch of the oculomotor nerve to the inferior oblique, consists of preganglionic fibres from the Edinger–Westphal nucleus, which relay in the ganglion. Postganglionic fibres travel in the short ciliary nerves to the sphincter pupillae and ciliary muscle. More than 95% of these fibres supply the ciliary muscle, which is much the larger muscle in volume.

The sympathetic root contains fibres from the plexus around the internal carotid artery within the cavernous sinus. These postganglionic fibres, derived from the superior cervical ganglion, form a fine branch that enters the orbit through the superior orbital fissure inside the common tendinous ring. The fibres may pass directly to the ganglion, or may join the nasociliary nerve and travel to the ganglion in its sensory root; either way, they traverse the ganglion without synapsing to emerge into the short ciliary nerves and are distributed to the blood vessels of the eyeball. Sympathetic fibres innervating dilator pupillae may sometimes travel via the short ciliary nerves (rather than the more usual route via the ophthalmic, nasociliary and long ciliary nerves).

The sensory fibres that pass through the ciliary ganglion are derived from the nasociliary nerve. They enter the short ciliary nerves and carry sensation from the cornea, the ciliary body and the iris.

Pterygopalatine ganglion

The pterygopalatine ganglion, known colloquially as the ‘ganglion of hay fever’, is the largest of the peripheral parasympathetic ganglia, and is well protected, deep in the pterygopalatine fossa. Immediately anterior to the pterygoid canal, the ganglion lies below and medial to the foramen rotundum and the maxillary nerve and lateral to the sphenopalatine foramen (see Fig. 38.30B). It is flattened and reddish-grey in colour and lies just below the maxillary nerve as it crosses the pterygopalatine fossa. The majority of the ‘branches’ of the ganglion are connected with it morphologically but not functionally, because they are primarily sensory branches of the maxillary nerve and so pass through the ganglion without synapsing to enter the ganglionic branches of the maxillary nerve.

The deep petrosal nerve (postganglionic sympathetic fibres) and the greater petrosal nerve (preganglionic parasympathetic fibres) converge to form the nerve of the pterygoid canal (the Vidian nerve in the Vidian canal). This nerve is an important landmark to the petrous portion of the internal carotid artery, and rarely can be transected to treat intractable rhinorrhoea. The pterygoid canal enters the pterygopalatine fossa, where the nerve of the pterygoid canal joins the pterygopalatine ganglion posteriorly and the parasympathetic fibres synapse on postganglionic neurones.

Some postganglionic parasympathetic fibres may join the maxillary nerve via a ganglionic branch and then travel via its zygomatic and zygomaticotemporal branches to the lacrimal gland, but most are thought to travel by orbital branches to the gland. The parasympathetic supply to the preocular part of the central artery of the retina is believed to be derived mainly from the pterygopalatine ganglion and is vasodilatory. Preganglionic secretomotor fibres of uncertain origin also travel in the nerve of the pterygoid canal and synapse in the pterygopalatine ganglion: postganglionic fibres are distributed to palatine, pharyngeal and nasal mucous glands via palatine and nasal branches of the maxillary nerve.

Postganglionic sympathetic fibres pass through the ganglion without synapsing. They arise in the superior cervical ganglion and travel via the internal carotid plexus and deep petrosal nerve to enter the pterygopalatine ganglion within the nerve of the pterygoid canal: they supply blood vessels and orbitalis. General sensory fibres destined for distribution via orbital, nasopalatine, superior alveolar, palatine and pharyngeal branches of the maxillary division of the trigeminal nerve also run through the ganglion without synapsing.

Orbital branches of the pterygopalatine ganglion

Several rami orbitales arise dorsally from the pterygopalatine ganglion and enter the orbit through the inferior orbital fissure. Branches leave the orbit through the posterior ethmoidal air sinus. There is strong experimental evidence from animal studies that postganglionic parasympathetic branches pass directly to the lacrimal gland, ophthalmic artery and choroid.

Lacrimation reflex

The lacrimal gland is innervated by secretomotor postganglionic parasympathetic fibres from the pterygopalatine ganglion. They reach the gland either via zygomatic and lacrimal branches of the maxillary nerve, or by passing directly from the ganglion ([Ruskell 2004]). Postganglionic sympathetic fibres from the superior cervical ganglion supply the lacrimal gland and may be involved in the regulation of blood flow and the modulation of gland secretion ([Dartt 2009]). The lacrimation reflex produces a significant increase in tear volume and is elicited by thermal, mechanical or chemical stimulation of polymodal nociceptors in the conjunctiva and cornea (Situ and Simpson 2010). The afferent limb of the reflex involves branches of the ophthalmic nerve, with an additional contribution from the infraorbital nerve if the conjunctiva of the lower eyelid is involved. Corneal afferents travelling in these nerves terminate in the nucleus of the spinal tract of the trigeminal nerve: experimental tract tracing studies in animals have implicated the transition between the trigeminal subnuclei caudalis and interpolaris as an important area that projects to preganglionic parasympathetic neurones lying close to or within the superior salivatory nucleus and to the facial motor nucleus, both regions involved in the efferent limb of the blinking reflex (Meng and Kurose 2013). The neural mechanism for controlling and maintaining basal tear production is less clear. Lacrimation may also occur in response to emotional triggers without any irritation of ocular structures, when it may be accompanied by alterations in the mimetic facial muscles, vocalizations and sobbing (Gračanin et al 2014): emotional lacrimation is thought to be mediated by limbic projections to the superior salivatory nucleus.

Submandibular ganglion

The submandibular ganglion is a small, fusiform body that lies on the upper part of hyoglossus, superior to the deep part of the submandibular gland and inferior to the lingual nerve, to which it is connected by several filaments. The posterior filament is the motor, parasympathetic root that conveys preganglionic fibres from the superior salivatory nucleus in the brainstem via the facial, chorda tympani and lingual nerves to the ganglion, where they synapse. Five or six postganglionic secretomotor branches from the ganglion supply the submandibular gland and its duct, and the sublingual and anterior lingual glands, by travelling either through the anterior filaments that connect the submandibular gland to the lingual nerve or along adjacent blood vessels to their targets. Neuronal cell bodies and small ganglia have been described in the interlobular connective tissue stroma of human submandibular ganglia, close to salivary parenchymal cells and blood vessels (Tosios et al 2010). The sympathetic root is derived from the plexus on the facial artery and consists of postganglionic fibres from the superior cervical ganglion that traverse the submandibular ganglion without synapsing. These fibres are vasomotor to the blood vessels of the submandibular and sublingual glands. Sensory fibres derived from the lingual nerve may also pass through the ganglion.

Parasympathetic components of the vagus nerve

Preganglionic parasympathetic axons destined for the thoracic viscera travel in the pulmonary, cardiac and oesophageal branches of the vagus nerve (see Fig. 56.7) and synapse in minute ganglia in the walls of the target viscera. Axons travelling in cardiac branches join the cardiac plexuses and synapse in ganglia distributed over both atria, the interatrial septum and perinodal subepicardial tissue: when stimulated, they normally slow the cardiac cycle and constrict coronary arteries, although low-level stimulation may increase heart rate. Pulmonary branches contain axons that synapse in ganglia of the pulmonary plexuses: they are motor (bronchoconstrictor) to the circular non-striated muscle fibres of the bronchi and bronchioles, and secretomotor to the mucous glands of the respiratory epithelium.

The parasympathetic neurones that innervate viscera in the abdomen and pelvis lie either in the dorsal nucleus of the vagus nerve or in the intermediolateral grey matter of the second, third and fourth sacral spinal cord segments. The vagus supplies preganglionic parasympathetic innervation to the abdominal viscera as far as the distal transverse colon, i.e. it supplies derivatives of the foregut and midgut. Derivatives of the hindgut are supplied by parasympathetic fibres travelling via the pelvic splanchnic nerves; the overlap between these two supplies is variable. The vagal trunks are derived from the oesophageal plexus and enter the abdomen via the oesophageal hiatus, closely related to the anterior and posterior walls of the abdominal part of the oesophagus (see Fig. 56.6). The anterior vagal trunk is mostly derived from the left vagus and the posterior vagal trunk from the right vagus. The nerves supply the abdominal part of the oesophagus and stomach directly. The anterior vagal trunk gives off a hepatic branch, which innervates the liver and its vasculature, including the gallbladder and bile ducts, and the other structures in the free edge of the lesser omentum (hepatoduodenal ligament). The posterior vagal trunk supplies branches to the coeliac plexus and these fibres frequently constitute the largest portion of the fibres that contribute to the plexus. They arise directly from the posterior vagal trunk and from its gastric branch, and run beneath the peritoneum, deep to the posterior wall of the superior part of the omental bursa, to reach the coeliac plexus. Their synaptic relays with postganglionic neurones are situated in the myenteric (Auerbach’s) and submucosal (Meissner’s) plexuses in the wall of the hollow viscera.

Pelvic splanchnic nerves

Pelvic splanchnic nerves (nervi erigentes) travel in the ventral rami of the second, third and fourth sacral spinal nerves. They leave the nerves as they exit the anterior sacral foramina and pass in the presacral tissue as a fine network of branches distributed to three principal destinations. Most pass anterolaterally into the inferior hypogastric plexus (see below). Some join the hypogastric nerves and ascend out of the pelvis as far as the superior hypogastric plexus, from where they are distributed with branches of the inferior mesenteric artery. A few run superolaterally in the presacral fascia, over the linea terminalis anterior to the left iliac vessels, and pass directly into the tissue of the retroperitoneum toward the sigmoid and descending colons. The pelvic splanchnic nerves are motor to the smooth muscle of the derivatives of the hindgut and the wall of the urinary bladder, are vasodilator to the erectile tissues of the penis and clitoris, and are secretomotor to the derivatives of the hindgut.

An experimental study of the differential expression of transcription factors in embryonic mice has argued that thoracic and sacral pools of preganglionic neurones share a common sympathetic identity and that the sacral autonomic outflow should therefore be regarded as sympathetic (Espinosa-Medina et al 2016). This controversial view has been challenged ([Horn 2018]).

Autonomic Plexuses

The autonomic nervous system in the thorax consists of the right and left sympathetic trunks and left and right vagus nerves, and the cardiac, oesophageal and pulmonary plexuses (see Figs 56.6–56.7). The autonomic supply to the abdominal and pelvic viscera is via the abdominopelvic part of the sympathetic trunk and the greater, lesser and least splanchnic nerves (sympathetic), and the vagus and pelvic splanchnic nerves (parasympathetic).

The somata of preganglionic sympathetic neurones are located in the intermediolateral grey matter (lamina VII) of the thoracolumbar segments of the spinal cord; those destined for the smooth muscle of the wall of the hollow viscera mostly pass through the sympathetic trunk without synapsing and relay in prevertebral ganglia (coeliac, mesenteric and pelvic). Postganglionic sympathetic fibres are distributed with the branches of the coeliac trunk and mesenteric arteries to three principal targets: the myenteric and submucosal ganglia (causing inhibition); blood vessels (inducing vasoconstriction); and sphincter muscles (inducing contraction). The neuronal somata of preganglionic parasympathetic axons are found in the dorsal nucleus of the vagus nerve in the medulla oblongata and in the second to fourth sacral segments of the spinal cord. Their main targets in the wall of the hollow viscera are the enteric neurones of the myenteric plexus. The vagus nerve plays a major role in oesophageal propulsion, gastric acid secretion and emptying of the stomach, gallbladder contraction and pancreatic exocrine secretion. Pelvic splanchnic nerves innervate the distal colon and rectum.

There are numerous interconnections between plexuses and ganglia, particularly in the major plexuses around the abdominal aorta and therefore descriptions, as here, are simplifications based on the ‘main’ supply to each organ (see Fig. 59.2).

Thoracic plexuses

Cardiac plexus

The cardiac plexus has a superficial component inferior to the aortic arch, lying between the arch and the pulmonary trunk, and a deep part between the aortic arch and tracheal bifurcation (see Fig. 57.61). The plexus has coronary, pulmonary, atrial and aortic extensions. The superficial (ventral) part is formed by the cardiac branch of the left superior cervical sympathetic ganglion and the inferior of the two cervical cardiac branches of the left vagus nerve. The deep (dorsal) part is formed by the cardiac branches of the cervical and upper thoracic sympathetic ganglia and of the vagus and recurrent laryngeal nerves. The only cardiac nerves that do not join it are those that join the superficial part of the plexus. Branches from the cardiac plexuses subsequently form the left and right coronary and atrial plexuses.

Pulmonary plexus

The autonomic nervous system (either by direct axonal innervation or circulating neurotransmitter) controls many aspects of airway function, including regulation of airway smooth muscle tone, mucus secretion from submucosal glands and surface epithelial goblet cells, vascular permeability and blood flow ([Belvisi 2002]). The trachea and bronchi are innervated by branches of the vagus nerves, recurrent laryngeal nerves and sympathetic trunks via the anterior and posterior pulmonary plexuses. The plexuses are interconnected and lie anterior and posterior to the structures of the lung root and hilum (see Figs 56.6–56.7, 57.61). The posterior plexus provides the majority of the autonomic innervation to the lung and is formed by approximately 12 (8–18) branches from the vagus nerve (Weijs et al 2015) and cardiac branches from the second to fifth (or sixth) thoracic sympathetic ganglia. The smaller anterior plexus is formed by 3 (2–4) branches of the vagus nerve and cervical sympathetic cardiac nerves via the superficial and deep parts of the cardiac plexus. Branches of the recurrent laryngeal nerves form a plexus on the membranous posterior wall of the trachea; the plexus primarily innervates the trachea and proximal parts of the main bronchi, with branches to the oesophagus.

Efferent preganglionic parasympathetic nerves from the vagus nerve synapse on small ganglia within the walls of the tracheobronchial tree, likely acting as sites of integration and/or modulation of the input from extrinsic nerves or permitting local control of aspects of airway function by local reflex mechanisms. The predominant contractile innervation of airway smooth muscle is parasympathetic cholinergic, while the primary relaxant innervation of the airways is non-cholinergic (parasympathetic nerves containing nitric oxide synthase and vasoactive intestinal peptide). These parasympathetic nerves are anatomically and physiologically distinct from one another and differentially regulated by reflexes. Stimulation of cholinergic nerves also results in mucus secretion and bronchial vasodilation. Sympathetic-adrenergic nerves play little, if any, role in directly regulating smooth muscle tone in the human airways, although they may control constriction of tracheobronchial blood vessels. Circulating noradrenaline (norepinephrine) can bring about bronchodilation through activation of β-adrenergic receptors in the airways. Extrapulmonary afferents may modulate neurally mediated regulation of airway smooth muscle tone (Canning and Fischer 2001). Vagal innervation is involved in the cough reflex, mucous production and control of bronchial diameter; inadvertent transection of the pulmonary vagal nerves during oesophagectomy may be related to the high incidence of postoperative pneumonia and pulmonary complications following oesophagectomy (Weijs et al 2017); preservation of vagal pulmonary branches is therefore desirable (Weijs et al 2016).

Oesophageal plexus

The oesophageal plexus surrounds the oesophagus below the level of the hila of the lungs (see Fig. 56.6). Preganglionic parasympathetic axons from the vagus and recurrent laryngeal nerves travel to ganglia in the oesophageal wall, either directly or through the oesophageal plexus, and are motor to the smooth muscle in the lower oesophagus and secretomotor to mucous glands in the oesophageal mucosa. Vasomotor sympathetic axons arise from the first to sixth (sometimes fewer) thoracic segments of the spinal cord. Those passing from the more superior cord segments often synapse in the middle and inferior cervical sympathetic ganglia; their postganglionic axons are vasomotor to the vessels of the cervical and superior part of the thoracic oesophagus. Preganglionic axons from the fifth or sixth thoracic spinal cord segments pass directly to the oesophageal plexus or to the coeliac ganglion, where they synapse; postganglionic axons innervate the vessels of the distal oesophagus.

Abdominopelvic autonomic plexuses and ganglia

The abdominopelvic autonomic plexuses are somewhat variable and often fuse or are closely interrelated. The following descriptions encompass their main features (see Figs 59.3–59.4, 73.8).

Coeliac plexus

The coeliac plexus is located at the level of the twelfth thoracic and first lumbar vertebrae. It is a dense network that unites the coeliac ganglia, and surrounds the coeliac trunk and the proximal superior mesenteric artery. It is posterior to the stomach and omental bursa and anterior to the crura of the respiratory diaphragm and the beginning of the abdominal aorta, and lies medial to the suprarenal glands. The plexus and ganglia receive the greater and lesser splanchnic nerves and branches from the vagal trunks. The plexus is in continuity with small branches along adjacent arteries and is connected to the phrenic, splenic, hepatic, superior mesenteric, suprarenal, renal and ovarian/testicular plexuses. Visceral afferent fibres in the coeliac plexus convey pain and other sensations from proximal abdominal viscera. Anaesthesia or ablation of these nerves (coeliac plexus blockade) is sometimes undertaken to treat medically intractable pain from pancreatic disorders.

Coeliac and aorticorenal ganglia

The coeliac ganglia are irregular neural masses, measuring approximately 2 cm across, located between the origin of the coeliac trunk and superior mesenteric artery, medial to the suprarenal glands and anterior to the crura of the respiratory diaphragm (Zhang et al 2006). They vary in number, size, shape and precise location; there are often two, one on each side. The right ganglion is frequently posterior to the inferior vena cava, and the left ganglion often lies posterior to the origin of the splenic artery. The ipsilateral greater splanchnic nerve joins the superior part of each ganglion and the lesser splanchnic nerve joins the inferior part. The most inferior part of each ganglion usually forms a distinct subdivision, the aorticorenal ganglion, which receives the ipsilateral lesser splanchnic nerve and gives origin to most of the renal plexus.

Phrenic plexus

The phrenic plexus is a periarterial extension of the coeliac plexus around the right inferior phrenic artery, adjacent to the right crus of the respiratory diaphragm ([Rusu 2006]). It contains one or two phrenic ganglia and a definable nerve trunk that connects the coeliac plexus and phrenic nerve: the phrenic ganglion is probably sympathetic (Tubbs et al 2008). The phrenic plexus supplies branches to the suprarenal glands and the respiratory diaphragm.

Superior mesenteric plexus and ganglion

The superior mesenteric plexus lies in the pre-aortic connective tissue posterior to the pancreas, around the origin of the superior mesenteric artery. It is an inferior continuation of the coeliac plexus and includes branches from the posterior vagal trunk and coeliac plexus. Its branches accompany the superior mesenteric artery and its branches. The superior mesenteric ganglion lies superiorly in the plexus, usually above the origin of the superior mesenteric artery.

Intermesenteric plexus

Like other parts of the abdominal aortic autonomic plexus, the intermesenteric plexus is not a discrete structure but is part of a continuous periarterial nerve plexus connected to the ovarian/testicular, inferior mesenteric, iliac and superior hypogastric plexuses. It lies on the lateral and anterior aspects of the aorta, between the origins of the superior and inferior mesenteric arteries, and consists of numerous fine, interconnected nerve fibres and a few ganglia continuous superiorly with the superior mesenteric plexus and inferiorly with the superior hypogastric plexus. It is not well characterized but receives parasympathetic and sympathetic branches from the coeliac plexus and additional sympathetic contributions from the first and second lumbar splanchnic nerves.

Inferior mesenteric plexus

The inferior mesenteric plexus lies around the origin of the inferior mesenteric artery and is distributed along its branches. It is formed predominantly from the aortic plexus, supplemented by sympathetic fibres from the first and second lumbar splanchnic nerves and ascending pelvic parasympathetic fibres from the inferior hypogastric plexus (via the hypogastric nerves and superior hypogastric plexus). Disruption of the inferior mesenteric plexus alone rarely causes clinically significant disturbances of autonomic function.

Superior hypogastric plexus

The superior hypogastric plexus lies anterior to the aortic bifurcation, the left common iliac vein, median sacral vessels, fifth lumbar vertebral body and sacral promontory, and between the common iliac arteries. It lies within extraperitoneal connective tissue in the midline, extending a little to the left. The breadth of the plexus and its constituent nerves varies; appearances range from a reticular-like arrangement to a band-like structure or one or two distinct nerve trunks (Paraskevas et al 2008). The medial attachment of the sigmoid mesocolon and superior limit of the mesorectum lie anterior to the distal part of the plexus, separated from it by a thin layer of loose connective tissue. The plexus is formed by branches from three main sources: the abdominal aortic plexus (sympathetic and parasympathetic), lumbar splanchnic nerves (sympathetic) and pelvic splanchnic nerves (parasympathetic), which ascend from the inferior hypogastric plexus via the right and left hypogastric nerves (Kraima et al 2015). Visceral sensory fibres also pass through the plexus. The hypogastric nerves lie in loose connective tissue just posterolateral to the proximal mesorectum and pass over the linea terminalis medial to the internal iliac vessels. The superior hypogastric plexus conveys branches to the inferior mesenteric plexus and to the ureteric, ovarian/testicular and common iliac nerve plexuses; additional small branches turn abruptly forwards into the proximal mesorectum to travel with the superior anorectal artery.

Inferior hypogastric plexus

The inferior hypogastric plexus lies in the thin extraperitoneal connective tissue on the pelvic side wall anterolateral to the mesorectum. The internal iliac vessels and the attachments of levator ani and obturator internus lie laterally, and the superior vesical and occluded part of the umbilical arteries superiorly. In males, the inferior hypogastric plexus lies posterolaterally, on each side of the seminal glands, prostate and the fundus of the urinary bladder: the point where the ductus deferens crosses the ureter provides an approximate guide to the superior limit of the plexus (Mauroy et al 2003). The proximal border of the plexus lies beneath the peritoneum of the rectovesical pouch and is in contact with the lateral aspect of the fundus of the urinary bladder. The anterior border reaches the posterior aspect of the prostate; at its inferior limit, the cavernous nerves of the penis pass forwards to reach the posterolateral aspect of the prostate (see Fig. 73.8). In females, each plexus lies lateral to the cervix of the uterus, vaginal fornix and the fundus of the urinary bladder, often extending into the broad ligament of the uterus; the proximal limit of the plexus corresponds approximately to the level where the uterine artery crosses the ureter (Azaïs et al 2013).

The inferior hypogastric plexus is formed mainly from pelvic splanchnic (parasympathetic) and sacral splanchnic (sympathetic) branches; a smaller contribution is derived from sympathetic fibres (from the inferior lumbar ganglia) that descend into the plexus from the superior hypogastric plexus via the hypogastric nerves. It gives origin to a complex network of small pelvic branches that supply the pelvic viscera either directly or indirectly via periarterial plexuses. The branches of the inferior hypogastric plexus supply the ductus deferens, seminal glands, prostate, bulbo-urethral glands and penis in males; the ovary, uterine tubes, uterus, cervix of the uterus and vagina in females; and the urinary bladder and distal ureter in both sexes. The plexus plays a key role in continence and sexual function.

Hypogastric nerves

The hypogastric nerves are usually paired nerve bundles but can consist instead of multiple filaments. They contain sympathetic fibres (mostly descending from the superior hypogastric plexus) and parasympathetic fibres (ascending from the inferior hypogastric plexus). The nerves run between the superior and inferior hypogastric plexuses on each side posterior to the presacral fascia, medial to the internal iliac vessels, and lateral to the anterior sacral foramina.

Other autonomic plexuses and ganglia

Additional plexuses are described for abdominopelvic viscera, such as the hepatic and ovarian/testicular plexuses. Each plexus tends to lie around the main arterial supply to the named organ, receive both sympathetic and parasympathetic fibres from one or more of the major autonomic plexuses, and contain at least one ganglion. For example, autonomic ganglia supplying the testis are found around the origin of the testicular arteries from the abdominal aorta and have connections with the renal and intermesenteric plexuses and the first and second lumbar splanchnic nerves (Motoc et al 2010).

Enteric Nervous System

The walls of the hollow viscera are densely innervated by both the enteric nervous system (intrinsic control) and the autonomic nervous system (extrinsic control). The latter is not essential for function, as evidenced by intestinal activity after transplantation of the extrinsically denervated part of the gastrointestinal tract. In contrast, neuropathies affecting the enteric nervous system, such as Hirschsprung’s disease, are potentially life-threatening. For a detailed description of the enteric nervous system, see Furness et al (2014).

Intrinsic innervation

The intrinsic innervation of the gastrointestinal tract is derived from enteric neurones distributed throughout its wall in thousands of small ganglia, each consisting of neuronal cell bodies supported by enteric glial cells; it is estimated that there are between 200 and 600 million neurones in the human enteric nervous system. Enteric neurones are derived from neural crest cells and innervate the hollow viscera from oesophagus to anus, together with the pancreas and bile ducts.

Most of the enteric neurones in the wall of the gastrointestinal tract are found in two ganglionated plexuses (see Fig. 59.9). The most extensive of these is the myenteric (Auerbach’s) plexus, which consists of a network of nerve fibres and small ganglia lying between the circular and longitudinal layers of the muscularis externa. It runs in continuity from the oesophagus to the anus. The submucosal (Meissner’s) plexus has outer and inner components and is present throughout the intestines but is absent or minimal in the oesophagus and stomach (Nagy and Goldstein 2017). Interconnecting, non-ganglionated nerve plexuses lie at various levels in the wall of the gastrointestinal tract, including the lamina propria (mucosal plexus); at the interface between the submucosa and muscularis externa; between the circular and longitudinal muscles (the non-ganglionated part of the myenteric plexus); and within the serosa.

Individual enteric neurones function in one of several ways: as afferent (sensory) nerves responding to mechanical and chemical stimuli; as efferent (motor) nerves innervating epithelial cells (influencing absorption, secretion and/or the release of hormones), smooth muscle (excitatory or inhibitory), arterioles (vasoconstriction or vasodilatation) and lymphoid tissue; or as interneurones that relay and integrate signals. Collectively, they are involved in a hierarchy of enteric reflexes that include local reflexes within the wall of the hollow viscera; reflexes mediated through prevertebral ganglia; and reflexes mediated through the central nervous system (the gut–brain axis). The functions of enteric neurones can be further modulated by local environmental factors, e.g. enteric glia, gut microbiota and feeding state, and by general factors in the host, e.g. the immune system, stress and disease (Brierley and Linden 2014). Pathological states become manifest by abnormal secretion, impaired absorption, disordered gastrointestinal motility and pain.

Intracranial and intratemporal course

The facial nerve has intracranial (cisternal), intratemporal and extratemporal portions. The intratemporal portion is further divided into meatal, labyrinthine, tympanic (horizontal) and mastoid (vertical) segments (see Fig. 42.12). The cisternal portion emerges from the ventrolateral aspect of the caudal border of the pons. The meatal portion enters the porus acusticus of the internal acoustic meatus accompanied by the nervus intermedius, the vestibulocochlear nerve and the labyrinthine vessels. In this part of its course, the facial nerve lacks a fibrous sheath or endoneurium and is surrounded by a thin layer of arachnoid. The motor root, which supplies the muscles of the face, and the nervus intermedius, which contains sensory fibres concerned with the perception of taste and parasympathetic (secretomotor) fibres to various glands, are still separate components; they usually merge within the meatus. The labyrinthine segment runs from the fundus of the internal acoustic meatus to the geniculate ganglion, where the nerve makes the first bend or genu (see Fig. 42.12). The labyrinthine segment is the shortest and narrowest part of the facial nerve; its lack of anastomosing arterial cascades renders it susceptible to vascular compression. The tympanic part initially curves around the oval window niche, then lies just anterior and inferior to the lateral semicircular canal and bends again at the second genu to become the vertical or mastoid part. The mastoid part is the longest of the petrous segments and runs from the pyramidal process to the stylomastoid foramen. The tympanic and mastoid segments of the facial nerve are supplied by the facial arch, formed by the petrosal branch of the middle meningeal artery and the stylomastoid branch of the posterior auricular artery.

The branches that arise from the facial nerve within the temporal bone can be divided into those that come from the geniculate ganglion (greater petrosal nerve) and those that arise within the facial canal (nerve to stapedius and chorda tympani).

Greater petrosal nerve

The greater (superficial) petrosal nerve, a branch of the nervus intermedius, is the main branch from the geniculate ganglion. It passes anteriorly, receives a branch from the tympanic plexus and traverses a hiatus on the anterior surface of the petrous part of the temporal bone. It enters the middle cranial fossa, runs forwards in a groove on the bone above the lesser petrosal nerve, and then passes beneath the trigeminal ganglion to reach the foramen lacerum. Here it is joined by the deep petrosal nerve from the internal carotid sympathetic plexus, to become the nerve of the pterygoid canal (Vidian nerve). The greater petrosal nerve contains parasympathetic fibres destined for the pterygopalatine ganglion, and taste fibres from the palate. The geniculate ganglion also communicates with the lesser petrosal nerve.

Nerve to stapedius

The nerve to stapedius arises from the facial nerve in the facial nerve canal behind the pyramidal eminence of the posterior wall of the tympanic cavity and passes forwards through a small canal to reach the muscle.

Chorda tympani

The chorda tympani (see Figs 42.11, 42.12) leaves the facial nerve some 6 mm above the stylomastoid foramen and runs anterosuperiorly in a canal to enter the tympanic cavity via the posterior canaliculus. It then curves anteriorly in the substance of the tympanic membrane between its mucous and fibrous layers, and crosses medial to the upper part of the handle of the malleus to the anterior wall of the tympanic cavity, where it enters the anterior canaliculus. It exits the skull and enters the infratemporal fossa by passing through the medial end of the petrotympanic fissure posterior to the capsule of the temporomandibular joint. It next descends medial to the spine of the sphenoid bone, which it sometimes grooves, lying posterolateral to tensor veli palatini. It is crossed medially by the middle meningeal artery, the roots of the auriculotemporal nerve and the inferior alveolar nerve (see Fig. 38.23) and joins the posterior aspect of the lingual nerve at an acute angle. The chorda tympani carries taste fibres from the anterior two-thirds of the tongue (but not the from the circumvallate papillae) and efferent preganglionic parasympathetic secretomotor fibres destined for the submandibular ganglion in the floor of the mouth.

Dehiscences of the facial nerve canal

The facial nerve may be somewhat variable in its anatomical course through the temporal bone (Proctor and Nager 1982, [Proctor 1991]). It may split into two or three strands, starting at the geniculate ganglion, and then make its way across the promontory to the stylomastoid foramen, or pass a few millimetres posteriorly to its second genu, before it turns inferiorly posterior to the fossa incudis, a position where it is particularly vulnerable during surgical exploration of the mastoid antrum. The more proximal the division into strands, the more bizarre is the subsequent course. More distal bifurcations pass either side of the fenestra vestibuli. It may be dehiscent, particularly in its second part, when it occasionally overhangs the stapes, or run inferior to the stapedial superstructure, a position that renders it vulnerable during surgery to the stapes (Barnes et al 2001). The motor fibres to the face may be carried through the chorda tympani, which is then enlarged. When this is the case, the distal facial nerve dwindles to a fibrous strand in a narrowed stylomastoid foramen. In chronic bone disease in the tympanic cavity, the facial nerve may be exposed in its canal. Inflammation may lead to facial paralysis of the infranuclear or lower motor neurone type.

Extratemporal course

The facial nerve emerges from the base of the skull at the stylomastoid foramen and almost immediately gives off the nerves to the posterior belly of digastric and stylohyoid and the posterior auricular nerve, which supplies the occipital belly of occipitofrontalis and some of the intrinsic auricular muscles (see Fig. 36.23). The nerve next enters the parotid gland high up on its posteromedial surface and passes forwards and downwards behind the mandibular ramus. Within the substance of the gland, it branches into superior (temporofacial) and inferior (cervicofacial) trunks, usually just behind and superficial to the retromandibular vein. The trunks branch further to form a parotid plexus (pes anserinus). Five main terminal branches arise from the plexus, diverge within the gland and leave by its anteromedial surface, medial to its anterior margin, to supply the muscles of facial expression (see Fig. 36.23). Six distinctive anastomotic patterns were originally classified by Davis et al (1956) and these are illustrated in Fig. 36.24. Numerous microdissection studies have demonstrated considerable individual variation in branching patterns and anastomoses between branches, both within the parotid and on the face (e.g. Lineaweaver et al 1997, Kwak et al 2004): the account that follows is therefore an overview. In surgical terms, these anastomoses are important and presumably explain why accidental or deliberate division of a small branch often fails to result in the expected facial nerve weakness.

The temporal branch usually divides into anterior and posterior rami soon after piercing the parotidomasseteric fascia below the zygomatic arch; there is often a middle (frontal) ramus. These rami cross the arch in subcutaneous tissue, lying in the subgaleal space: their course is extremely variable.

Twigs supply intrinsic muscles on the lateral surface of the auricle and the anterior and superior auricular muscles. They communicate with the zygomaticotemporal branch of the maxillary nerve and the auriculotemporal branch of the mandibular nerve. The more anterior branches supply the frontal belly of occipitofrontalis, orbicularis oculi and corrugator and join the supraorbital and lacrimal branches of the ophthalmic nerve.

Zygomatic branches

Zygomatic branches are generally multiple. They cross the zygomatic bone to the lateral canthus of the eye and supply orbicularis oculi and may also supply muscles innervated by the buccal branch. Twigs communicate with filaments of the lacrimal nerve and the zygomaticofacial branch of the maxillary nerve.

Buccal nerve

The buccal branch of the facial nerve is usually single. It has a close relationship to the parotid duct for about 2.5 cm after emerging from the parotid gland and typically lies below the duct. Superficial branches run beneath the subcutaneous fat and the superficial musculo-aponeurotic system (SMAS). Some branches pass deep to procerus and join the infratrochlear and external nasal nerves. Upper deep branches supply zygomaticus major and levator labii superioris and form an infraorbital plexus with the superior labial branches of the infraorbital nerve. They also supply levator anguli oris, zygomaticus minor, levator labii superioris alaeque nasi and the small nasal muscles (these branches are sometimes described as lower zygomatic branches). Lower deep branches supply buccinator and orbicularis oris and communicate with filaments of the buccal branch of the mandibular nerve.

Marginal mandibular nerve

There are usually two marginal mandibular nerves. They run forwards towards the angle of the mandible under platysma, and then turn upwards across the body of the mandible to pass under depressor anguli oris. The branches supply risorius and the muscles of the lower lip and chin. Filaments communicate with the mental nerve. The marginal mandibular branch has an important surgical relationship with the inferior border of the mandible.

Cutaneous branches

Cutaneous branches of the facial nerve accompany the auricular branch of the vagus and probably supply small areas on both aspects of the auricle, in the depression of the concha and over its eminence.

The facial nerve has intra- or extracranial connections with the cutaneous branches of all three divisions of the trigeminal nerve (including branches of the auriculotemporal, buccal, mental, lingual, infraorbital, zygomatic and ophthalmic nerves); with branches of the vestibulocochlear, glossopharyngeal and vagus nerves; and with branches of the cervical plexus (including the great auricular, greater and lesser occipital and transverse cervical nerves). These cutaneous connections are significant in facilitating the perineural spread of tumours that arise either within the parotid or on the face and explains why some patients with perineural spread from cutaneous or parotid malignancies may present with vocal cord palsy.

Cervical branch

The cervical branch of the facial nerve emerges from the lower part of the parotid gland and runs anteroinferiorly under platysma to the anterior neck. Typically single, it supplies platysma and communicates with the transverse cutaneous cervical nerve.

Lesions of the facial nerve

Facial paralysis may be due to an upper motor neurone lesion (when frontalis is partially spared because of the bilateral cortical representation of the muscles of the upper part of the face) or a lower motor neurone lesion (when all branches may be involved). Lower motor neurone facial paralysis is most commonly idiopathic (Bell’s palsy). There are a large number of other recognized causes that include geniculate herpes zoster (Ramsay Hunt syndrome), and malignant tumours of the parotid gland and temporal bone. Iatrogenic damage also accounts for a significant number of palsies, most often acquired in vestibular schwannoma, parotid and middle ear or mastoid surgery.

Bell’s palsy

Bell’s palsy is an idiopathic lower motor neurone facial palsy. It may be complete or partial, and is characterized by a flaccid paralysis of the ipsilateral mimetic facial muscles (muscles of facial expression); decreased lacrimation in the ipsilateral eye (which is controlled by neurones in the greater petrosal nerve); and hyperacusis or decreased tolerance of loud noises in the ipsilateral ear as a result of paralysis of stapedius. Its cause remains the subject of speculation but is most probably a herpes virus infection (Zandian et al 2014). Magnetic resonance imaging studies suggest that there are inflammatory changes in the labyrinthine and perigeniculate segments of the facial nerve. In the vast majority of cases, spontaneous full recovery takes place after a few weeks.

Extracranial course

As the accessory nerve exits the jugular foramen, it runs posterolaterally and passes either medial or lateral to the internal jugular vein; occasionally, it may pass through the vein. The extradural part of the nerve then crosses the transverse process of the atlas and is crossed by the occipital artery before descending obliquely, medial to the styloid process, stylohyoid and the posterior belly of digastric. Running with the superior sternocleidomastoid branch of the occipital artery, it reaches the upper part of sternocleidomastoid and enters its deep surface, to form an anastomosis with fibres from C2 alone, C3 alone, or C2 and C3 (the ansa of Maubrac). It may also communicate with the ventral root of the first cervical nerve (McKenzie branch).

The accessory nerve occasionally terminates in sternocleidomastoid. More commonly it emerges, usually as one trunk, 5–10 mm cephalad to the point where the great auricular nerve winds around sternocleidomastoid, and moves from a plane posterior to the muscle to one that is anterior. The relationship between the accessory nerve and the great auricular nerve in the posterior triangle is the key to exposure of the accessory nerve: the general relations of the posterior triangle vary with individual physique, but this relation between the two nerves is reliably consistent. The accessory nerve then runs across the fatty areolar tissue at the apex of the posterior triangle, in close relation to the superior superficial cervical lymph nodes in levels Va and Vb, deep to platysma. It is separated from the underlying levator scapulae by this areolar tissue, and, more deeply, by the prevertebral fascia (see Fig. 35.7A). One slender branch passes to the upper fibres of trapezius either deep to sternocleidomastoid or just beyond it. The nerve pierces the fascia covering the deep surface of trapezius close to the anterior border of the muscle and then runs caudally about 2 cm from that border. It passes down in a characteristic sinuous fashion, accompanied by slender vessels to the deep, inner face of trapezius. A branch from the cervical plexus (third and fourth cervical ventral rami) joins the nerve just above the clavicle. Intraoperative stimulation of this branch rarely evokes a muscular response; it probably conveys afferent fibres from the middle and lower parts of trapezius. The nerve now turns medially, continuing in parallel to the spine of the scapula about 4 cm above it. At the medial end of the spine, the nerve turns caudally again, passing down parallel to the medial border of the scapula. It divides into terminal muscular branches about 7 cm distal to the scapular spine. Although sternocleidomastoid, and the middle and the lower portions of trapezius, may be partially supplied by branches from the cervical plexus, the upper part of trapezius is innervated solely by the accessory nerve.

The cervical course of the accessory nerve follows a line from the lower anterior part of the tragus to the tip of the transverse process of the atlas, and then across sternocleidomastoid and the posterior triangle to a point on the anterior border of trapezius 3–5 cm above the clavicle.

The accessory nerve is thought to provide the sole motor supply to sternocleidomastoid; the second and third cervical nerves are believed to carry proprioceptive fibres from it. The supranuclear pathway of fibres destined for sternocleidomastoid is not simple; current evidence favours bilateral hemispheric innervation, although opinion varies as to the extent of the ipsilateral input. The motor supply to the descending (upper) and transverse (middle) portions of trapezius is primarily from the accessory nerve under predominantly contralateral supranuclear control. Usually, trapezius receives an innervation from the cervical plexus, in most cases from C3 and C4 (Tubbs et al 2011). A study using intraoperative electroneurography and histochemical analyses found that, when present, the cervical fibres did not consistently innervate all three parts of the muscle (descending, transverse and ascending), and that fibres from C2 usually travelled via the accessory nerve, while fibres from C3 and C4 innervated trapezius independently (Pu et al 2008). In addition, to their motor contribution, C3 and C4 also carry proprioceptive fibres from trapezius.

On the basis of the incomplete denervation of the muscle that sometimes happens following sacrifice of both the accessory nerve and the cervical plexus, it has been suggested that trapezius receives a partial motor supply from other sources, possibly via thoracic roots. (For a detailed review of the applied surgical anatomy of the accessory nerve plexus, see [Brown (2002].)

Sensory ganglia have been described along the course of the intradural portion of the nerve.

Lesions of the accessory nerve

Lesions of the accessory nerve may be sustained centrally, at its exit from the skull or in the neck. The supranuclear fibres that influence motor neurones innervating sternocleidomastoid decussate twice; a lesion of the corticospinal system above the pons therefore produces weakness of the ipsilateral sternocleidomastoid and contralateral trapezius. Episodic contraction of sternocleidomastoid and trapezius, often accompanied by contraction of other muscle groups, e.g. splenius capitis, occurs in spasmodic torticollis, a focal dystonia. In jugular foramen syndrome, caused by pathologies including nasopharyngeal carcinoma or a jugular paraganglioma, lesions of the glossopharyngeal, vagus and accessory nerves coexist. The accessory nerve can be injured more distally in the neck by trauma or by surgical exploration in the posterior triangle, particularly at the apex of the triangle. Typically, there is immediate pain, then dropping of the shoulder and a remarkable loss of function. The average ISHA is about 50°. The pain is characteristic: often severe, deep-seated, dull, constant and boring in nature, and felt around the scapula and the posterior aspect of the neck and shoulder. The posture of the scapula is also characteristic: because of the loss of the great suspensory muscle, trapezius, the scapula drops down and away from the spinal column (see Fig. 49.37). There is often winging of the scapula, easily distinguished from that caused by paralysis of serratus anterior by the posture of the scapula (see Fig. 49.38). The nerve appears to be relatively immune to the harmful effects of delayed repair, even as late as 4 years after injury, with early relief of pain long before there is reinnervation of muscle (Camp and Birch 2011).